<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Developing 2+2+2 Pathways in Agribusiness to Meet the Needs of California?s Agriculture Industry</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pushpa Ramakrishna</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Madera Community College Center, as part of Reedley College, will undertake "Developing 2+2+2 Pathways in Agribusiness to Meet the Needs of California's Agriculture Industry". This project will develop new pathways and credentials in agribusiness education to train the next generation of farmers, leaders, and professionals. The project also aims to increase workplace diversity by recruiting under-represented students into agriculture. The State of California ranks first in the nation for agricultural production, an industry that contributes over $50 billion annually to the economy. A diverse and well-trained workforce is critical to the success of California's and the nation's agricultural industry.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will create seamless 2+2+2 pathways from high school, to two-year community college, and to four-year institutions for students interested in pursuing an education in agriculture business and related fields. Students will work towards a certificate, Associate of Science degree, and/or transfer to a four-year college and university. High school students will take college-level classes through dual enrollment pathways, thereby giving them a head start to a college education. An intensive two-week Summer Academy in Agriculture Sciences and Technology will expose students to educational and career opportunities in agriculture. Taken together these various academic pathways underpin the intellectual merit of the project and its focus on improved recruitment, retention, completion, and success through excellent classroom instruction, academic counseling, dedicated tutorial services, modified curriculum/course rotation, and internship opportunities. Finally, improved course articulation with undergraduate institutions will allow students the opportunity to transfer to four-year programs in agriculture.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1700704</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ganesan</FirstName>
<LastName>Srinivasan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ganesan.srinivasan@scccd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Samuel</FirstName>
<LastName>Rodriguez</LastName>
<EmailAddress>samuel.rodriguez@reedleycollege.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Reedley College</Name>
<CityName>Reedley</CityName>
<ZipCode>936542017</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5596383641</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>995 N. Reed St</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7412</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECH EDUCATION PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1032</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED TECHNOLOGY EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
