<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>High-Impact Introduction to the Geosciences through the Undergraduate Coral Research Initiative</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>322591</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>ICER</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Jones</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non Technical&lt;br/&gt;Many former senior military and national security officials believe global warming poses a threat to our nation?s security, both through increased flooding of coastal military installations and via increased political instability from the disruption of food production and economic systems.  Understanding the impacts of global climate change and mitigating its effects will require the concerted effort of geoscientists.  At the same time, our country faces a critical need for people with training in the geosciences to fulfill employers? need for qualified personnel.  The difficulties developing our nation?s geoscience workforce starts early, as most college students are unfamiliar with the various academic disciplines that are a part of the geosciences and the career possibilities for those with training in the geosciences.  Consequently, very few students begin college with an intention to pursue a degree or career in the geosciences.  This proposal expands and develops the pool of students pursuing careers in geosciences by providing mentored research experiences in the geosciences at the critical junction when students are most likely to be deciding their career trajectory.  By providing students at a two-year college the opportunity to receive mentorship from scientists at four-year universities and federal agencies, this program develops the STEM workforce through enhanced education in traditionally underrepresented populations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical&lt;br/&gt;Mentored research opportunities are a proven means to recruit, retain, and advance students in STEM fields, including the diverse disciplines that make up the geosciences, and mentored research therefore provides an exemplary model for developing the next generation of geoscientists.  This mentored research program, called the Undergraduate Coral Research Initiative (UCRI), builds upon the recent discovery by USGS scientists of a unique coral refuge from global warming among the shaded mangrove prop roots in Hurricane Hole, within the US Virgin Islands Coral Reef National Monument Marine Reserve.  Over the course of three years, at least fifteen students will be guided through all phases of the research process, beginning with developing science literacy skills (Phase I), followed by practical research skills in experimental design, data collection in a marine context, data analysis, and presentation of research findings (Phase II).  Students will play a central role in designing and executing experiments to address the biotic and abiotic factors that promote coral survivorship in some, but not all, parts of this mangrove habitat.  Because coral reefs are a keystone component of marine ecosystems, the work conducted by students will contribute to our understanding of, and ability to protect, coral from the stresses induced by global warming.  Finally, students will be provided a broader perspective of careers in geosciences through geology field skills training with students and faculty at a four-year university (Phase III).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1700818</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Carrigan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>matthew.carrigan@sfcollege.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Santa Fe College</Name>
<CityName>Gainesville</CityName>
<ZipCode>326066210</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3523955000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3000 NW 83rd Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
