<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Support for the "Frontiers of Attosecond and Ultra-fast X-ray Science" School</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Cronin</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides travel support for US students (students enrolled in US universities) and US postdocs (postdoctoral researchers employed at US universities) to participate in the "Frontiers of Attosecond and Ultra-fast X-ray Science" School that will be held during March 19-28, 2017 at the Ettore Majorana Foundation and Centre for Scientific Culture in Erice, Sicily, in Italy.  The school program will have lectures from international experts on attosecond science and technology.  The lectures will discuss fundamentals and applications of free electron lasers, synchrotron radiation, and ion collisions for studies of electron dynamics in atoms, molecules, nanostructures and condensed matter.  These topics are among the forefront of the scientific activities in atomic, molecular, and optical physics.  This School offers an opportunity for students and postdocs to interact with senior scientists from the United States and also from a broader international community.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The support of students and postdocs through this award makes a substantial contribution to the education and training of future scientists. Students and postdocs with a background in attosecond and ultrafast x-ray science acquire a broad range of knowledge and skills that enable them to contribute to progress in many areas of science and technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/23/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1700216</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Louis</FirstName>
<LastName>DiMauro</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dimauro@mps.ohio-state.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ohio State University</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432101016</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6146888735</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1241</Code>
<Text>AMO Experiment/Atomic, Molecul</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
