<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference in Formal Power Series and Algebraic Combinatorics</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>69984</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomek Bartoszynski</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will provide support for US participants, especially women, graduate students, postdocs, and junior faculty, to attend the twenty-ninth and thirtieth international conferences in Formal Power Series and Algebraic Combinatorics (FPSAC). The 2017 edition will be held in London, United Kingdom, on July 9-13, 2017 (more info on the website https://sites.google.com/site/fpsac2017/). The 2018 edition will be held in Vancouver, Canada, on July 16-20, 2018 (more info on the website http://fpsac.org). The most important annual conference series in algebraic combinatorics in the world, FPSAC offers young American researchers a unique opportunity to interact closely with top mathematicians from many countries. Each conference, which includes nine one-hour plenary lectures, thirty half-hour contributed talks, and forty posters, will attract over 200 participants from all over the world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A distinguishing characteristic of FPSAC conferences is the concerted effort to recognize and encourage outstanding young scientists. At least one plenary speaker is an "emerging star," and talented young researchers are well represented among the speakers selected for contributed talks. Another special feature of the FPSAC conferences is a continued tradition of inclusiveness. The conference seeks to draw substantial participation from underrepresented groups. Furthermore, English and French have been designated as official languages for FPSAC 2017 and 2018 to promote a diverse pool of participants. Attendance at this conference will be exceptionally valuable for graduate students and junior researchers. Somewhat interdisciplinary, the conferences link research in combinatorics to other topics in pure mathematics such as algebraic geometry, commutative algebra, representation theory, K-theory and symplectic geometry, and to topics in other sciences such as computer science, physics, and biology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1700378</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Mason</LastName>
<EmailAddress>masonsk@wfu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wake Forest University</Name>
<CityName>Winston Salem</CityName>
<ZipCode>271098758</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3367585888</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1834 Wake Forest Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7970</Code>
<Text>Combinatorics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
