<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR - TT:  Commercial electrospinning prototype for spider silk</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>199592</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This PFI: AIR Technology Translation project focuses on translating the ability to produce a device that is capable of continuously electrospinning recombinant spider silk proteins (rSSp) into yarns and then post-spin processing them. These fibers, with robust mechanical properties, will solve needs for use in both the medical device field as sutures as well as a ballistic thread for applications such as body armor. However, traditional wet-spinning methodologies of rSSp have yet to yield a method of spinning that scales to industrial levels or results in fiber mechanical properties that match native spider silk fibers. This project will result in a proof-of-concept continuous electrospinning device that also has the ability to post-spin process the fibers, a critical component of spinning spider silk as the process is well documented to improve fiber mechanical ability.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project addresses the following technology gaps as it translates from research discovery toward commercial application: 1) No device exists to continuously electrospin fibers and then post spin process them and 2) There is no method of spinning rSSp that results in fibers with mechanical properties mimetic to native spider silk that can scale to industrial levels. Specific knowledge gaps and methods of addressing them are: a) constructing the electrospinning device by modifying existing rotating-mandrel equipment to spin continuous yarns.  This will be accomplished by incorporating a rotating bell that will collect the electrospun fibers which can then be pulled away from the bell in a continuous fashion.  b) Incorporating a means by which to move the yarn outside of the device.  An arm will be engineered that will attach to the accumulated fibers from the bell?s surface and move that growing yarn outside the shielding.  c) Thread the yarn through a series of godets and stretch baths for processing which is traditionally done by hand threading.  d) Collecting the rSSp yarn on a collection spool.  At the end of the godet and stretch baths, the yarn will be accumulated on a standard spool that is in-synch with both the electrospinning rate and godets.   Producing the proof-of-concept device will allow the exploration of appropriate conditions for:  i) rSSp dope conditions, ii) electrospinning parameters such as voltage and needle distance and iii) stretch bath and stretch parameters of the rSSp yarn as well as rSSp:polymer blends. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Personnel involved with this project will include undergraduate and graduate students who will not only perform the research but will also be involved in the technology translation and commercial aspects of the project such as patent pathways, customer discovery and licensing discussions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1700949</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Justin</FirstName>
<LastName>Jones</LastName>
<EmailAddress>justin.a.jones@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Randolph</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewis</LastName>
<EmailAddress>randy.lewis@usu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Utah State University</Name>
<CityName>Logan</CityName>
<ZipCode>843221415</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4357971226</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Sponsored Programs Office</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
