<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>PFI:AIR-TT: Aircraft Icing Detection System</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>199992</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jesus Soriano Molla</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Accelerating Innovation Research-Technology Transfer (AIR-TT) project focuses on the transformation of a microwave microstrip resonator developed for measuring soil water content into an aircraft icing detection instrument. Microwave microstrip resonators have been used to measure soil water content for decades. A new technique for fingerprinting the presence of de-icing fluid, liquid water or ice and quantifying their amount on the surface of the resonator was developed at the University of Michigan. This project focuses on translating this discovery into a new type of instrument for aircraft ice detection. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Icing is hazardous to aircraft and occurs in ways that are difficult for pilots to detect. In addition, icing can occur throughout the year in nearly all regions of the globe, making detection and avoidance an important component of flight safety procedures. Unfortunately, existing icing detection systems are not capable of detecting ice directly on the structure of airplanes, where ice accumulation could disrupt the airflow and cause loss of control.  The aircraft icing detection system developed in this project fills this gap.  A prototype microstrip resonator will be developed that will be mounted flush with the aircraft surface. Work will be done to correlate the frequencies and resonance modes to distinguish between ice, water, and spongy ice for a range of ice thicknesses on the aircraft surface. It is expected that the work will show that the prototype can measure the thickness of films of water and de-icing fluid ranging from sub-millimeter to a few millimeters.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project also contributes to the education of various graduate students. The project engages master students in technology translation efforts from research discovery toward commercial products. The students will gain hands on experience while being mentored by academics and practitioners.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1701057</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nilton</FirstName>
<LastName>Renno</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nrenno@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Hughes</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kchughes@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8019</Code>
<Text>Accelerating Innovation Rsrch</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
