<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Individual recognition and long-term memory of third-party relationships in a social bird</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>20280</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090500</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jodie Jawor</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;There is mounting evidence that the evolution of intelligence is primarily driven by the need to navigate complex social relationships. However, the way in which a species' social system influences developing intelligence is less well understood. While it is known that some animals are aware of the relationships between individuals other than themselves, previous studies have concentrated on short-term knowledge about relationships within a single social group. This narrow focus limits the inferences that can be drawn about how different social systems shape intelligence. This project will test whether acorn woodpeckers can remember the relationships between others for years, an ability that has not been investigated in any non-human species. Acorn woodpeckers are a group-living bird in which relatives maintain a relationship even after years of separation, and kin who no longer live together may act as allies in times of conflict. Thus, if acorn woodpeckers can recognize and remember their neighbors' kin for years, they could benefit by keeping track of competitors' allies. This study aims to identify whether they have this ability. The project will create paid positions for two field assistants and several undergraduates will be mentored and learn transferable skills by assisting in data collection and analysis. The investigators will also continue their scientific outreach and education efforts with youth from under-served communities. By improving scientific understanding of the relationship between sociality and cognition, this project could provide perspective on the evolution of intelligence in general.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to expand our understanding of social cognition by testing the hypothesis that acorn woodpeckers can remember the relationships between others for at least two years. The investigators will create playback stimuli that simulate two birds calling in unison, which acorn woodpeckers only do naturally with current or former members of their own group. Woodpeckers will then receive playbacks of the following simulated vocal exchanges: 1) two related birds who formerly lived together two years ago, 2) two related birds who never lived together, and 3) two unrelated birds who never lived together. In all cases, the callers will be unrelated to the subject. If acorn woodpeckers remember the relationships between birds that lived together two years ago, they should recognize Stimulus 1 as being more socially congruent than 2 and 3, and should thus exhibit a longer response latency to Stimulus 1, indicating less violation of expectation. If they recognize the relationship between callers via an acoustic cue of relatedness rather than by memory, they should show a longer response latency to both Stimuli 1 and 2 compared to 3.  This work will also provide relevant training and mentoring to undergraduate students.  Results will be communicated to the scientific community through publications and the general non-scientific community through outreach efforts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1701451</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Walter</FirstName>
<LastName>Koenig</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wdk4@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Webster</LastName>
<EmailAddress>msw244@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Pardo</LastName>
<EmailAddress>map385@cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7659</Code>
<Text>ANIMAL BEHAVIOR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
