<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: Integrating Physiology and Genomics to Test for Local Adaptation in a Montane Ectotherm</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>20111</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010207</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>George W. Gilchrist</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will investigate the processes determining color and size differences between western fence lizards occurring at high versus low elevations on mountains in California. High elevation lizards are darker and larger than low elevation lizards. Such differences in traits within a species are generally assumed to be genetically based and a result of adaptation to local environments. However, phenotypic differences can also result from the effects of different environmental conditions on development. The researchers will use a combination of physiological experiments and genomic analyses to identify whether color and size differences in western fence lizards are a consequence of natural selection or phenotypic plasticity. Results will provide critical insights into the role and evolutionary advantages of environmentally dependent phenotypic differences in heterogeneous environments. In addition, the project includes day-long educational workshops targeting young girls interested in STEM fields and development of an interactive exhibit on lizards for a local museum.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This study focuses on a phenotypic cline in the western fence lizard (Sceloporus occidentalis) along an elevational gradient in the Sierra Nevada Mountains of California. By combining techniques from genomics, functional ecology, and transcriptomics, this research will develop a comprehensive picture of the origin and function of high elevation phenotypes in western fence lizards. The researchers plan to evaluate the influence of temperature and day length on juvenile phenotypes, and to identify candidate genomic regions implicated in phenotypic differentiation. Juvenile lizards will be reared in a laboratory common garden experiment with treatments that mimic conditions at high and low elevation. This experimental design will decouple the genetic and environmental constituents of phenotype, and also shed light on the functional implications of trait differences. By comparing gene expression profiles of lizards reared in native and non-native conditions, fixed and plastic responses to environmental conditions at both organismal and genomic levels will be identified.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1701231</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Leache</LastName>
<EmailAddress>leache@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lauren</FirstName>
<LastName>Buckley</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lbuckley@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nassima</FirstName>
<LastName>Bouzid</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bouzidnm@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7377</Code>
<Text>EVOLUTIONARY ECOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
