<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Canonical Bases, Categorification, and Modular Representations</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>244836</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew  Douglass</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The symmetries of a snowflake or a baseball are described by the notion of a group. Groups also describe more abstract symmetries, including supersymmetry in theoretical particle physics. Many important symmetries are described by continuous groups known as Lie groups, after mathematician Sophus Lie; these groups are generated by associated Lie algebras.  Quantum groups, which are deformations of such symmetries, also serve as a shadow of higher structures. This research project aims to further develop a new approach, via so-called i-quantum groups, to representations of Lie algebras and Lie superalgebras. This new approach aims to uncover the underlying geometric and higher categorical structures of i-quantum groups.  Results are expected also to have applications to knot theory. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Because of recently discovered connections to geometry of flag varieties, canonical bases, and categorification, i-quantum groups, which are co-ideal subalgebras of Drinfeld-Jimbo quantum groups, have been shown to play an increasingly important role in the theory of quantum groups and representations of Lie algebras and Lie superalgebras. In this project the investigator plans to develop the theory of canonical bases and categorical actions of i-quantum groups and their modules in the Kac-Moody setting. In particular, a categorification of affine -quantum groups will be formulated and applied to study the modular representation theory of quantum (super)groups of classical type at roots of unity and classical algebraic groups in prime characteristic. Character formulae in Bernstein-Gelfand-Gelfand category for exceptional Lie superalgebras will also be formulated.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/26/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1702254</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weiqiang</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ww9c@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O.  BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
