<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DISSERTATION RESEARCH: An Experimental Test of Generalist Foraging Behavior as a Community Stabilization Mechanism</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>18340</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cesar Nufio</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Species can become rare or common for many reasons. Scientists are increasingly interested in how such changes in the abundance of one species can impact other species, particularly those that eat species that become rare.  Some scientists think that the rareness of one species leads to the rareness of other species that rely on this species, potentially causing a lot of local extinctions -- perhaps even the collapse of an entire ecosystem.   Other scientists disagree.  They think that declines in one species can benefit other species if the first species might compete with the second, leading to a stable ecosystem in which there is an overall balance in the number of species that are increasing relative to those that are decreasing.  Key to predicting the vulnerability of plants and animals to changes in their environment is figuring out which of these opposing views is most likely.  Such understanding will help managers, policy makers and scientists develop strategies to support the diversity of life on earth. The goal of this project is to test how a coastal ecosystem responds to disturbances and, in particular, whether a top predator can adjust to changes in the abundance in its prey.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research uses a predatory whelk on the Oregon coast to examine how different possible foraging strategies of generalist predators influence the stability of rocky intertidal communities. The researchers will use whelks trained on different prey in the laboratory to replicate different methods of generalist foraging in the field (e.g., constant prey preferences and adaptive foraging). The whelks will be exposed to two natural pulse recruitment perturbations in the field.  Researchers will use the changes in species densities following the perturbations to determine the resilience and resistance of the communities. This will allow the researchers to examine the role that generalists play in promoting community stability and what forms of generalist foraging are the most likely to stabilize communities. This study will support the training of a graduate and undergraduate students and will provide opportunities for outreach through the development of an exhibit for a science center that explains the concept of food webs and how food webs influence the everyday lives of visitors to the science center.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/01/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1702051</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Novak</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mark.novak@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kyle</FirstName>
<LastName>Coblentz</LastName>
<EmailAddress>coblentk@oregonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Oregon State University</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973318507</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5417374933</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OREGON STATE UNIVERSITY</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
