<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WiFiUS: Collaborative Research: SELIOT: Securing Lifecycle of Internet-of-Things</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Monisha Ghosh</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project focuses on developing effective and efficient methods for detection of vulnerable devices in an IoT network, as well as mitigation techniques, as a reaction to identified vulnerabilities. The vision for the scientific impact of this project is a comprehensive set of tools for securing networked IoT devices throughout their lifecycle, coupled with the requirement to co-exist with inherently vulnerable or legacy devices. The project aims to achieve this vision by focusing on three phases of an IoT device's lifecycle:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;1. Birth: identify vulnerable devices when they are first introduced into an IoT network.&lt;br/&gt;2. Life: verify the configuration and operation of devices during their normal operation and updating firmware even in resource-constrained devices. &lt;br/&gt;3. Repurposing: infer changes in device ownership (including disposal) and perform secure deletion of sensitive data whenever ownership change is confirmed.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;All of the above will be achieved with a strong emphasis on assuring that new security techniques are meaningful and usable by a wide range of users.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Research outcomes of this project are expected to benefit society in addressing important IoT security problems before manufacturers saturate the market with ostensibly useful and innovative gadgets that lack sufficient security features, thus being vulnerable to attacks and malware infestations, which can turn them into rogue agents. PhD students involved in the project will benefit from unique opportunities for developing valuable research skills in the important emerging area of IoT security, as well as collaborating with international partners, thus exposing them to new research perspectives. One aspect of anticipated impact is in training the next generation of information security experts who, beyond understanding and appreciating security and privacy concerns in IoT, are also sufficiently skilled to address them. Another aspect of this project's impact will be achieved by transferring our results into prototypes, which can be turned into products and services.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1702911</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gene</FirstName>
<LastName>Tsudik</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gts@ics.uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926173213</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>141 Innovation Drive, Ste 250</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>RES IN NETWORKING TECH &amp; SYS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8229</Code>
<Text>WiFiUS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
