<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2017-2019 Northeast LSAMP Bridge to the Doctorate Program: University of Connecticut</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>1071484</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>leroy jones</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Louis Stokes Alliances for Minority Participation (LSAMP) program assists universities and colleges in diversifying the STEM workforce through their efforts at significantly increasing the numbers of students successfully completing high quality&lt;br/&gt;degree programs in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM)disciplines. Particular emphasis is placed on transforming STEM education through innovative recruitment and retention strategies and experiences in support of groups&lt;br/&gt;historically under-represented in STEM disciplines: African-Americans, Alaskan Natives, American Indians, Hispanic Americans, Native Hawaiians, and Native Pacific Islanders. The Bridge to the Doctorate (BD) Activity provides support for postbaccalaureate&lt;br/&gt;studies in STEM programs leading to the STEM doctoral degree.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The University of Connecticut (UConn) is the host site for the 2017-2019 Bridge to the Doctorate (BD) program for the Northeast Louis Stokes Alliance for Minority Participation (NELSAMP) under the leadership of this institution. This is the third post-baccalaureate program at the institution that supports a graduate student cohort of underrepresented minority (URM) STEM Ph.D. students from LSAMP campuses across the nation. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The BD Activity provides extensive training in specific STEM disciplines as well as professional development and guidance that promote peer mentoring and leadership in the scientific community. Students receive rigorous academic and research training experiences that support completion of the Ph.D. and the transition to a competitive career in academia and industry. Over the duration of the project and beyond, the BD program at UConn serves to increase the number and quality of students from underrepresented groups completing STEM&lt;br/&gt;Ph.D. degrees and entering the STEM workforce. Formative and summative evaluation will occur with the summative evaluation including a comparison group to assess impact of the program interventions on student outcomes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The long-term impact of the BD activity is reflected in America's STEM workforce, both academia and in industrial research and development. By nurturing future STEM leaders, the value added is seen in the visibility of underrepresented minorities in&lt;br/&gt;science and engineering, increasing representation and providing role models and motivation for the next generation.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/12/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1702132</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kent</FirstName>
<LastName>Holsinger</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kent.holsinger@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mun</FirstName>
<LastName>Choi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mun.choi@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/05/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeremy</FirstName>
<LastName>Teitelbaum</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jeremy.teitelbaum@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maria</FirstName>
<LastName>Martinez</LastName>
<EmailAddress>maria.d.martinez@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erik</FirstName>
<LastName>Hines</LastName>
<EmailAddress>erik.hines@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joelle</FirstName>
<LastName>Murchison</LastName>
<EmailAddress>joelle.murchison@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9133</Code>
<Text>ALLIANCES-MINORITY PARTICIPAT.</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
