<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Efficient and Durable Solar Water Splitting by a Hybrid Nitride System</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>282763</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project relates to artificial photosynthesis (AP) - the process by which solar energy is directly harvested and stored in chemicals such as hydrogen.  AP is a critical emerging technology for ensuring the Nation's future needs for sustainable energy and chemicals.  Presently, AP photoelectrode materials lack the ability to sustain stable high efficiency.  The project will address this challenge by studying the mechanisms behind photoelectrode degradation, along with efforts to improve the stability of tantalum nitride (an efficient AP photoelectrode) by integrating it with a nitride-based organic coating and catalyst material.  The results will contribute significantly to the eventual goal of employing artificial photosynthesis as a large-scale solar energy storage solution.  The experimental efforts will be complemented by educational efforts designed to develop novel curricula aimed at educating non-science majors on the importance of renewable energy.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;The project is inspired by the principal investigator's recent success in understanding the factors that limit the performance of tantalum nitride (Ta3N5).  The previous results suggest that surface passivation by a non-oxide material, together with a catalyst, is needed to actualize the full potential of Ta3N5 for high-efficiency solar water splitting.  Graphitic C3N4 (g-C3N4) represents a rare material choice that meets the requirement.  The project is also conceived within the context that g-C3N4 has been shown effective in promoting a 2-electron pathway for water oxidation.  Together, the system presents a unique opportunity to study material-related issues at the photoelectrode/water interface for solar energy applications.  The experiments will generate important insight into photoelectrode destabilization mechanisms.  They are also expected to yield practically useful strategies to address critical issues such as low photovoltage and poor stability.  The most significant outcome will be the first demonstration of water splitting at efficiencies &gt;10% by a photoelectrode/water junction.  Specific aims will be directed at 1) demonstrating conformal and uniform g-C3N4 coverage on the surface of Ta3N5, with carbon nanodots (CDots) deposited on the g-C3N4 as a co-catalyst to disproportionate the hydrogen peroxide formed during water oxidation; 2) characterizing the structure of the hybrid material; 3) conducting electrochemical and spectroscopic characterization to probe whether the introduction of g-C3N4 mitigates the Fermi level pinning effect that is typical to Ta3N5; and 4) measuring the charge transfer kinetics at the photoelectrode/water interface on Ta3N5 with and without g-C3N4 to understand how g-C3N4 influences the charge transfer rates.  Beyond the technical objectives, the project will provide an opportunity to expand the sustainable-energy workforce through graduate and undergraduate student education, and build upon previous successes by the principal investigator's team in educational outreach.  A new collaboration with educational experts will be formed to quantitatively assess the effectiveness of these efforts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1703662</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dunwei</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dunwei.wang@bc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Boston College</Name>
<CityName>Chestnut Hill</CityName>
<ZipCode>024673800</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6175528000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>140 Commonwealth Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
