<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>WERF: Enhanced evaluation of the removal of contaminants of emerging concern in decentralized water reuse systems by non-targeted analysis</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>304532</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karl Rockne</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>PI: Natalie Mladenov&lt;br/&gt;Proposal ID: 1705901 &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The wastewater infrastructure in the United States and many developed countries is largely centralized and many systems are reaching the end of their design life. As an alternative to replacing thousands of miles of failing sewer pipe, decentralized wastewater treatment systems (DEWATS) coupled with membrane filtration and other advanced treatment technologies can meet water supply needs at the community-level. One important challenge in water reuse and recycling systems is the persistence of multiple types of contaminants, including contaminants of emerging concern (CECs) such as pharmaceutically active compounds that potentially number in the thousands and have frequently been detected in wastewater effluent and receiving waters. The contaminants and their potential byproducts generated during the treatment process pose an unclear risk to human health, and the mechanisms by which these chemicals are removed or transformed in DEWATS are key issues this project seeks to address. This research will employ a systematic non-targeted analytical approach to comprehensively identify both known and unexpected contaminants and byproducts in lab-scale membrane treatment systems. This project will also advance education and diversity through development of a Water Reuse Demo and Competition activity to convey themes dealing with water scarcity and reuse to middle school girls in the all-female We Are STEM Enrichment Program at San Diego State University. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;DEWATS that utilize aerobic and anaerobic membrane bioreactor technology (MBR and AnMBR, respectively), especially if coupled to additional polishing steps, have the potential to provide treatment at levels comparable to or better than conventional centralized treatment plants and will have a role in augmenting non-potable and potable water supplies. A key to the implementation of membrane reactors in DEWATS is ensuring that these systems meet current water quality standards and offer superior treatment for multiple classes of contaminants, including CECs that are detected in treated waters and the environment. For anaerobic treatment via DEWATS, the current understanding of the fate of contaminants, which has been developed around conventional large-scale aerobic treatment systems, is incomplete, and research on this front is needed to advance the use of anaerobic systems. There is a diversity of parent compounds as well as metabolites of unknown toxicity that are formed during MBR and AnMBR treatment. The goals of this research are to 1) evaluate the removal and transformation mechanisms for contaminants in aerobic and anaerobic membrane bioreactor systems and 2) enhance the identification of parent compounds as well as byproducts in MBR and AnMBR systems.  This research will employ a non-targeted analysis based on gas chromatography coupled to time-of-flight mass spectrometry (GC×GC/TOF-MS) in order to comprehensively identify both known and unknown chemicals and their bio-transformation and photo-transformation products. The research will also investigate how photolysis, which is critical in pond or wetland treatment systems that tend to follow anaerobic treatment, contributes to chemical removal and transformation. The impact of this work will be far reaching for the water reuse field because this more exhaustive evaluation of chemicals and their transformation in small-scale membrane treatment systems will inform the growing decentralized movement in the US and abroad.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1705901</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Dodder</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ndodder@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eunha</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoh</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ehoh@mail.sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Natalie</FirstName>
<LastName>Mladenov</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nmladenov@sdsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>San Diego State University Foundation</Name>
<CityName>San Diego</CityName>
<ZipCode>921822190</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6195945731</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5250 Campanile Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1440</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
