<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Bioengineering of Channelrhodopsins for Neurophotonic and Nanophotonic Applications</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>520000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Leon Esterowitz</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A vital area of research that expands the scope and horizons of biophotonics is the recent discovery of new forms of channelrhodopsins (ChRs-a family of proteins that function as light-gated ion channels). ChRs have played an important role in optogenetics and the recent discovery of new channelrhodopsins from algae, has expanded the potential applications of this unique class of microbial rhodopsins. Optogenetics applications include restoring vision to the blind and uncovering the basis of a host of brain disorders including strokes, traumatic brain injury, addiction, anxiety disorders, deafness, epilepsy, Parkinson's and Alzheimer's. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;At present key questions such as the molecular basis of the cation and anion selectivity, the mechanism of light-activated channel-gating and control of channel kinetics remain largely unknown. In order to answer these questions and test specific hypotheses, the PIs will utilize advanced vibrational spectroscopic and bioengineering techniques. These include low-temperature and time-resolved FTIR difference spectroscopy, confocal near-IR Raman and femtosecond visible-pulse/IR-probe spectroscopy. The research program will involve undergraduate, graduate and postdoctoral trainees. This will provide a pipeline to industry for talented engineers and scientists trained in the new field of biophotonics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/22/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1706322</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph</FirstName>
<LastName>Bunch</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bunch@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/22/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Rothschild</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kjr@bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/22/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shyamsunder</FirstName>
<LastName>Erramilli</LastName>
<EmailAddress>shyam@buphy.bu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/22/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Trustees of Boston University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>022151300</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173534365</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>881 COMMONWEALTH AVE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7236</Code>
<Text>BIOPHOTONICS, IMAGING &amp;SENSING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
