<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NeuroNex Innovation Award: Southwest Magnetogenetics Project (SoMa)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>800000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080200</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sridhar Raghavachari</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>To better understand how the brain functions, scientists are in search of new methods to activate specific neurons in laboratory animals without restricting their behaviors. This research effort will create technologies that rely on magnetic fields to stimulate specific, genetically modified neurons. A major advantage of this "magnetogenetic" technology is fact that magnetic fields easily penetrate bone, skin and tissue making it easier for scientists to probe the role of specific cells deep within the body without using any implanted devices that could otherwise interfere with normal animal behavior or cause damage to the target tissue. Better understanding of how the brain works in laboratory animals will help reveal fundamental principles of computation in the brain that may apply across animal species to include humans. This deeper understanding of the brain is key for developing better diagnosis and treatments for neural disorders and to improve artificial systems like neural networks designed to operate like the human brain. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This work will focus on understanding how biogenic magnetic nanoparticles tethered to temperature sensitive ion channels render specific cells sensitive to magnetic fields. The major goals of this effort will be the development of a comprehensive theory for the mechanism of action for these magnetogenetic channels, and the creation of a set of transgenic fly lines that display robust behavioral responses to magnetic fields. These magnetogenetic fly lines will be compatible with Gal4/UAS system such that magnetogenetic channels can be easily targeted to specific cells. The outcome of this work will be both a fundamental understanding of magnetogenetic mechanisms and a set of transgenic fly strains that will empower researchers to probe neural circuits in this common model organism.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/12/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1707562</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Weiwei</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhong</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Weiwei.Zhong@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/31/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Benjamin</FirstName>
<LastName>Arenkiel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>arenkiel@bcm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/31/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>01/12/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jonathan</FirstName>
<LastName>Silberg</LastName>
<EmailAddress>joff@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/31/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Herman</FirstName>
<LastName>Dierick</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dierick@bcm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/12/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Caleb</FirstName>
<LastName>Kemere</LastName>
<EmailAddress>caleb.kemere@rice.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/31/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
<LastName>Robinson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>robinson.jacob@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/31/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>William Marsh Rice University</Name>
<CityName>Houston</CityName>
<ZipCode>770051827</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7133484820</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6100 MAIN ST</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
