<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Quantum Coherence with Holmium Atoms: Magic Traps, Clocks, and Entanglement</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>210000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexander Cronin</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project will study the properties of holmium  atoms.  The holmium atom has one of the most complex internal structures of any element, and therefore could be valuable for several new technologies.  This research team will explore how holmium's complex structure can be used to develop new methods for atomic timekeeping and for quantum memory.  The first application is important because atomic clocks are the most accurate time and frequency standards, and they provide the basis for technologies such as the Global Positioning System (GPS).  The second application is important because it could help enable quantum communication networks.  Experimental methods using lasers and electromagnetic fields will be developed to cool and trap holmium atoms, to prepare them in different internal states, and to measure interactions between holmium atoms. This will enable the research team to make more precise measurements of holmium atoms' collisional properties and the sensitivity to magnetic fields for various transitions between holmium atomic energy levels.  This project will also train scientists in modern techniques of atomic physics and prepare students for careers in academia and industry. The results of this research will be disseminated to the local public in the Madison, Wisconsin, area through open houses in the Physics dDpartment, through visits to local schools, and by providing internships for local high school students. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The rare earth element Holmium (Ho) has a 128-dimensional ground state manifold, the largest of any stable atomic isotope. Experiments will use a Magneto-Optical Trap of Ho atoms. Optical control techniques using rf and microwave fields will be developed to prepare specific Zeeman substates in the 128-dimensional ground manifold. A pair of states to be used for an optical clock transition will be magnetically trapped in a configuration that makes the energy difference of the states insensitive to magnetic field noise. An array of magnetic traps will be created using lithographically defined chip structures with current carrying wires.   Rydberg states will be probed using two-photon excitation, and dressing techniques for creating long range atomic interactions will be studied. These techniques have the potential to create entangled many body states for improved precision of the clock transition.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1707854</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Saffman</LastName>
<EmailAddress>msaffman@wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1241</Code>
<Text>AMO Experiment/Atomic, Molecul</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
