<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Theory of the Speed-Limited Particle-in-Cell Simulation Method</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav S. Lukin</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will develop the theory and explore practical applications of a new algorithm for simulation of plasma -- a state of matter with freely interacting electrons and ions not bound together in atoms.  This new algorithm has the potential to enable simulation of larger and more complicated plasma systems, leading to a better fundamental understanding of plasma physics, improved predictive capabilities for space weather, better modeling of fusion devices and plasma-based rocket thrusters, and more efficient manipulation of plasma for semiconductor fabrication and other industrial purposes.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The new algorithm, the speed-limited particle-in-cell (SLPIC) method, is an extreme variant of the immensely useful particle-in-cell (PIC) technique.  SLPIC facilitates multiscale simulation by avoiding the need to resolve unimportant small-scale phenomena -- phenomena that must otherwise often be resolved, even when physically negligible, to avoid numerical instabilities.  To accomplish this, SLPIC limits the speed of fast particles (e.g., electrons), while keeping track of what their actual speed should be.  The speed-limited motion is a consequence of an approximate Vlasov equation; it accurately simulates particle distribution functions as long as they change sufficiently slowly.  This project will develop the theory and use of SLPIC, examining its advantages and disadvantages with respect to standard PIC simulation, and apply it to test problems, including plasma sheaths, the solar wind, and Hall rocket thrusters.  In addition, this project will explore the possibility that SLPIC techniques might help mitigate the finite grid instability well-known in standard PIC methods.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1707430</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Cary</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cary@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/30/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gregory</FirstName>
<LastName>Werner</LastName>
<EmailAddress>greg.werner@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/30/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1242</Code>
<Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7244</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>026Z</Code>
<Text>NSCI: National Strategic Computing Initi</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7569</Code>
<Text>CYBERINFRASTRUCTURE/SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
