<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Magnetically-Driven Transitions in Molecule-Based Materials</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>440560</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical abstract:&lt;br/&gt;The overall goals of this project are to explore magnetically-driven transitions in molecule-based materials  and to invest in the education of a diverse group of young people at the University of Tennessee. Both initiatives advance the fundamental understanding of new electronic and magnetic states of matter while contributing to important societal values and outcomes. The scientific impacts of this research derive from our across-the-board interest in the fundamental interactions between light and matter, the emergent behaviors that are unveiled when materials are driven away from ambient conditions, and the new states of matter that emerge when phases compete. This work builds on prior experience with low temperature, high magnetic field, and  high pressure spectroscopy, and it leverages the facilities at the National High Magnetic Field Laboratory and the National Synchrotron Light Source II at Brookhaven National Laboratory. At the same time, planned activities support the interdisciplinary education of a diverse group of young researchers for future employment in academics, government laboratories, and industry in the area of advanced materials. A broad range of outreach and service activities are planned, especially in the area of conference and workshop organization and service to various national laboratories. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical abstract:&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on the spectroscopic properties of molecule-based materials and how external stimuli like magnetic field and pressure impact functionality. Building on key advances of the previous award period, current efforts concentrate on phase transitions in model quantum magnets and hybrid multiferroics and the structure-property relationships that can be unraveled in these systems. Within this broad scientific area, several materials have been selected that are expected to show large or widely applicable effects and where the analysis of the spectroscopic response can reveal the microscopic aspects of coupling between charge, structure, and magnetism. What brings these efforts together is an overarching interest in the behavior of materials under extreme conditions and the spectroscopic techniques with which these phenomena are investigated. Findings from this comprehensive experimental program will advance both theoretical understanding and the design of new materials.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1707846</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janice</FirstName>
<LastName>Musfeldt</LastName>
<EmailAddress>musfeldt@utk.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Tennessee Knoxville</Name>
<CityName>KNOXVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>379960003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8659743466</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 CIRCLE PARK</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>026Z</Code>
<Text>NSCI: National Strategic Computing Initi</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>053Z</Code>
<Text>Quantum Leap Materials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>6863</Code>
<Text>SEBML-MOORE'S LAW</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
