<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NeuroNex Technology Hub: Nemonic: Next generation multiphoton neuroimaging consortium</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>1770000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080200</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Edda (Floh) Thiels</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Multiphoton neuroimaging is a powerful approach for measuring neural activity in the brain, offering subcellular resolution of thousands or more neurons at time. However, current technology has technical limitations that restrict what experiments are possible. Therefore, this project will create new technology through a NeuroNex neurotechnology hub, called Nemonic (NExt generation Multiphoton NeuroImaging Consortium). The Nemonic project has three parts. First, the development component will create new systems in a series of Case Studies to enable currently impossible neuroscience experiments. Second, the dissemination component will spread this technology broadly to other neuroscience labs through open source resources, workshops, and industry partnerships. Third, the advancement component will push the fundamental technology of multiphoton neuroimaging into the next frontier. Two specific technologies will be developed: miniaturized photonic systems for multiphoton neuroimaging; and super-resolution imaging to image submicron structures. Also, a series of meetings will foster novel collaborations to more rapidly advance engineering technologies that are relevant to multiphoton neuroimaging in the future. Technology developed in the Nemonic project will also be relevant to manufacturing, 3D printing, and photonics. This work will also increase partnerships between academia and industry, enhance STEM training, and recruit and support the scientific training and careers of women and URM scientists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Case Studies will develop new instrumentation for large field-of-view two- photon and three-photon imaging, scalable temporal multiplexing, and integrated behavior. This technology will be developed for compatibility with an array of model systems. The focus will be on calcium and glutamate imaging, in cell bodies and processes, and other fluorescent indicators can be employed. The workshops will cover optical design, fabrication, assembly, and use, for an audience of neuroscientists and engineers. One advancement project will develop high peak power ultrafast lasers with transform limited pulses, with integrated, beam conditioning, beam steering, focusing, and detection systems. The other advancement project will develop super-resolution multiphoton imaging using spatial frequency modulation, adaptive optics, and novel pulse conditioning. Together, this work will advance multiphoton neuroimaging and a suite of related technology, through research, enhanced training, and industry partnerships. This NeuroTechnology Hub award is co-funded by the Division of Emerging Frontiers within the Directorate for Biological Sciences as part of the BRAIN Initiative and NSF's Understanding the Brain activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/22/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1707287</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Spencer</FirstName>
<LastName>Smith</LastName>
<EmailAddress>slab@unc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/31/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of North Carolina at Chapel Hill</Name>
<CityName>CHAPEL HILL</CityName>
<ZipCode>275991350</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9199663411</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 AIRPORT DR STE 2200</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7275</Code>
<Text>CROSS-EF ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
