<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Astroparticle Physics with the VERITAS and CTA Gamma-Ray Observatories</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>366125</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jean Cottam Allen</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Gamma-rays are the highest energy form of electromagnetic radiation. Observations of astrophysical gamma-rays serve as probes of physical conditions and processes in the most extreme environments throughout the Universe, and can be used to test fundamental physics.  This award supports scientists at the University of Delaware to carry out gamma-ray astrophysics research using a currently operating observatory and participate in the planning and development of a next-generation gamma-ray observatory.  The Very Energetic Radiation Imaging Telescope Array System (VERITAS), located in southern Arizona, is designed to perform high sensitivity pointed observations of both Galactic and extragalactic sources.  The University of Delaware group will work on hardware and calibration tasks for VERITAS as well as analysis and interpretation of the scientific data from Galactic gamma-ray sources.   The group is also involved in the technology development and scientific planning for the Cherenkov Telescope Array (CTA), an international gamma-ray observatory currently in the prototyping stage.  The group will continue to organize and host the "Fermi Summer School," a two-week high energy astrophysics course for graduate students and post-docs.  They will also continue to engage in a broad range of efforts in education and public outreach.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The University of Delaware group will conduct both scientific analysis and hardware-related activities. They will use gamma-ray observations with VERITAS to study supernova remnants, gamma-ray binary systems, and new gamma-ray sources identified by the complementary High Altitude Water Cherenkov Observatory.  They will also conduct prompt VERITAS follow-up observations to search for gamma-ray emission from sources of astrophysical neutrinos identified by IceCube, and mine the VERITAS archive for gamma-ray counterparts to the enigmatic Fast Radio Bursts.  The group will work on the maintenance and calibration of VERITAS.  They are involved with the hardware maintenance of the upgraded camera, and the development of a new calibration device.  Finally, the group will participate in commissioning of the CTA prototype telescope at the VERITAS site.  They will also lead the scientific planning for Galactic gamma-ray studies with CTA.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1707544</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamie</FirstName>
<LastName>Holder</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jholder@physics.udel.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/30/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Delaware</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>197162553</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3028312136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>210 Hullihen Hall</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Delaware</StateName>
<StateCode>DE</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1643</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Cosmic P</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
