<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Gravitation Physics and Relativistic Astrophysics</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>140000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds theoretical research in several different topics in relativistic astrophysics and general relativity.  One focus is on tests of general relativity and on sources of gravitational radiation that might be detected by the Laser Interferometer Gravitational Wave Observatory (LIGO) and by future space based detectors. Theoretical studies of sources of gravitational waves funded by this award will be useful to aid detection of signals from black holes and other sources, and also to aid in their interpretation. Gravitational wave studies can tell us about the nature of gravity, properties of black holes, and properties of the early Universe. A second focus is the exploration of newly discovered conservation laws involving black holes, and their implications for deep and poorly understood issues in quantum gravity such as the information loss paradox discovered by Stephen Hawking.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In more detail, the principal research topics of this award are: (i) The development of methods to compute the gravitational waveforms from point particles inspiraling into spinning black holes, using a combination of analytical and numerical approaches; (ii) Generalizing the mathematical formalism of Wald and Zoupas to develop a comprehensive description and understanding of conservation laws involving soft hair on black holes, and studying their physical consequences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1707800</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eanna</FirstName>
<LastName>Flanagan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>flanagan@astro.cornell.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Cornell University</Name>
<CityName>Ithaca</CityName>
<ZipCode>148502820</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6072555014</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>373 Pine Tree Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1244</Code>
<Text>GRAVITATIONAL THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
