<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Wavelength Scaling of Plasma and Spatio-Temporal Dynamics of Laser Filamentation in Solids</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>325000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Vyacheslav S. Lukin</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research project will improve the understanding of the physical mechanisms and the spatio-temporal dynamics of laser filamentation in solids.  Laser filamentation is self-guidance of a high-power laser pulse propagating through a gas, liquid or solid material when self-focusing of the pulse is balanced by defocusing due to the laser-induced modifications in the material.  This remarkable phenomenon finds a lot of applications such as table-top ultraviolet and x-ray generation, lightning guiding, rainmaking, selective radiotherapy on cancer cells, long-lived waveguides in air, and remote sensing of pollutants.  This project will also promote basic science education to groups, such as grandparent-led rural families, who have been traditionally underrepresented in science.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Laser filamentation is self-guidance of a high-power laser pulse when self-focusing due to the optical Kerr effect is balanced by defocusing due to material ionization and/or other nonlinear mechanisms.  Although laser filamentation has been studied mainly using near-infrared and visible wavelengths, recent progress in ultrafast laser technology enables the investigation of laser filamentation using longer wavelengths such as mid-infrared and long-wavelength infrared.  In this project, laser filamentation in solids will be experimentally studied by measuring plasma densities directly inside the filaments, with the experiments guided by 3-dimensional computer simulations of laser matter interactions.  The project will impact filament-based technology such as new ultrabroadband and ultrashort light generation for spectroscopy and optical communications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1707237</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bonggu</FirstName>
<LastName>Shim</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bshim@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/30/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Binghamton</Name>
<CityName>BINGHAMTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>139026000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6077776136</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4400 VESTAL PKWY E</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1241</Code>
<Text>AMO Experiment/Atomic, Molecul</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1242</Code>
<Text>PLASMA PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7621</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS-BROADEN PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1062</Code>
<Text>BASIC PLASMA SCIENCE &amp; ENGINEERING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7621</Code>
<Text>PHYSICS-BROADEN PARTICIPATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8084</Code>
<Text>CDS&amp;E</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
