<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Postdoctoral Fellowship in Biology FY 2017: Evolutionary patterns in sand-entrapment in plants and consequences for insect herbivores</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>138000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Daniel Marenda</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This action funds an NSF Postdoctoral Research Fellowship in Biology for FY 2017, Research Using Biological Collections. The fellowship supports research and training of the fellow that will utilize biological collections in innovative ways. Specifically, this proposal examines an often-noted, but virtually unstudied phenomenon: a great many plants entrap sand or other substrate with sticky trichomes. Sand entrapment traits are well-preserved in herbarium specimens, but the distribution and evolution of such traits in plants is poorly-known. Entrapped sand and dust have negative effects on insect and mammalian herbivores, wearing down their mandibles and teeth, and the presence of this substrate lessens herbivory on plants. During this experiment, the fellow and undergraduate researchers will use herbaria, insect collections, and laboratory experiments to further explore this interesting phenomenon.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research supported by this award has four primary goals. (1) To determine the extent of sand-entrapment across the plants, utilizing herbarium collections and compiled floras for desert and dune regions. (2) To determine whether plants trade-off this effective physical defense with chemical defenses, using a live collection of sand verbenas (Abronia species) and a common pest caterpillar (Hyles lineata). (3) To determine whether sand-entrapment dictates which insects can eat these sand-covered plants. Lastly [4] to determine whether insects feeding on these and other gritty plants have evolved similar "tooth" morphology to herbivorous mammals - the ability to wear down their grinding surfaces. These projects will be conducted with several undergraduate assistants, and will be incorporated into lessons for elementary through high school students.  Results form the studies will be distributed in peer-reviewed journals and presented at scientific meetings and symposia.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/21/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/21/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1708942</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>LoPresti</LastName>
<EmailAddress/>
<StartDate>06/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>LoPresti                Eric</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956163167</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>001Y</Code>
<Text>Collections Postdocs</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
