<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Kahler Manifolds with Curvature Lower Bound</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>163209</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thomas Ivey</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Complex numbers are everywhere in modern mathematics, from solving quadratic equations, to modeling fluid flow, to probing the spaces hidden in the curled-up dimensions of string theory.  The natural domains of complex-number-valued functions are complex manifolds, including the n-dimensional complex Euclidean space. This project concerns the relationship between the geometry of a natural class of complex manifolds, called Kahler manifolds, and the behavior of complex functions on these manifolds.  One of the most beautiful results in complex analysis (the study of complex-valued functions) is the uniformization theorem, which says that one-dimensional complex manifolds have essentially only three shapes: a sphere, a disc, or a plane, corresponding to positive, negative, or zero curvature. A higher-dimensional version of uniformization has long eluded mathematicians; for example, it is conjectured that if an open n-dimensional complex manifold has positive curvature then it is a copy of complex n-space.  The PI will address this long-standing conjecture.  The resulting research, which lies at the intersection of many branches of mathematics, will establish new and interesting connections between analysis, algebra, differential geometry and topology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More precisely, the PI will work on the uniformization conjecture of Yau, which states that a complete noncompact Kahler manifold with positive bisectional curvature is biholomorphic to complex n-space. So far there have been numerous attempts at this conjecture, starting with Mok-Siu-Yau in early 1980s.  Along with the uniformization conjecture, the PI will also address related problems such as Siu's conjecture on Stein-ness of complete noncompact Kahler manifolds with positive bisectional curvature.  As in the PI's earlier work, the Gromov-Hausdorff convergence theory will serve as an important tool to study these conjectures. The PI will also study the Gromov-Hausdorff limit of Kahler manifolds with curvature lower bound (e.g., the degeneration of the complex structure). In some sense, this is a generalization of the breakthrough result of Donaldson-Sun on Kahler manifolds. The expectation is that the limit space should carry a natural complex analytic structure.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1709894</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gang</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gang.liu@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<ZipCode>602013149</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8474913003</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 Maple Ave.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
