<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Emergent Unconventional Superconductivity at Interfaces between Superconductor, Topological, and Magnetic Materials</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Computers are ubiquitous, yet typical computation methods consume enormous amounts energy, soon to reach unsustainable levels. Thus, an eminent national grand challenge is to develop a more energy efficient method with which to process information without losing computing power. This project addresses this challenge by determining the unique physical properties of unconventional superconducting materials, which could then be used to design a more powerful and energy efficient computer, referred to as a topological quantum computer. Unconventional superconductors are materials that exhibit useful zero-resistance states, but whose properties are poorly understood. The proposed work combines theoretical and experimental expertise to fabricate nanoscale superconducting devices, and investigate the different combinations of materials and electronic transport measurements that best establish and probe unconventional superconductivity. The results of the research help determine properties that may be useful in a quantum computer. The collaborative research team incorporates a diverse group of undergraduate and graduate students in research activities and provides a rich environment for training in nanoscale and quantum technologies. Educational aspects are further integrated through course development, research-related seminars, and outreach activities that especially target groups under-represented in physics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to determine the symmetry and transport properties of superconductors suspected of exhibiting unconventional pairing symmetry as result of proximity coupling to topological and ferromagnetic materials. The aim is to both better understand complex superconducting systems and also to determine their potential use in electronic devices. The experimental effort consists of making phase-sensitive as well as quantum transport measurements of the hybrid topological superconductor/magnetic structures to determine the superconducting order. The experimental research is closely coordinated with a theoretical effort that uses both numerical and analytic techniques to analyze the experimental data and aid in the design of new experiments. Key expected outcomes include: determining the pairing symmetry of proximity-coupled and intrinsically superconducting topological insulators; observing if exotic excitations, possibly Majorana, exist and determining their relation to the pairing symmetry; and developing new techniques for probing unconventional superconductors, including enhanced phase-sensitive probes. The collaborative research team incorporates a diverse group of undergraduate and graduate students in research activities and provides a rich environment for training in nanoscale and quantum technologies. Educational aspects are further integrated through course development, research-related seminars, and outreach activities that especially target groups under-represented in physics.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1710437</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nadya</FirstName>
<LastName>Mason</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nadya@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dale</FirstName>
<LastName>Van Harlingen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dvh@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Gilbert</LastName>
<EmailAddress>matthewg@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>026Z</Code>
<Text>NSCI: National Strategic Computing Initi</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>053Z</Code>
<Text>Quantum Leap Materials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
