<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Quantum Field Theory, Atomic Physics and General Relativity</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michael Cavagnero</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will attempt to combine relativistic quantum theory of nanoscale phenomena with the concepts of general relativity, a theory primarily designed to cover astrophysical phenomena. One of the aims is to study the consequences for relativistic geodesy, where one uses tiny frequency shifts in atomic transitions, as a function of the altitude of an atomic clock, in order to map out the Earth's surface. To accomplish this task, modern computer algorithms will be developed in concert with an improved understanding of quantum field theories to advance our quantitative understanding of quantum mechanical bound states of atoms. Only by combining quantum field theory with the notion of curved spacetime can our current understanding of the very large be reconciled with our current understanding of the very small. This project will continue and extend the PI's explorations of this synthesis of two world views. The supervision of graduate students and the completion of an extensive monograph on the subject matter will complement the research program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research planned for this project will cover theoretical physics research in various related fields, including extensions of the Dirac equation to curved space-time, pseudo-Hermitian extensions of Dirac theory, the use of highly powerful parallel computer algorithms for the calculation of atomic properties. Existing discrepancies between theory and experiment (the so-called muonic hydrogen/proton radius puzzle and the enhancement of internal pair creation in the decay of 8Be) will be analyzed theoretically, and higher-order corrections will be studied. The Dirac formalism will be augmented by a coupling of the bispinor to curved space-time, with special emphasis on consequences for relativistic geodesy. Finally, investigations on atom-surface contact interactions and non-contact friction effects will complement the research program.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1710856</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ulrich</FirstName>
<LastName>Jentschura</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ulj@mst.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Missouri University of Science and Technology</Name>
<CityName>Rolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>654096506</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5733414134</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>300 W 12th Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Missouri</StateName>
<StateCode>MO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1284</Code>
<Text>AMO Theory/Atomic, Molecular &amp;</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1289</Code>
<Text>PRECISION MEASUREMENTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
