<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Dynamic Full-Duplex single-channel wireless communication systems</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>329999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jenshan Lin</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Due to the explosive growth in demand, access to spectrum has become one of the overarching issues limiting the potential of communication systems to provide a high quality of service and coverage.  A fundamental limitation of current systems is the need to operate in half-duplex modes, where to support bi-directional communication, different frequencies are assigned for forward and reverse channels, or alternatively, communicating nodes take turns in time. In both these approaches, resources are not fully utilized. The research undertaken in this project focuses on enabling efficient and robust, in-band Full Duplex (FD) systems. In FD systems, bi-directional communication occurs, simultaneously, in the same frequency band, improving spectral efficiency and easing frequency planning. Through the models and results developed in this project, researchers and practitioners will be able to better evaluate different FD techniques and architectures leading to significant improvements in performance and deployment strategies of next generation wireless systems. Spectrum that is harvested using FD systems can then be repurposed to improve service to existing users as well as create new opportunities for economic growth. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the project is to lay out the basic framework for a thorough understanding of the potential of FD systems, especially in conditions where the wireless channel is rapidly evolving. Recent advances in FD systems have shown that it is feasible to attain high levels of isolation between receive and transmit paths, paving the way to a host of FD solutions and applications. While achieving a desired isolation has been proven, it is extremely challenging to maintain the isolation, especially in highly dynamic wireless channels.  The objective of the proposed research is to study the dynamics of FD systems utilizing spatial, analog and digital cancellation to enable the system to operate reliably in constantly changing environments caused by propagation conditions, multipath, and interference. A number of technical research challenges will be addressed including developing new heuristics that are capable of adapting to the dynamic wireless channel rapidly, utilizing novel approaches to cognitive learning of the operational conditions. The project is highly structured such that the central theme is consistent throughout all phases: develop and validate theory and algorithms to enable FD systems under a wide variety of dynamic conditions. Through a fusion of research, educational and outreach goals, results generated from the work performed under this award will be widely disseminated to researchers, practitioners, and the general public.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1710746</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ahmed</FirstName>
<LastName>Eltawil</LastName>
<EmailAddress>aeltawil@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926173213</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>141 Innovation Drive, Ste 250</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7564</Code>
<Text>COMMS, CIRCUITS &amp; SENS SYS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>153E</Code>
<Text>Wireless comm &amp; sig processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
