<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>University of Utah - Operation of the Telescope Array, TALE, and the TAx4 Expansion</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>800000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jean Cottam Allen</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cosmic rays are highly energetic sub-atomic particles from space that travel at velocities near the speed of light.  The origin of cosmic rays and their acceleration mechanisms are unknown, but they likely originate in extreme astrophysical phenomena both within and beyond our galaxy.  The Telescope Array (TA) is the largest cosmic ray observatory in the northern hemisphere.  Located outside Delta, Utah, and representing a joint US-Japanese effort, TA was designed to study the nature and origin of the highest energy particles in the Universe.  This award to the University of Utah supports the continued operation of TA, the TA Low Energy extension (TALE), and the expanded observatory (TAx4) as it comes online.  The University of Utah is the host institution for TA and therefore plays a critical role in its daily operation.  This award will also support the University of Utah group's involvement in the Astrophysics Science Project Integrating Research and Education (ASPIRE) program, which engages area teachers, students, and the public through a web site of interactive educational materials and visits to local schools.  The group will also host associated experiments in other fields that benefit from the TA location and infrastructure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary objectives of the TA experiment are to measure the energy and spatial distributions, and the chemical composition of the highest energy cosmic rays in order to address the nature and origin of ultra-high energy cosmic rays.  The cosmic ray physics group at the University of Utah plays critical roles in the design, integration, deployment, operation, and management of TA.  These efforts include facility and detector maintenance, staffing for observing shifts, data handling, simulation and analysis, and maintaining compliance with the Bureau of Land Management regulations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1712517</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Matthews</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jnm@cosmic.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/28/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gordon</FirstName>
<LastName>Thomson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>thomson@physics.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/28/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pierre</FirstName>
<LastName>Sokolsky</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ps@physics.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/28/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Jui</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jui@cosmic.physics.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/28/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1643</Code>
<Text>Particle Astrophysics/Cosmic P</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
