<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The STEM Faculty Institute to Promote Faculty Change</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>324945</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Nixon</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The STEM Faculty Institute at Brigham Young University (BYU) will provide intensive training on student-centered teaching strategies for faculty members from the colleges of Life Sciences, Physical and Mathematical Sciences, and Engineering. Over the course of the project, as many as 10,000 students in large, introductory STEM courses will be affected by these improved teaching methods, resulting in improved success and retention in STEM majors, and contributing to the national need for a highly skilled STEM workforce. In addition to analyzing the impacts on engaged student learning, the project will study factors that influence faculty motivation for improving the quality of their teaching practices, contributing knowledge about how to best structure faculty development programs for maximum impact.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The STEM Faculty Institute will support institutional change through an evidence-based faculty development program with four components:  (1) intense training that will include an annual week-long summer workshop to assist faculty members in understanding student-centered teaching theories and developing their own classroom techniques and strategies; (2) mentoring by colleagues who will work closely with them over the course of two semesters, supporting their implementation of evidence-based teaching practices; (3) accountability based on the production and evaluation of deliverables; and (4) meaningful incentives, including open badges that certify participant success at student-centered teaching, for recognition and rank advancement. To improve understanding of how to motivate faculty to change their instructional practices, the project team will gather quantitative and qualitative data about how faculty members are experiencing this process of change, and about the effect of increased use of student-centered instructional practices on student learning and engagement at BYU. In a design-based research cycle, the results from each year will be used to refine the structure of the STEM Faculty Institute and improve faculty success in pedagogical change. Ultimately, this project will improve student learning, engagement, and retention in STEM fields by supporting faculty implementation of evidence-based teaching practices.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1712056</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Nelson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kerekesj@berkeley.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>11/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamie</FirstName>
<LastName>Jensen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Jamie.Jensen@byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>R. Steven</FirstName>
<LastName>Turley</LastName>
<EmailAddress>turley@byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>11/27/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Geoff</FirstName>
<LastName>Wright</LastName>
<EmailAddress>geoffwright@byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sansom</FirstName>
<LastName>Rebecca</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rsansom@chem.byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>West</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rickwest@byu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brigham Young University</Name>
<CityName>Provo</CityName>
<ZipCode>846021231</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8014223360</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>A-285 ASB</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
