<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Engagement in Engineering Pathways: An Initiative to Retain Non-Traditional Community College Students Using Peer-Led Instruction and Learning</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>213116</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Alexandra Medina-Borja</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Student engagement in STEM coursework continues to be a challenge in undergraduate education and continues to be a barrier in the retention of all students, especially those that are underrepresented and/or non-traditional. To succeed in diversifying and increasing the STEM workforce, as well as improving the quality of STEM graduates entering the workforce, student engagement must improve. Valencia College is a highly diverse two-year, non-residential, open access public institution that serves the Orlando, Florida area. The goal of this project at Valencia College is to use peer-facilitated instruction in core engineering coursework known to have high attrition rates, with the goal of retaining non-traditional students in engineering. Adopting evidenced-based teaching and learning practices proven successful at four-year institutions, the intent of this project is to measure the impact on engineering students' engagement at two-year colleges with the aim of diversifying and broadening the participation in engineering. This project has potential to increase understanding of these methods in STEM courses at two-year colleges, as well as improve the teaching quality and student engagement at Valencia College. Further, the new knowledge generated during this project around the use of peer-facilitated instruction at two-year colleges has potential to improve the success and participation of non-traditional students in engineering and STEM disciplines across a broad range of institutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More specifically, the project will design and implement peer-facilitated recitation activities linked to fundamental engineering courses, such as engineering analysis, statics, and dynamics. At Valencia College, these courses have the highest failure rate among female and underrepresented minority students. Through the design and implementation of peer­led, problem-based, and contextualized real-world applications in these fundamental engineering courses, the goal of the project is to increase student engagement and persistence. As a cross-sectional study design, engagement will be measured using scales such as students' mathematics efficacy, engineering efficacy, academic self-concept, and sense of belonging. By adopting a teaching and learning model that has been effective at large research-intensive universities, the proposed project offers an innovative and adaptable approach to supporting and retaining diverse students at a community college in introductory engineering courses. Results from student metrics will inform faculty professional development efforts to increase faculty support and maximize student learning. The project will affect institution practices informed by data as well as reach a national audience in the STEM community to further ignite educational practice and educational research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/13/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/13/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1712008</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lisa</FirstName>
<LastName>Macon</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Lmacon@valenciacollege.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mohua</FirstName>
<LastName>Kar</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mkar@valenciacc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Courtney</FirstName>
<LastName>Demings</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cdemings@valenciacollege.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Valencia Community College</Name>
<CityName>Orlando</CityName>
<ZipCode>328023028</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4075822909</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P O BOX 3028</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
