<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CIF:Small: Ramanujan-sums in signal representation</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Brown</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research explores new directions in the representation of signals, based on certain&lt;br/&gt;mathematical ideas introduced by Ramanujan many decades ago. In particular the applicability of&lt;br/&gt;Ramanujan-sums in the representation of digital signals is studied in detail. Signals acquired and&lt;br/&gt;stored in many scientific areas such as speech, music, medical, genomic, and finance often&lt;br/&gt;contain hidden periodic patterns bearing important information. These are difficult to identify and&lt;br/&gt;localize because of the large volume of data, and extreme localization of information.&lt;br/&gt;Conventional representations of signals based on Fourier and wavelet transforms are not efficient&lt;br/&gt;for this purpose. This research involves the use of Ramanujan-sums to develop new&lt;br/&gt;representations that are efficient and economical. These offer insights into the role of&lt;br/&gt;mathematics, especially number theory, in representation of signals in science and technology,&lt;br/&gt;with emphasis on particular hidden structures such as periodicities. Such representations are&lt;br/&gt;expected to have significant impact in scientific applications involving large data bases.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More specifically, the research goes deep into Ramanujan subspaces, nested periodic subspaces,&lt;br/&gt;and Ramanujan filter banks, which are crucial to the representation of periodic sequences. This&lt;br/&gt;enables one to address some fundamental research problems in signal processing. This includes&lt;br/&gt;the minimum information that should be gathered from a discrete-time signal in order to identify&lt;br/&gt;multiple periodicities, the design of digital filter banks that serve as projection operators onto&lt;br/&gt;periodicity subspaces, and optimal design of dictionaries of atoms to represent sums of periodic&lt;br/&gt;signals with unknown integer periods. The research also involves the theory and implementation&lt;br/&gt;of gridless methods to achieve super resolution in period-estimation for continuous-time signals,&lt;br/&gt;and extension to two- and higher-dimensional signals.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/28/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/28/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1712633</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>P.</FirstName>
<LastName>Vaidyanathan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ppvnath@systems.caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/28/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7797</Code>
<Text>COMM &amp; INFORMATION FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7936</Code>
<Text>SIGNAL PROCESSING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
