<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: The Impact of Atmospheric Pollution on the Quality of the Runoff from Storm Events</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>5400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>As the Human population increases, so does the demand for clean drinking water. Rooftop runoff is largely underused, but has the potential to provide potable water to communities where treated water is limited or unavailable. In order to determine the potential for rooftop runoff to serve as a small-scale drinking water source, research must be conducted on the impact of atmospheric pollution, specifically smog, on the quality of the runoff from storm events. Many Chinese residents lack access to potable water, and regularly face the additional hardship of heavy atmospheric pollution. Professor Yungfeng Yang of Tsinghua University School of Environment, an expert in environmental microbiology and microbe mediated biogeochemistry, will serve as host and mentor. Results from this project could assist in making rooftop runoff a viable water source for people in heavily populated and polluted cities throughout the world, including the USA. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A lack of access to water, complexes to store and treat water, and exposure to excessive amounts of fluorine and arsenic in groundwater sources prevent many Chinese citizens from acquiring clean drinking water. Utilization of rooftop runoff has the potential to improve the accessibility of water sources. In addition to lacking clean water, Chinese citizens' health is also heavily impacted by atmospheric pollution which is influenced by industrial activities, traffic, and coal burning. Particulate Matter (PM2.5) accumulates in the form of smog, which has been proven to reduce visibility, contribute to acid rain, and get trapped in lungs. Beijing, China and Los Angeles, United States both sit in a bowl-like depression which can trap particulates that can cause smoggy conditions; however, regulations have proved successful in preventing Los Angeles from having serious smog problems. Poor atmospheric conditions negatively impact rooftop runoff quality and produces bacterial contamination. This study will investigate the impact of atmospheric conditions on rooftop runoff quality in Beijing in order to develop rooftop runoff collection and treatment techniques that could provide potable water to Chinese residents in need. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award, under the East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes program, supports summer research by a U.S. Graduate student and is jointly funded by NSF and the Chinese Ministry of Science and Technology.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/25/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1713940</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristen</FirstName>
<LastName>Wyckoff</LastName>
<EmailAddress/>
<StartDate>04/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Wyckoff                 Kristen        N</Name>
<CityName>Knoxville</CityName>
<ZipCode>379201892</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9200</Code>
<Text>US CHINA COOP IN BASIC SCIENCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
