<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Exploring Connections between Lichen Distribution and Forest Biodiversity</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>5400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research seeks to explore the connections between lichen distribution and ecosystem parameters and forest biodiversity. It will be conducted in collaboration with Dr. Glenn Aguilar in UNITEC Institute of Technology, whose knowledge in modelling distribution will be crucial to incorporate different factors affecting lichens growth for the publication of the results. New Zealand is particularly rich in lichen species with 1799 species currently recognized. If these species disappear there will be ecological consequences. Lichens play an important ecological role in the ecosystem; especially since they act as bio indicators of pollutants and help monitor air quality. They are sensitive to land use and habitat changes. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will utilize existing plant monitoring plots across the Auckland Region to establish characteristics of lichen distribution defining relationships between abundance and environmental parameters to provide a correlation with lichen cover, location, temperature, anthropogenic impact and height among others.  A field experiment will be carried out using two lichens associated with the trees species in the Auckland region. The currently identified lichens in New Zealand lack essential information as distribution, population size and ecological requirements to determine the baseline data of the lichen distribution and diversity. Lichens are a key component of forest biodiversity. Their relationship with their substrate can provide data on threatened species in order to understand the significance of lichens in these ecosystems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award, under the East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes program, supports summer research by a U.S. graduate student and is jointly funded by NSF and the Royal Society of New Zealand.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1713829</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gladys</FirstName>
<LastName>Benitez</LastName>
<EmailAddress/>
<StartDate>05/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Benitez                 Gladys         N</Name>
<CityName>Cidra</CityName>
<ZipCode>007390000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5941</Code>
<Text>NEW ZEALAND</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
