<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAPSI: Using Drone Technology to Address Key Knowledge Gaps in the Life Histories of Sea Turtles</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>5400</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office Of Internatl Science &amp;Engineering</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne L. Emig</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project uses drones to study the abundance and activities of sea turtles on nesting beaches, and nearshore habitats of Australia. Collaborators include Mark Hamann and Karen Joyce (James Cook University), Mick Guinea (Charles Darwin University), Scott Whiting and Tony Tucker (Department of Parks and Wildlife), Amanda Hodgson (Murdoch University Cetacean Research Unit), and indigenous communities throughout Australia. Australia boasts some of the most ecologically diverse and well-studied sea turtle habitats in the world. Collaboration with sea turtle and remote sensing experts will provide access to expertise, advanced drone technology, and multiple species of sea turtles and habitats, that were previously inaccessible to the PI. Optimal drone-based methods will be developed to study sea turtles at nesting beaches and in nearshore waters. These methodologies will be available to enhance sea turtle conservation programs worldwide and promote a deeper understanding, awareness and conservation of the marine environment in the next generation of environmental stewards. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project evaluates the use of drones for studying sea turtles on nesting beaches, and in nearshore foraging, mating, and developmental habitats of Australia. The research involves collaborations with multiple researchers, institutions, and indigenous communities throughout Australia. Australia boasts some of the most ecologically diverse and well-studied habitats in the world for several species of sea turtles. Direct interaction with experts in sea turtle biology and remote sensing provides access to more advanced drone technology, methodologies, and multiple sea turtle species and habitats. Optimal drone-based methodologies will be developed to study the demographics and behavior of sea turtles in multiple life stages at nesting beaches and adjacent critical habitat. This opportunity will enhance the applicant?s expertise in the use of drones in marine field ecology while generating methodologies that will be available to enhance sea turtle conservation programs worldwide. The collaborative nature of this project will promote a deeper understanding, awareness and conservation of the marine environment among the next environmental stewards. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award, under the East Asia and Pacific Summer Institutes program, supports summer research by a U.S. graduate student and is jointly funded by NSF and the Australian Academy of Science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/25/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1713379</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Bevan</LastName>
<EmailAddress/>
<StartDate>04/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bevan                   Elizabeth      M</Name>
<CityName>Birmingham</CityName>
<ZipCode>352057835</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5912</Code>
<Text>AUSTRALIA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5978</Code>
<Text>EAST ASIA AND PACIFIC PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7316</Code>
<Text>EAPSI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
