<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Preparing for the DKIST Era:  Numerical Modeling of the Lower Solar Atmosphere</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>281040</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Neff</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Sun's magnetic field plays a critical role in connecting the different layers and powering the various regions of the solar atmosphere, as well as in driving "space weather."  Detailed observations with a new generation of ground-based telescopes could help us better understand the Sun's magnetic field.  To interpret these observations, we need to develop a more complete knowledge of the physical processes occurring in the solar atmosphere.  This research project will use advanced computer models to identify key processes in the lower solar atmosphere that influence the Sun's magnetic field.  The project will thus enable the effective use of telescopes built with public investment.  It will also provide science enrichment and research experience to K-12 students and undergraduate students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research team will perform three-dimensional numerical simulations of the solar chromosphere to help interpret sensitive high-resolution observations from telescopes such as the Daniel K. Inouye Solar Telescope (DKIST) and the Atacama Large Millimeter/submillimeter Array (ALMA).  The team will employ the numerical code Bifrost for the simulations, which will include a realistic treatment of physical processes such as ambipolar diffusion and non-equilibrium ionization, as well as their effects over a wide range of size scales.  The simulations will also yield synthetic observables that can be compared to data from DKIST and ALMA to identify processes that drive the dynamics and heating of solar chromosphere.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1714955</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Juan</FirstName>
<LastName>Martinez Sykora</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jumasy1980@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bay Area Environmental Research Institute</Name>
<CityName>Petaluma</CityName>
<ZipCode>949525159</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7079389387</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>625 2nd St Ste 209</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1214</Code>
<Text>PLANETARY ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1206</Code>
<Text>THEORETICAL &amp; COMPUTATIONAL ASTROPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
