<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RUI: The transcriptional response to quantitative variation in RpoS concentration in E. coli</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>112226</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Molecular and Cellular Bioscience</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Arcady Mushegian</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project develops a quantitative understanding of how bacteria turn their genes on and off in response to stresses. This project will provide undergraduate students with experience performing research in microbiology, molecular genetics, and genomics. In addition, the PI will provide research internships to high school students participating in an Upward Bound program. These students are from backgrounds underrepresented in science, and the internships will give these students a path towards careers in science.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The project studies two major questions about how the transcription of genes in the E. coli genome varies in response to the concentration of the regulatory protein RpoS. First, the project will test the role of specific transcription factors (TFs) in altering how genes respond to RpoS levels. This will be done by RNA-seq studies of the response to RpoS levels in strains lacking certain TFs. These whole genome studies will be complemented by detailed manipulations of TF binding sites in specific promoters. Second, the research will characterize the dose-response relationship between RpoS and transcription, and its influence over a physiological transition. This research will be done by altering RpoS levels using an arabinose-inducible RpoS system, and then measuring the effect on transcription using RNA-seq.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1716794</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Stoebel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>stoebel@hmc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Harvey Mudd College</Name>
<CityName>CLAREMONT</CityName>
<ZipCode>917115901</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9096218121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>301 Platt Boulevard</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1112</Code>
<Text>Genetic Mechanisms</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7465</Code>
<Text>NANOSCALE BIO CORE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
