<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CHS: Small: Collaborative Research: EEG-Guided Electrical Stimulation for Immersive Virtual Reality</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>357038</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ephraim P. Glinert</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Spatial presence, in Virtual Reality (VR) terminology, refers to the perception (or illusion) of being physically present in a simulated environment.  VR strives to create interactive environments that provide experiences of spatial presence through accurate delivery and perception of multimodal sensory stimuli.  Research in VR spans fields ranging from neuroscience and medicine to gaming.   While the computing and gaming industries have generated tremendous advances in hardware and software for graphics processing and 3D display technologies, VR systems still lack capabilities for providing users with haptic feedback (a sense of touch), which is crucial for generating truly immersive, real-world experiences.   It is known that an increase in the feeling of spatial presence manifests itself in the form of increased brain activity.   This research aims to achieve the control of haptic sensory stimulation adaptively, based on the changes in brain activity associated with perceptual responses elicited by sensory stimulation in VR environments.  Project outcomes will include novel scientific discoveries and engineering enhancements that will make significant contributions to other areas of interest, such as prosthetic limbs, augmented reality, and telepresence applications.  The project will help train a new generation of engineers skilled in addressing multidisciplinary challenges, while through outreach activities STEM careers will be promoted at the K-12 level.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research objective is to identify and analyze brain activity associated with the increased feeling of haptic spatial presence elicited by electro-tactile stimulation and measured through EEG, and to investigate closed-loop techniques to control electro-tactile stimulation for enhanced haptic presence in VR environments.  Specifically, the project will: (1) develop an electrical haptic stimulation framework; (2) design analysis techniques to identify markers of haptic inputs in EEG; (3) establish control policies for adaptive electrical stimulation; and (4) evaluate and refine EEG-guided adaptive stimuli control framework in VR environments.  In particular, the proposition to actuate haptic feedback through electrical stimulation is novel, while formulating design principles for model-based optimal EEG-guided closed-loop haptic feedback for immersive spatial presence is transformative.  Additional innovative propositions to advance adaptive control under uncertainty and psychophysical investigations are unique; these present a potentially game-changing opportunity for VR system development and perhaps for general human-computer interaction.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/24/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/24/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1717654</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Weber</LastName>
<EmailAddress>djw50@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Murat</FirstName>
<LastName>Akcakaya</LastName>
<EmailAddress>akcakaya@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems (CHS)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8624</Code>
<Text>IntgStrat Undst Neurl&amp;Cogn Sys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Understanding the Brain/Cognitive Scienc</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8091</Code>
<Text>BRAIN Initiative Res Support</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
