<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CSR:NeTS:Small:GigaPaxos: System Support for Group-Scalable, Reconfigurable Replica Coordination</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>450000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>M. Mimi McClure</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is developing a cloud computing technology called GigaPaxos that enables Internet services to be dynamically moved close to their users. For example, imagine you and your friend jointly editing a shared document or playing your favorite online game at a WiFi-enabled cafe. Wouldn't it be convenient if the document or game server magically moved to a "nano-data center" located right at the WiFi access point ensuring local-area-network-like fast performance and resilience to outages in Internet connectivity or data centers? GigaPaxos promises to realize this vision to bring these low-latency and fault-tolerance benefits to any mobile cloud service with minimal programming effort.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A key intellectual merit of this project lies in dramatically increasing "group scalability" or the ability to maintain a very large number of independent consensus instances, one each for each lightweight fault-tolerant principal as small as a distributed counter, a user's calendar, a single record in a key-value store, etc. GigaPaxos allows each consensus instance to consume no more than a few hundred bytes; enables developers to programmatically sprinkle and reconfigure lightweight replicas of services in accordance with resource management, performance, or availability objectives; enables flexible consistency semantics; enables byzantine fault-tolerance support to accommodate untrusted machines; and facilitates a number of realistic end-to-end application case studies to validate ease-of-use and user-perceived quality of experience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impacts of this project include new course curriculum on distributed systems targeting senior undergraduates and Masters students; a computer science diversity and enrollment effort targeting University of Massachusetts Amherst undergraduates as well as high school students; an aggressive dissemination plan involving fostering a vibrant open-source community to help sustain GigaPaxos beyond the project's duration; and quantitative user- and developer-centric usability case studies that will help improve GigaPaxos and potentially simplify distributed systems development in the long term.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project researchers will host the open-source code repository at https://github.com/MobilityFirst/gigapaxos and documentation and research publications at https://gigapaxos.io for the duration of the project and indefinitely beyond that contingent on community interest.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/31/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/31/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1717132</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arun</FirstName>
<LastName>Venkataramani</LastName>
<EmailAddress>arun@cs.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/31/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Amherst</Name>
<CityName>Hadley</CityName>
<ZipCode>010359450</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4135450698</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Research Administration Building</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>Computer Systems Research (CSR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
