<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NeTS: Small: Learning-Guided Network Resource Allocation: A Closed-Loop Approach</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>479000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Thyagarajan Nandagopal</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Based on network measurement and user behavior data, much recent work has studied the modeling and prediction of network utility and user experience using machine learning techniques. While it provides important insights, prediction itself is often not the ultimate goal in networks. Ideally, a network could identify users with poor experience and take proper actions to proactively improve the overall performance. To achieve this goal, the project advocates a closed-loop approach that uses learning-aided utility model to explicitly guide resource allocation in networks and uses feedback to (in)validate and improve the learned utility model. This investigation provides important insights in understanding, designing, and analyzing learning-model-aided resource optimization algorithms. Furthermore, because of its generality, this closed-loop approach can be applied in other systems with the following characteristics: 1) the system is too complex to rely on domain knowledge only to build a white-box utility model; 2) there exists sufficient data so that a utility model can be learned; 3) to maximize the overall utility, one can optimize over certain control variables that affect the utility value; and 4) there exists a feedback loop so that the effect of the control can be observed. The outcome of the project can be applied to such systems in different disciplines. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Utilizing this proposed framework is highly challenging due to the unknown and noisy nature of the network utility function, and in the context of high dimensionality, coupled resource constraints, and non-convex optimization. To address these challenges, the project considers two complementary approaches: a greedy approach and an integrated approach. The greedy approach has much flexibility in applying diverse learning models, which may fit different application scenarios better in practice, but is difficult to analyze. The integrated approach builds upon Gaussian Process (GP) bandits that integrate both the constructed model and model uncertainty in resource allocation decisions. This approach is more amenable to theoretical analysis, although highly challenging. In both approaches, one needs to optimally allocate resource based on the learned models. The contribution of the project comes from solving the corresponding non-convex optimization problems. The last step is to use the closed-loop feedback to build a better or optimal utility model. The integrated approach aims to develop hierarchical GP bandit algorithms for dimensionality reduction, ideally with theoretical performance guarantees. The greedy approach leverages perturbed-exploration schemes for general learning models and strives for practicality and generality.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1718901</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xin</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>liu@cs.ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Huasen</FirstName>
<LastName>Wu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hswu@ucdavis.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Davis</Name>
<CityName>Davis</CityName>
<ZipCode>956186134</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5307547700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OR/Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
