<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Conference in Geometric Topology</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>45000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides partial support for participation by U.S.-based mathematicians at an international conference in geometric topology to be held in Tuscany, Italy, during June 5-9, 2017. Topology is the study of the properties of spaces that do not depend on a way to measure distance; this conference focuses on those spaces that arise in geometric contexts such as surfaces and three-dimensional spaces (with the universe we live in being one example). The conference will feature both research talks on the latest developments in the area and three mini-courses designed for advanced graduate students and other early career mathematicians. The conference will provide an opportunity for those conducting cutting-edge research to present their results and a venue for discussion and collaboration among established researchers and junior mathematicians in the field. This award will allow a significant number of U.S.-based early-career mathematicians to attend, and a majority of this funding will support these mathematicians.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will focus primarily on low-dimensional hyperbolic geometry, and, more generally, geometric structures on manifolds. Mini-courses on character varieties and knot symmetries, arithmetic hyperbolic 3-manifolds, and renormalized volume will provide an introduction to several of the emerging trends in the field. This will be complemented by research talks from a distinguished international group of speakers.  More information on the conference can be found at &lt;br/&gt;http://www.dm.unipi.it/~martelli/Cortona2017/Cortona.html</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/16/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1719746</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Canary</LastName>
<EmailAddress>canary@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kenneth</FirstName>
<LastName>Bromberg</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bromberg@math.utah.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Utah</Name>
<CityName>SALT LAKE CITY</CityName>
<ZipCode>841128930</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8015816903</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>75 S 2000 E</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Utah</StateName>
<StateCode>UT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
