<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Travel Support for Young Topologists Meeting - Stockholm, Sweden - July 2017</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This travel grant provides partial support for U.S. participation in the Young Topologists Meeting 2017, held in Stockholm, Sweden by the Royal Institute of Technology and Stockholm University, July 3rd-7th, 2017. The Young Topologists Meeting (YTM) is an annual European conference focused on the work of graduate students and young researchers in topology that brings in participants from all over the world. At the YTM, junior topologists present their work to a large international audience, and also attend mini-courses taught by senior topologists. The conference provides opportunities for the participants to meet new colleagues and mentors, to learn about current progress of researchers in their fields, and to form research collaborations. Its open and supportive atmosphere encourages young mathematicians, including those from underrepresented groups, to pursue research careers in topology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The YTM is an annual event, first started in 2007, which traditionally alternates between Copenhagen, Denmark and Lausanne, Switzerland until 2017 when it will be hosted in Stockholm, Sweden. The conference features parallel sessions of contributed talks by graduate students and young researchers, covering a broad spectrum of topics in topology. In addition to these talks, there will be mini-courses by two senior topologists, focusing in particular on techniques that expose underlying structure and connections in algebraic topology and in general on new applications, avenues of research, and open problems. This year the mini-courses will be on group homology and stability ("Topology interacting with number theory, representation theory, and algebraic geometry") and on the comparison of the differential graded world and spectra ("The equivalence of differential graded modules and HZ-module spectra, applications, and generalizations").  More details are available on the conference web page: &lt;br/&gt;https://www.math-stockholm.se/konferenser-och-akti/young-topologists-meeting-2017-1.670396</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/25/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1719564</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Yeakel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>syeakel@math.umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
