<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Building STEM Student Success at Fisk University</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia M. Rankins</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Implementation projects provide support to Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) to design, implement, and assess strategies that can lead to comprehensive institutional efforts to increase the number of students receiving undergraduate degrees in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) and enhance the quality of their preparation by strengthening STEM education and research. The project at Fisk University seeks to establish the foundation for building STEM student success. The goal of the project is to prepare students to contribute in an enduring way to new knowledge as a result of more competitive preparation for graduate school and careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Activities that are part of this project are: increasing students' deeper learning and successful transition to advanced courses by supplementary instruction into General Biology and College Algebra courses; increasing student confidence and competence in quantitative and computational approaches related to the biological sciences; and  increasing enriched faculty-mentored undergraduate research opportunities across the STEM disciplines assured by intentional  quantitative and computational integration into courses and faculty research collaborations. The  activities and strategies are evidence-based and will inform further efforts by the institution to strengthen STEM undergraduate education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1719414</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Princilla</FirstName>
<LastName>Evans</LastName>
<EmailAddress>psmart@fisk.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lee</FirstName>
<LastName>Limbird</LastName>
<EmailAddress>llimbird@fisk.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Fisk University</Name>
<CityName>Nashville</CityName>
<ZipCode>372083051</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6153298531</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 17th Avenue North</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Tennessee</StateName>
<StateCode>TN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
