<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Initiative in NanoBioengineering Undergraduate Research and Education for Minority Students (INBUREM)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>350000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia M. Rankins</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Historically Black Colleges and Universities - Undergraduate Program provides support projects to design, implement, and assess strategies that can lead to comprehensive institutional efforts to increase the number of students receiving undergraduate degrees in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) and enhance the quality of their preparation by strengthening STEM education and research. The project at Alabama State University seeks to strengthen the research, recruitment and retention activities in STEM disciplines with emphasis in the areas of bioengineering and nanobiotechnology. The overall goal is to significantly increase the preparedness of underrepresented minority students at the University choosing career paths in STEM majors, graduate programs, and workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Activities that are part of this project are: academic year, as well as summer undergraduate research experiences to include international research experiences; opportunities for high school students to conduct research in the summer; faculty and student development activities such as seminars, instrumentation workshops, and workshops on innovative teaching practices; presentations at scientific conferences; and activities to assist students in the transition to graduate school.  The activities and strategies are evidence-based and what is learned through this project can serve as a model for other institutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1719377</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shree</FirstName>
<LastName>Singh</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ssingh@alasu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Komal</FirstName>
<LastName>Vig</LastName>
<EmailAddress>komalvig@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Alabama State University</Name>
<CityName>Montgomery</CityName>
<ZipCode>361010271</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3342294742</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>915 South Jackson Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
