<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CHS:  Small: Socially-Aware Navigation</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>516000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ephraim P. Glinert</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The promise of robots to serve in assistive capacities for care and cooperation is invaluable.  Socially assistive robots have the potential to make a positive impact on people in need of physical therapy, children in need of educational intervention, children with developmental disorders, and patients post-stroke.  However, socially inappropriate behavior can harm the long-term adoption of these assistive platforms.  In particular, while typically understood only as getting from point A to point B, robot movement can constitute communication without any use of words, and even when not intended. This can have serious ramifications for the success of a social interaction between one or more people and a robot.  A robot in a long-term interaction (say in a hospital, school, or home setting) may have dozens or even hundreds of navigation destinations every day; sometimes, the "optimal" navigation behavior may not match the socially appropriate course of action.  Socially inappropriate navigation behavior has been attributed as a major impediment to the long-term adoption of assistive robots in hospital settings.  To address that problem, this project will develop a socially-aware navigation planner for autonomous robots that mimics the social conventions of human-human interactions, and will thereby advance the applications of autonomous robot technology.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Model-based navigation planning for social appropriateness will involve observing the activities and intentions of people in social proximity to a robot and/or other people, and then selecting robot trajectories that are both spatially and socially optimal.  This work will then build upon that foundation by expanding the library of spatial communication that a robot can understand and communicate in an autonomous fashion.  The research will incorporate high-level features, such as intent recognition, into the model development along with low-level features, such as interpersonal distance, to create models of complex behavior considering both the spatial scene and the inferred intention of the actors in that scene.  The Pareto Concavity Elimination Transformation (PaCcET) multi-objective optimization framework will be utilized to develop socially appropriate navigation behavior policies.  The developed planner will be validated on several types of robot platforms.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/01/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1719027</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Feil-Seifer</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dave@cse.unr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Monica</FirstName>
<LastName>Nicolescu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>monica@cse.unr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Logan</FirstName>
<LastName>Yliniemi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>logan@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/28/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems (CHS)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7367</Code>
<Text>Cyber-Human Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7923</Code>
<Text>SMALL PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
