<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Implementation Grant: Pi-STEM E3 (Pathways into STEM Careers, Enrichment, Engagement, and Empowerment)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>776819</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia M. Rankins</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Implementation Projects provide support to Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs) to design, implement, study, and assess comprehensive institutional efforts to increase the number of students receiving undergraduate degrees in science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) and enhance the quality of their preparation by strengthening STEM education and research. The project at Lawson State Community College seeks to build on previous successful efforts to increase participation of African-American students in STEM disciplines.  The goal of this project is to significantly improve student success rates in the community college's STEM programs by creating critical thinkers, increasing STEM literacy, and educating the next generation of STEM professionals. A significant broader impact is the  collaboration between the community college and its middle school and high school partners.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The overarching goal of the project is to increase the number of underrepresented minorities and women in STEM career paths by focusing on creating a year-round STEM Enrichment Institute and academic enhancement program for eighth graders and high school students; implementing a college bridge program for incoming freshman and graduating high school seniors; and providing research, mentoring, and academic development opportunities for STEM students, improving persistence and efficacy. The project will employ activities and strategies that are evidence-based, but will be studied for effectiveness in the setting of this two-year institution.  The project will be advised and evaluated for effectiveness by internal and external advisory boards and by a team of evaluators. This project provides a model for how community colleges can take a more direct, purposeful role in impacting the potential employment pool of STEM professionals.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/08/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1719329</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bruce</FirstName>
<LastName>Crawford</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bcrawford@lawsonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Calvin</FirstName>
<LastName>Briggs</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cbriggs@lawsonstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lawson State Community College</Name>
<CityName>Birmingham</CityName>
<ZipCode>352211717</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2059251666</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3060 Wilson Road S W</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
