<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the 2017 International Conference on Architecture Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matt Mutka</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This proposal is for support of a travel to the 22nd ACM International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS), to be held in Xi'an, China, April 8-12, 2017. ASPLOS is a premier forum for multidisciplinary systems research spanning computer architecture and hardware, programming languages and compilers, and operating systems. Papers in ASPLOS may target diverse goals such as performance, energy and thermal efficiency, resiliency, security, and sustainability. The proposal requests travel support funds to enable students to defray the costs of traveling to and attending ASPLOS-22. The funds requested from NSF will help support a large number of students who are expected to attend ASPLOS, including those who are not ACM members. Priority will be given to students that are US citizens and permanent residents, as well as to students belonging to under-represented groups.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The importance of forum such as ASPLOS continues to grow as we come to the end of Moore's Law, experience the explosion of big data, scales ranging from ultra-low power wearable devices to exascale parallel and cloud computers, and the need for sustainability, and increasingly human-centered applications. ASPLOS embraces systems research that directly targets these new problems in new ways. Historically, the conference has attracted top research papers from both academia and industry, and many innovations published in the proceedings have been influential in the history of the processor industry. The acceptance rates for submitted papers is typically between 15-20%.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1720467</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xuehai</FirstName>
<LastName>Qian</LastName>
<EmailAddress>xuehai.qian@usc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern California</Name>
<CityName>Los Angeles</CityName>
<ZipCode>900890001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2137407762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Park</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1640</Code>
<Text>INFORMATION TECHNOLOGY RESEARC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>Computer Systems Research (CSR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7941</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER ARCHITECTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7943</Code>
<Text>PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
