<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Profitable Recycling of Silicon Solar Cells and Modules</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Schwerdtfeger</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to make the solar industry even more sustainable by reducting long term potential environmental impact. With the rapid deployment of solar modules, recycling of end-of-life modules will become a necessity in 15 years. The International Renewable Energy Agency (IRENA) estimates that end-of-life modules will appear in large quantities by the early 2030's and by 2050 they will total 78 million tonnes. Today most end-of-life modules end up in landfills. More importantly, this project will develop a technology to enable a profitable recycling business without any government support, financial and/or legislative. IRENA predicts a new industry worth $15 billion by 2050 from recycling 78 million tonnes of modules. By recovering all the valuable components in modules, our technology has the potential to generate $60 billion in revenue from 78 million tonnes of modules.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project develops sustainable recycling processes and related equipment for silicon solar cells and modules. The focus of the project is to recover all the valuable, toxic, and bulky components in cells and modules including solar-grade silicon, silver, lead, copper, tin, aluminum, and glass. It will be demonstrated that the recovered silicon meets the specifications of solar-grade silicon and the recovered metals are over 99% pure. The target for solar-grade silicon recovery is 85% and the target for metal recovery, especially silver, is over 90%. The chemicals for recycling will be carefully chosen so their wastes neutralize each other for a minimal environmental impact.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/09/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/09/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1720800</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Coby</FirstName>
<LastName>Tao</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cobytao@tg-companies.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>TG Companies, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Fountain Hills</CityName>
<ZipCode>852680000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8179651286</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>16038 E Tumbleweed Dr</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
