<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Rapid, instrument-free Nucleic Acid Test for Pathogens and Biothreats</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>224929</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Henry Ahn</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This SBIR Phase I project will develop a prototype for a rapid and sensitive, point-of-care (POC) two-dimensional paper networks (2DPN) nucleic acid test for the detection of pathogens or biothreats. The proposed product is based on a disruptive platform technology called the Template Assisted Rapid Assay (TARA), which works directly on diverse biological samples without nucleic acid purification. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TARA seamlessly integrates minimal sample preparation with target amplification and detection, which has been the greatest challenge in POC nucleic acid testing. The test eliminates the need for excess devices for sample collection, resource-intensive refrigerated storage and transport of samples, access to instrumentation and laboratory (with its overhead costs which are required for RT-qPCR, Reverse Transcription Polymerase Chain Reaction) tests that are the most commonly used tests for pathogen or biothreat detection currently. The company will show proof-of-concept of the device via the example of MERS-CoV detection. A microfluidic-based automated 2DPN TARA card can be applied broadly to applications for point-of-care or on-the-field nucleic acid detection of infectious agents or biothreats. The 2DPN TARA card provides the sample to answer, and easy to use, assay system.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/12/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1720900</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>HyunDae</FirstName>
<LastName>Cho</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hcho@crosslifetech.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CrossLife Technologies Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Carlsbad</CityName>
<ZipCode>920106511</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8587401696</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3129 Tiger Run CT, #111</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
