<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  A novel shear-based platelet function test (PFT) using 3D MEMS electrodes</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>224984</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project relates to the management of clotting&lt;br/&gt;and bleeding which is a major clinical challenge that costs &gt; $100B healthcare system burden. In&lt;br/&gt;the United States, it affects more than ten million patients of major surgery, trauma,&lt;br/&gt;cardiovascular disease, stroke and cancers. The underlying biology is a complex orchestration of&lt;br/&gt;protein and cellular pathways that react in the context of blood flow. Proven diagnostic tools that&lt;br/&gt;capture this complexity, and also meet the constraints of diverse challenges do not exist. This&lt;br/&gt;project intends to create a novel modular hemostasis test platform using proprietary microsystem&lt;br/&gt;modules deployed in configurable cartridges tailored to meet clinical requirements. Initially a&lt;br/&gt;3D microelectrode based platelet function test module will be developed and optimized with&lt;br/&gt;potential for best in class performance following multi-scale optimization of the dynamic,&lt;br/&gt;physical diagnostic environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project seeks to develop a simple, low&lt;br/&gt;cost platelet function assay (PFA) with the objective of delivering best in class performance via&lt;br/&gt;multiscale optimization of the local biophysical diagnostic environment. Multiplate Electrode&lt;br/&gt;Aggregometry (MEA), a macroscale impedance-based device has already shown promise, yet&lt;br/&gt;remains cumbersome and has suboptimal classification accuracy between patient subsets. In&lt;br/&gt;MEA tests, as with most PFAs, the role of local fluid shear and macro/microscale physical&lt;br/&gt;environment remains largely neglected despite their well-recognized role in platelet response.&lt;br/&gt;Preliminary work suggests untapped potential in controlling and modifying PFA performance.&lt;br/&gt;By optimizing these signals with respect to clinical end points and subpopulation differentiation,&lt;br/&gt;this shear-based micro-platelet function test modules stand to revolutionize platelet function&lt;br/&gt;testing for the broadest possible benefits.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1722200</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>QI</FirstName>
<LastName>QIN</LastName>
<EmailAddress>qiqin100@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>10/16/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xin</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhao</LastName>
<EmailAddress>silverknightzx@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Atantares Corp</Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>024765653</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6179977857</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>72 WILLIAMS STREET</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1185</Code>
<Text>SENSORY SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
