<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Development of a Natural Language Dialogue System for the Blind and Visually Impaired to Enable Greater Efficiency in Remote Assistance</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Kamei</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to dramatically increase the quality of life and economic independence for the nearly 22 million blind or visually impaired people in the US. The economic benefits include a significant reduction in the nearly $100B in annual economic losses from lower productivity due to visual impairment and in annual cost of social services to the blind or visually impaired.   This project will create low-cost, high-value tools and services that will give blind and visually impaired people the same level of environmental awareness as fully sighted people. At scale, this technology will result in the direct employment of more than 20,000 people to support the service, while also providing millions blind/visually impaired people with the tools and opportunity to join the work force.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The proposed project will develop a real-time, life-enhancing service to the blind enabled by a mix of machine learning and a remote human assistant to create a real-time, semi-virtual, personal assistant with the quality of an in-person, trained human assistant.  In the proposed project, the core innovation is a high-level machine intelligence tool created by integration of  state-of-the-art  Natural  Language  Understanding  (NLU)  software and  Image  Recognition  and  Analysis (IA)  software  with  novel  inter-agent  routing  and  state-of-the-art  Graceful  Degradation,  or  seamless  error handling  and  resolution  by  either  software  or  human agents.  Despite the  incredible  advancements  in  NLU and  IA  agents,  integration  of  multiple  different  software  agents  into  a  single,  context-specific  application remains a difficult and risky development effort worthy of funding by the NSF. By  doing  this,  we  will  (1)  enhance  the  user  experience  with richer  environmental  feedback,  (2)  enhance the  productivity  of  our  human  agents,  allowing  individual  human  agents  to  serve  many  more  users  and thereby  create  scalability  that  will  make  the  service  both  self-sustaining  and  affordable,  and  finally  (3) increase  the  user?s  experience  of  personal  independence  through  interaction  with  machine-based  tools rather than emotionally and socially charged interactions with human agents.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1722399</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Suman</FirstName>
<LastName>Kanuganti</LastName>
<EmailAddress>suman@aira.io</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Aira Tech Corp</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920378411</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9494560460</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4225 Executive Square #460</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
