<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>DCL: EAGER: MAKER: Determining the Efficacy of Maker Activities by Navigating Discourse (DEMAND)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>284560</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Abiodun Ilumoka</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Makerspaces have become increasingly popular in schools throughout the United States thanks to movements like MakerFaire and other grassroots efforts.  However, finding space and staff for a Makerspace can be daunting for schools. The DEMAND project will address these barriers with standards-based kits containing Maker materials, detailed lesson plans, and assessment rubrics.  The kits will be available to all elementary school teachers within the partner district and a lead teacher will be identified at each school. The goal of the DEMAND project is to build a community of teachers and students committed to integrating "Making", using a uniform pedagogy across the school district. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The investigators plan to investigate 1)the efficacy of the kit-based approach to Making (vs. a dedicated Makerspace), 2) the benefits of learning with Maker activities compared to other activities, and 3) the role of Maker activities in learner agency and broadening participation in STEM.  The objective is to produce a well-researched teacher professional development (PD) model for Maker activities. This project will encourage school-based cohorts to attend the PD sessions. The investigators will conduct case studies, comparing individual teachers in schools, and contexts, across the district. The project will explore a new model for engaging more teachers in learning about Making activities, thereby serving as a launching point to expose a wider range of students to Making in various contexts. Additionally, in order to understand learner agency within the Maker process and the affordances for students' problem-solving skills and self-efficacy, the investigators will analyze student and teacher discourse as they engage in Making activities. &lt;br/&gt; </AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1723661</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Albert</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jalbert@citadel.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Citadel Military College of South Carolina</Name>
<CityName>Charleston</CityName>
<ZipCode>294090002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8439535533</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>171 Moultrie Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>058Z</Code>
<Text>EAGER: MAKER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
