<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>National Ecological Observatory Network: Operations Activities</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>46125163</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Roland Roberts</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The National Ecological Observatory Network (NEON) provides a standardized instrumentation and observational platform with the capability to measure the structure, composition, processes, and dynamics of the biosphere from local to continental scales. NEON is the first continental-scale facility designed to enable ecological research on the causes of and responses to environmental change. It provides this capability through in situ sensing capabilities, biological measurements, airborne remote sensing, and data products delivered through a cyberinfrastructure backbone that ensures community access to these resources. NEON supports a large and diverse group of stakeholders - ecologists, educators, policy makers, and engineers - who use the NEON infrastructure and data in their research, management and training programs. Data provided by NEON contributes to collaborative, innovative, multi-disciplinary approaches to educate undergraduate and graduate students. Education and training initiatives include workshops, seminars, tutorials, and data carpentry courses. NEON recruits individuals from underserved and minority communities, through a program that capitalizes on the distributed nature of NEON and the expertise at localized ecological domains to promote broader community engagement.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award to the Battelle Memorial Institute (BMI/Battelle) is to operate the NEON for three years (FY 2018 - 20). The first year of operations is being performed as construction is finalized, while the second and third years occur after construction is complete. The award supports the scientific, technical and human resource requirements of NEON operations. During this operations phase, BMI is exploring efficiencies across the observatory network that will inform full operations, while maintaining the scientific integrity of the data products being provided to the scientific community. BMI is also ramping up engagement with the scientific community to increase awareness and use through the utilization of advisory groups, outreach through workshops, and other approaches. Activities during initial operations provide data essential for addressing the effect of stressors, such as land use change and invasive species, among other environmental factors, on regional and continental scale ecological processes. NEON provides, for the first time, a highly coordinated national infrastructure for monitoring critical ecological properties at multiple spatial and temporal scales. The NEON infrastructure is deployed across 20 ecological domains that span the continental United States, Alaska, Hawaii, and Puerto Rico. Included are 81 observation sites (47 terrestrial, 34 aquatic), along with complementary remote sensing airborne activities. The operations plan is expected to ingest data, monitor data quality, and process data into useable products that are broadly accessible to stakeholders. Additionally, NEON provides research infrastructure in the form of assignable assets to support community-driven research and educational activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/06/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1724433</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Farnsworth</LastName>
<EmailAddress>farnsworthr@battelle.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>11/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Battelle Memorial Institute</Name>
<CityName>Columbus</CityName>
<ZipCode>432012693</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4103068510</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>505 KING AVE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>056F</Code>
<Text>NEON-OPERATIONS &amp; MAINTENANCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7350</Code>
<Text>NAT ECOLOGICAL OBSERVATORY NET</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
