<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAR-PF:   Climate sensitivity in mountain lakes of the Sierra Nevada, CA: controls on thermal regimes and carbon cycling</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>87000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Judith Ellen Skog</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Dr. Adrianne Smits has been granted an NSF EAR Postdoctoral Fellowship to carry out research and educational activities at the University of California, Davis. The main research goal is to examine how physical characteristics of high elevation lakes mediate the influence of snowmelt in determining lake temperature and carbon chemistry. This study will advance understanding of interactions between climate, geomorphology, and lake temperature in high elevation watersheds, as well as landscape controls on carbon cycling in mountain lakes. This study will benefit water resource management in mountain regions by developing models that predict high elevation lake temperature and identify lake sensitivity to climate change. Dr. Smits will directly involve undergraduate students in the proposed research, training them in scientific methods and analysis. In addition, Dr. Smits will develop education and outreach materials that integrate art and science via collaboration with the Art/Science Fusion Program at UC Davis, in order to communicate the results of this research with broad audiences.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The objectives of this research are (i) to develop predictive empirical models of high elevation lake temperature by investigating how local and regional drivers interact to affect lake heat budgets and warming rates and (ii) to quantify landscape patterns and controls on ecosystem metabolism and carbon emissions in mountain lakes. A combination of in-situ high frequency temperature data, remote sensing products, heat budget algorithms, and time series analyses will be used to achieve the first objective. Dr. Smits will improve existing algorithms for quantifying lake heat budgets by including the advectic role of snowmelt, therefore better reflecting the hydrology of mountain lakes. To achieve the second objective, Dr. Smits will conduct a multi-lake survey of carbon biogeochemistry across relevant environment gradients and will use an oxygen mass balance approach to quantify ecosystem metabolism.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/06/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1725266</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adrianne</FirstName>
<LastName>Smits</LastName>
<EmailAddress/>
<StartDate>07/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Smits                   Adrianne       P</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981024521</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1579</Code>
<Text>HYDROLOGIC SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
