<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Calcium in Bridgmanite in the Deep Mantle</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>271735</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sonia Esperanca</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Volcanic activity, such as that seen in Hawaii today and Yellowstone in the recent past, are linked to heat coming from deep in the Earth's interior. Although seismic studies have identified a few large scale candidate structures in the deep mantle that could represent the source of heat or material to feeds these large volcanic centers, little is known about the origin and nature of those structures.  In this project, the team will investigate probable compositional changes in the dominant mineral in the Earth's deep mantle, in order to better understand the nature of the global-scale structures in the deep mantle that could affect our planet's changing surface.  It is expected that the experiments to be conducted in this project will result in advancing our knowledge of the formation of deeply rooted volcanism and their evolution.  Such knowledge is important in a range of topics that include assessing some types of natural hazard and providing insights into the processes that led to the formation of the Earth as a planet. The project will support undergraduate research at Arizona State University, providing laboratory research opportunities for students interested in the geosciences. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Preliminary experiments suggest that Ca, Calcium, dissolves into bridgmanite (the dominant lower mantle mineral) at the pressure-temperature conditions of the deep mantle. In this project, it is planned to measure the pressure-temperature conditions where Ca enters into the crystal structure of bridgmanite.  An additional goal of the study will be to measure the physical properties of Ca-bearing bridgmanite to compare with the properties of the seismically identified large scale mantle structures, such as Large Low Shear Velocity Provinces. The proposed experiments include in situ X-ray measurements at high pressure-temperature and chemical analysis of the recovered samples using electron microscopy.  Because Ca-bearing minerals play an important role in the storage capacity of the lower mantle for heat producing elements, this research project is expected to close a gap in our knowledge of how heat producing elements are distributed among different geochemical structures in the deep mantle.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1725094</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sang-Heon</FirstName>
<LastName>Shim</LastName>
<EmailAddress>SHDShim@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1573</Code>
<Text>PETROLOGY AND GEOCHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1574</Code>
<Text>GEOPHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
