<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Multipoint Laser Vibrometer for Studying Multiscale and Nonstationary Dynamics of Materials and Complex Structures</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>470250</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanne D. Culbertson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Major Research Instrumentation award supports the acquisition of a Multipoint Laser Vibrometer (MPV800) system to enable potentially transformative research in civil and mechanical engineering, materials, and biomedical engineering.   The MPV800 system tracks transient and random vibrations and structural deformations, allowing researchers to monitor the dynamic response of materials, components and systems with challenging geometries and soft materials, such as biological tissues. The MPV 800 also monitors nonlinear vibration and wave propagation. Researchers will gain an enhanced understanding of the dynamic behavior of complex systems that can lead to advances in early-diagnosis of disease, more reliable 3D printing processes and the development of novel materials and structures with enhanced resilience. The MPV800 system will also be used in laboratory projects to educate the next generation of vibration engineers and outreach events for industry and the public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The MPV800 laser vibrometer with 5-optical units and 40 fiber heads enables noncontact and full-field vibration measurements up to 0.5 mm spatial resolution, and bandwidth ranging from several Hz to 100 kHz. This new system also uses a wavelength of 1550 nm for higher reflectance and lower noise in testing soft and hard materials, even materials with high water content such as biological tissues, swollen polymers and hydrogels. A total of 10 major users will use the system to measure the dynamic response of soft, porous, multiphasic, and hard materials with an unprecedented range and resolution in time and space. The MPV800 system will provide essential measurements to update models of sophisticated assemblies in civil and aerospace applications.  It will also be used for noncontact characterization and structural health monitoring of 3D printed parts and tissue scaffolds. Analysis of wave propagation in cartilage and tendons will reveal new insights on the high loading-rate response of those tissues and the tissue behavior that leads to osteoarthritis.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1725413</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Allen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>msallen@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melih</FirstName>
<LastName>Eriten</LastName>
<EmailAddress>eriten@engr.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL STUDIES AND ANALYSES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>028E</Code>
<Text>BIOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>036E</Code>
<Text>CIVIL INFRASTRUCTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>039E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>082E</Code>
<Text>MFG MACHINES &amp; METROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1385</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL STUDIES AND ANALYSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
