<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a 500 MHz Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) Spectrometer with Cryoprobe</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>478169</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI), the Chemistry Research Instrumentation, and the Established Program to Stimulate Competitive Research (EPSCoR) Programs. Professor Leah Casabianca from Clemson University and colleagues Mark Thies, Julia Brumaghim, Sourav Saham, and Nishanth Tharayil are acquiring a 500 MHz nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR) spectrometer equipped with a cryoprobe. This spectrometer allows research in a variety of fields such as those that accelerate chemical reactions of significant economic importance, as well as the study of biologically-relevant species. In general, NMR spectroscopy is a powerful tool available to chemists for the structural study molecules. An NMR is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the changing interactions between molecules in solution or in the solid state. The results from these NMR studies have an impact in synthetic organic/inorganic chemistry, materials chemistry, forensics, and biochemistry. This instrument is an integral part of teaching as well as research performed by undergraduate students. Students from a Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) program are also involved in the use of the instrument.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NMR spectrometer enhances research and education at all levels. It benefits researchers exploring selenium antioxidant mechanisms using 77-selenium NMR spectroscopy, studying nanoparticle toxicity, and determining dynamic time and length scales in ionic polymers. The instrumentation is employed in studying anion and ion pair recognition and stimuli-responsive functional materials.  Researchers are analyzing bioconjugates of carbon quantum dots and carrying out biogeochemical research on soil carbon sequestration. The spectrometer is also used for studying fluorine chemistry, tailoring lignin properties for high-value applications, synthesizing peptoid polymers, and studying applications to synthetic organic chemistry.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1725919</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sourav</FirstName>
<LastName>Saha</LastName>
<EmailAddress>souravs@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Julia</FirstName>
<LastName>Brumaghim</LastName>
<EmailAddress>brumagh@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leah</FirstName>
<LastName>Casabianca</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lcasabi@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Thies</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mcths@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nishanth</FirstName>
<LastName>Tharayil</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ntharay@clemson.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Clemson University</Name>
<CityName>CLEMSON</CityName>
<ZipCode>296345701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8646562424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>230 Kappa Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>South Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>SC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EPSCoR Co-Funding</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
