<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAR-PF:   A Spatially Explicit, Process-Based Model of Regional Lake Carbon Cycling</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>87000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Fellowship</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Judith Ellen Skog</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Dr. Jacob A. Zwart has been granted an NSF Earth Sciences Postdoctoral Fellowship to carry out a research and education plan at the United States Geological Survey Office of Water Information. Lakes contribute significantly to the global carbon cycle; however, quantification of regional and global process rates is based upon crude scaling of site-specific rates to regional and global lake area coverage. These types of scaling processes disregard the complex interactions of hydrologic setting, climate, land cover, and geomorphology and are incapable of prognostication. To fill this knowledge gap, the postdoctoral fellow will develop spatially-explicit models to predict emergent properties of regional lake carbon cycling. This interdisciplinary research will enhance our understanding of the carbon cycle through more accurate incorporation of lakes into regional carbon cycles and enable further work that directly evaluates the sensitivity of lake carbon cycling to climate and land cover change. The postdoctoral fellow will enhance graduate and undergraduate education through design and implementation of an ecosystem modeling short-course at annual meetings of the Global Lake Ecological Observatory Network. Furthermore, the postdoctoral fellow will develop an interactive data visualization of spatially-explicit regional modeling results accompanying peer-reviewed publications to enhance project exposure and public understanding of complex interactions combining to produce emergent properties of lake ecosystems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The postdoctoral fellow will use existing models to develop a process-based modeling framework rooted in first-principles of hydrology, physics, and ecology capable of being 1) applied over large geographic regions, 2) assimilating large and diverse datasets, 3) being reproducible, efficient, and open-source, and 4) forecasting lake carbon fluxes in response to global change scenarios. The project will create three research products with accompanying models of broad interest to hydrologists, limnologists, ecologists, and biogeochemists: 1) lake water and energy budgets, 2) watershed constituent loads, and 3) lake carbon fluxes for each lake in the model domain. At the United States Geological Survey Office of Water Information, the postdoctoral fellow will leverage their expertise in web-based processing of large gridded datasets, high-throughput computing, coupling of surface water and groundwater models, and lake hydrodynamic modeling to achieve the project aims. Using the modeling framework, the postdoctoral fellow will test the hypothesis that contemporary climate change resulting in increased temperatures and intensification of precipitation has increased greenhouse gas emissions from lakes.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1725386</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jacob</FirstName>
<LastName>Zwart</LastName>
<EmailAddress/>
<StartDate>07/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Zwart                   Jacob          A</Name>
<CityName>Notre Dame</CityName>
<ZipCode>465565645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber/>
<StreetAddress/>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7137</Code>
<Text>POSTDOCTORAL FELLOWSHIPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
