<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of State of the Art Imaging X-Ray Photoelectron Spectroscopy: Integrating Nanotechnology, Catalysis, Physics, Manufacturing and Archaeological Research &amp; Educa</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>629650</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jenshan Lin</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of the proposal is to acquire a state-of-the-art high-resolution imaging automated X-ray photoelectron spectroscopy (XPS) system that has the capability to characterize materials non-destructively with one-micron spatial resolution. The high-resolution XPS spectra will help users understand the surface chemistry of catalyst materials used in energy conversion, sensors, additive manufacturing, and quality control of semiconductor manufacturing for sensors and electronics. The proposed acquisition will reinforce many interdisciplinary research projects across University of Central Florida (UCF), led by the PI and co-PIs with complementary expertise, in various research fields including nano-biotechnology, engineering, physics, chemistry, anthropology, and nano/micro-manufacturing. The proposed instrument will allow UCF to become a center of excellence for surface characterization in central Florida and will foster collaborations with local industries. Universities around the country will also benefit through the collaborations with the PI and co-PIs, as well as other committed and future users at UCF and in the central Florida region. The proposed instrument will augment education and training of students through the interdisciplinary research and educational usage of this instrument. It will train students at the frontier of science and technology to prepare them for their future careers in industry, academia, and government.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed XPS system can elucidate the chemical properties of a wide variety of materials used in different research fields such as nanomedicine, catalysis, nano-engineering, quantum information technologies, and anthropology. For examples, the proposed XPS system will be utilized for characterizing materials to understand atomic composition (atomic ratio) and bond/oxidation states information, quality control of raw materials and finish products for electronics and semiconductor manufacturing, unraveling the mechanism of action of the catalytic activity of energy-conversion materials in fuel cells, understanding the defects and impurities in semiconductors and insulating crystals, studying surface changes in nanoparticles exposed to biological environment, studying the surface chemistry of metallic alloy powders used for additive manufacturing, and non-destructive imaging for anthropologists to study the material processing and atomic composition of artifacts. A large number of research projects are expected to benefit from the proposed acquisition of high-resolution XPS system.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1726636</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Scott</FirstName>
<LastName>Branting</LastName>
<EmailAddress>scott.branting@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tania</FirstName>
<LastName>Roy</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Tania.Roy@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sudipta</FirstName>
<LastName>Seal</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sseal@mail.ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yongho</FirstName>
<LastName>Sohn</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Yongho.Sohn@ucf.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Central Florida</Name>
<CityName>ORLANDO</CityName>
<ZipCode>328168005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4078230387</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4000 CNTRL FLORIDA BLVD</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
