<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a 0.7-m Research Grade Telescope for Texas A&amp;M University-Commerce</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>338169</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Astronomical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James Neff</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Department of Physics and Astronomy at Texas A&amp;M University-Commerce will open a new research-grade astronomical observatory at a site near their campus.  The observatory will feature a 0.7-meter diameter reflecting telescope with a CCD imaging detector, along with hardware and control software to allow both on-site and remote semi-autonomous observing.  The new observatory will be used for multiple purposes:  scientific research involving college students, improvement of astronomy classes, training of local school teachers in astronomy, and outreach to the local community.   The project will serve the national interest by making a significant impact on the education of students in the region and beyond and creating an exceptionally well prepared generation of scientists and leaders. The primary service area of the university is extremely diverse and made up of a large percentage of economically disadvantaged communities with diverse demographics. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research program will be led by Texas A&amp;M University-Commerce astronomy faculty and will involve undergraduate and masters-level students from the university, as well as students from community colleges participating in summer programs.  The university researchers will also collaborate with astronomers both nationally and internationally.  The large and varied observational research program will emphasize bright, time-variable astronomical objects such as rotating asteroids, cataclysmic variable stars and pulsating white dwarf stars.  The team will also help characterize newly-discovered exoplanets by making extended follow-up observations of exoplanet candidates from satellite missions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1726357</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Wood</LastName>
<EmailAddress>matt.wood@tamuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/22/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kent</FirstName>
<LastName>Montgomery</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kent.montgomery@tamuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/22/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kurtis</FirstName>
<LastName>Williams</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kurtis.williams@tamuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/22/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M University-Commerce</Name>
<CityName>Commerce</CityName>
<ZipCode>754293011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9038865964</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research &amp; Sponsored P</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1207</Code>
<Text>OBSERVATIONAL ASTRONOMY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7697</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
