<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a 400 MHz Solid-State NMR Spectrometer Console for Advanced NMR Spectroscopy of Complex Organic and Hybrid Materials</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>274750</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) and the Chemistry Research Instrumentation (CRIF) programs. Professor Klaus Schmidt-Rohr from Brandeis University and colleagues have acquired a console upgrade for a 400 MHz NMR spectrometer with solid state capabilities. This spectrometer allows research in a variety of fields such as those that accelerate chemical reactions of significant economic importance, as well as the study of biologically-relevant species. In general, Nuclear Magnetic Resonance (NMR) spectroscopy is one of the most powerful tools available to chemists for the elucidation of the structure of molecules. It is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the interactions between molecules in solution or in the solid state. Access to state-of-the-art NMR spectrometers is important to chemists who are carrying out frontier research. The results from these NMR studies have an impact in synthetic organic/inorganic chemistry, materials chemistry, forensics and biochemistry. This instrument is an integral part of teaching as well as research performed by undergraduate, graduate students and postdoctoral fellows via independent student research and traditional academic research and coursework. The instrument is available to researchers nationwide. Locally, the requested instrument is shared with interested users at Brandeis University and in the Greater Boston area for hands-on NMR measurements. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award of a 400 MHz NMR console with solid state capabilities is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels, especially in areas such as: (a) determining the chemical structure of protective aromatic-rich organic overlayers on mesoporous oxide supports, (b) quantifying functional-group concentrations in cross-linked stimuli-responsive or post-modified catalytically active polymers, (c) studying the structure of catalytically active metal organic frameworks, including the proximity of different linkers, (d) characterizing a biological underwater adhesive, and (e) determining the structure of natural organic matter in the environment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/02/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/02/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1726346</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Klaus</FirstName>
<LastName>Schmidt-Rohr</LastName>
<EmailAddress>srohr@brandeis.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/02/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Brandeis University</Name>
<CityName>WALTHAM</CityName>
<ZipCode>024532728</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7817362121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>415 SOUTH ST MAILSTOP 116</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8248</Code>
<Text>SusChEM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8650</Code>
<Text>Sustainable Chemistry</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
