<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Accelerating Systemic Change Network: Promoting Knowledge Development to Support Institutional Change in Higher Education</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>905141</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrea Nixon</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Over the last several decades, researchers and curriculum developers in undergraduate STEM education have made enormous strides in developing knowledge about effective teaching and learning practices. However, this important work has not yet translated into widespread change in teaching practices, because knowing what needs to be done does not equal knowing how to move an institution or department toward that goal. The goal of the Accelerating Systemic Change Network (ASCN) is to develop new knowledge about how to move institutions to adopt more effective teaching and learning practices. The ASCN will bring together two important groups of people and ideas:  1) the established knowledge about organizational change, discipline-based education research, and institutional economics; and 2) the practical wisdom and the needs of higher education instructors and networks of people who aim to improve undergraduate education. These instructors and networks can use the resulting new knowledge about institutional change to accelerate the impact of their own work at improving undergraduate STEM education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ASCN started a year ago with a team of 24 university faculty and administrators from leading STEM education institutions. These 24 individuals represent various disciplines and have experience in discipline-based education research, education research, the economics of higher education, and institutional transformation. This organization can be thought of as a network of change networks because its members are themselves members of other more specialized change networks. The ASCN has six working groups covering the key issues of successful institutional transformation: logic models, leadership issues, costs and benefits of change, measurement and communication of progress, diversity and inclusion issues, and alignment of incentives with systemic change. The network will be an open network, so that anyone may join if they have the capability to contribute to the effective functioning of the ASCN.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1726315</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
<LastName>Slakey</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lslakey@honors.umass.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Beach</LastName>
<EmailAddress>andrea.beach@wmich.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Henderson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>charles.henderson@wmich.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maura</FirstName>
<LastName>Borrego</LastName>
<EmailAddress>maura.borrego@austin.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Western Michigan University</Name>
<CityName>Kalamazoo</CityName>
<ZipCode>490085200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2693878298</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1903 West Michigan Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1998</Code>
<Text>IUSE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8209</Code>
<Text>Improv Undergrad STEM Ed(IUSE)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
