<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of Focused Ion Beam-Scanning Electron Microscope for Nanofabrication and Characterization</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>640062</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanne D. Culbertson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) award will support the acquisition of a dual beam Focused Ion Beam/Scanning Electron Microscope system. This system meets a critical need for a synthesis, characterization and fabrication tool for materials and devices at the nanometer-to-atomic length scales. It will enable fundamental research in nano- and micro- structured materials and devices, materials interfaces, catalyst characterization and nano-mechanical testing leading to novel material systems such as high strength steels and lightweight alloys for enhanced energy efficiency. It will advance multidisciplinary research programs in science and engineering, ranging from structural engineering materials, energy and functional materials to nanostructured materials and devices and fundamental physics.   This award will also support an array of new educational and research training activities focused on advanced manufacturing, characterization and nano-mechanical testing, ranging from K-12 to graduate levels, which will help develop the future science, technology, engineering and mathematics workforce and increase the participation of underrepresented students.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The dual beam Focused Ion Beam system can produce ultra-high resolution images for characterization and the fabrication of nm-to-µm scale structures.  Key projects include (1) Research on interfacial structures of galvanized high strength steels and lightweight magnesium alloys for automotive applications--to better understand complex interfacial reactions at the nanoscale; (2) Studies of glassy metals to reveal atomic arrangements or clusters on the atomic scale; (3) New avenues for nano-mechanical characterization of Mg-X nanolaminates for ultra- high strength and formability; (4) Probing nanoscale damage gradients in irradiated materials; (5) Mechanical behavior of both bulk and nanomaterials at very high strain rates generated by Laser pulses;  (6) High-throughput alloy screening technique which will enable design of multi-principal component or high entropy alloys.  The instrumentation will enable cross disciplinary research and will dramatically facilitate collaborations with other institutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1726897</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Geraci</LastName>
<EmailAddress>andrew.geraci@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bin</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<EmailAddress>binl@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mario</FirstName>
<LastName>Alpuche</LastName>
<EmailAddress>malpuche@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Siddhartha</FirstName>
<LastName>Pathak</LastName>
<EmailAddress>spathak@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dhanesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Chandra</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dchandra@unr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Board of Regents, NSHE, obo University of Nevada, Reno</Name>
<CityName>Reno</CityName>
<ZipCode>895570001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7757844040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1664 North Virginia Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>027E</Code>
<Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8025</Code>
<Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
