<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI:   Acquisition of a 400 MHz NMR Spectrometer Console to Enhance Faculty and Undergraduate Research at Allegheny College</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>236990</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) and the Chemistry Research Instrumentation (CRIF) Programs. Professor Timothy Chapp from Allegheny College and colleagues Ivelitza Garcia and Mark Ams have acquired a console upgrade for a 400 MHz nuclear  magnetic resonance (NMR) spectrometer. In general, NMR spectroscopy is one of the most powerful tools available to chemists for the structural studies of molecules. It is used to identify unknown substances, to characterize specific arrangements of atoms within molecules, and to study the interactions between molecules in solution or in the solid state. Access to state-of-the-art NMR spectrometers is important to chemists who are carrying out frontier research. The results from these NMR studies have an impact in synthetic organic/inorganic chemistry, materials chemistry, forensics and biochemistry. This instrument is an integral part of teaching as well as research performed by undergraduate students via independent student research and traditional academic coursework. Students work on these projects during independent studies, summer research and senior projects, which prepares them to enter competitive graduate programs and/or industries across the country.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This NMR spectrometer enhances research and education at all levels. The instrument is used in studies of molecular torsion and probes the role of fluorine on carbon-hydrogen-pi interactions.  It is used in determining Gibbs Free Energies, measuring the potential attractions between substituents in organic molecules.  The instrument also serves researchers investigating sulfur chemistries and synthesizing phosphorus-stereogenic frustrated Lewis pairs (FLPs) for catalytic asymmetric hydrogenation. The spectrometer is used to characterize products of synthesis and the protonation of binuclear nickel-phosphido complexes as molecular electrocatalysts for hydrogen production.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1726109</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ivelitza</FirstName>
<LastName>Garcia</LastName>
<EmailAddress>igarcia@allegheny.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mark</FirstName>
<LastName>Ams</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mams@allegheny.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Chapp</LastName>
<EmailAddress>tchapp@allegheny.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Allegheny College</Name>
<CityName>Meadville</CityName>
<ZipCode>163353902</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8143325380</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>520 North Main Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8396</Code>
<Text>Clean Energy Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8397</Code>
<Text>Hydrogen Storage or Generation</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
