<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of an X-ray Photoelectron Spectrometer for Research and Education</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>553700</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Guebre X. Tessema</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With this award from the Major Research Instrumentation Program and support from the Division of Materials Research (DMR), the University of Southern Mississippi (USM) will acquire an X-ray Photoelectron Spectrometer (XPS) with an integrated ultraviolet photoelectron source (UPS) and argon gas cluster ion sputtering (GCIS). XPS measures the binding energy of electrons from the chemical elements in the sample providing information on chemical composition, chemical states, and electronic properties of materials.  This information yields critical information to better understand how the structure and composition of a surface or interface of a given material gives rise to unique properties, function, and performance.  The XPS will be housed in the School of Polymers and High Performance at USM and fully integrated into the Mississippi Polymer Institute (MPI) analytical services. XPS will immediately enhance research in federally-funded and industry supported programs involving more than 14 research groups at USM, Jackson State University (JSU), and University of Mississippi Medical Center (UMMC). Integration of XPS with the MPI analytical services will provide access to cutting-edge surface characterization to local and regional industries, including entrepreneurial startups housed in the USM Accelerator (small business incubator). In addition to advancing research initiatives at USM and regional universities, significant impacts are anticipated on education, training, and outreach efforts via exposure of graduate, undergraduate, and high school students to advanced surface-sensitive instrumentation.  XPS operating principles will be fully integrated into the existing education curriculum focused on soft materials.  Outreach to K-12 and undergraduates via our "Job Shadowing" program, High School Polymer Science Competition, and the summer research experience for teacher (RET) and undergraduates (REU) programs will ensure the next generation of STEM students are engaged with proactive programs.  Overall, XPS will serve as a valuable resource for the recruitment and retention of outstanding students, postdoctoral scholars, faculty, and collaborators, including those underrepresented in STEM fields.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The acquired XPS system is ideally suited to support a broad range of research themes enabling analysis of a variety of soft and hard materials using both x-ray and ultraviolet excitation modes for surface characterization. Key instrument capabilities include large area spectroscopy, micro area spectroscopy, mapping/imaging, and angle-resolved depth profiling.  UPS is analogous to XPS, but the lower photon energies result in excitation of only the low binding energy valence electrons enabling the determination of the work function of the material being analyzed.  A multi-mode argon gas cluster ion sputtering source (GCIS) further expands the utility of the instrument to depth profile soft materials such as organic, polymeric, and biological materials, a unique capability that is currently unavailable in the MS geographical region.  The XPS system will enhance research across multiple disciplines and drive technological innovations for advanced applications in sustainable energy (storage, conversion, and conservation), organic polymer optoelectronics, biodegradable, bioactive and biosensor materials, and polymer composites and nanocomposites.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1726901</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sarah</FirstName>
<LastName>Morgan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Sarah.Morgan@usm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Song</FirstName>
<LastName>Guo</LastName>
<EmailAddress>song.guo@usm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiaodan</FirstName>
<LastName>Gu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Xiaodan.Gu@usm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Derek</FirstName>
<LastName>Patton</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Derek.Patton@usm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Azoulay</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jason.azoulay@usm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Southern Mississippi</Name>
<CityName>Hattiesburg</CityName>
<ZipCode>394015876</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6012664119</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2609 WEST 4TH ST</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Mississippi</StateName>
<StateCode>MS</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
