<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a Variable-Temperature, Wide-Spectral-Range Fourier-Transform Infrared Spectrometer for Enhancing Research and Teaching in a Liberal Arts College Setting</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>307117</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Z. Charles Ying</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This instrument acquisition grant supports purchase of a state-of-the-art Fourier transform infrared spectrometer at Kenyon College. The spectrometer uses infrared waves to study a host of novel materials with potential applications in energy and optoelectronic fields. The research work is performed by undergraduate students in a liberal arts setting. The spectrometer strengthens the research infrastructure at Kenyon College, complementing the existing optical spectroscopic tools on campus. Together, these instruments provide an optical materials characterization facility aimed at serving regional campuses nearby. To enhance educational goals, the principal investigator incorporates experimental activities into existing courses in the curriculum. Additionally, to broaden the interest in sciences, several outreach activities for high school students are initiated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Fourier transform infrared spectrometer purchased through this grant covers a wide spectral range, extending into the far-infrared region, and has the ability to perform temperature dependent measurements. The spectrometer allows researchers to explore the physics related to free carriers, phonons, electron-phonon interaction and band phenomena (including band inversion) of solid materials. Research projects enabled by the instrument explore novel materials, including nanocrystals, narrow band gap semiconductors, epitaxial double perovskites films and optoelectronic films. Specifically, the following important issues are addressed: (i) phonon characteristics of nanoparticles are investigated in order to understand how phonon modes are influenced by the nanoparticle geometry; (ii) several narrow band gap semiconductors are examined in order to probe the band inversion characteristics; (iii) evaluating the reflectivity spectra as a function of temperature, systematic studies are performed to explore how phonons influence various properties of epitaxial double perovskites; and (iv) phonon modes and the electron-phonon interaction in optoelectronic films are studied in order to understand their dependence on the quality of films.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/22/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/22/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1726802</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Peiris</LastName>
<EmailAddress>peirisf@kenyon.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/22/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kenyon College</Name>
<CityName>Gambier</CityName>
<ZipCode>430229623</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7404275114</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>22 Ransom Hall</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7697</Code>
<Text>INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8990</Code>
<Text>Optics and Photonics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9229</Code>
<Text>RES IN UNDERGRAD INST-RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
