<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI: Acquisition of a 4D Microtomography Apparatus for Nano/microstructured Materials and in-situ Nano/Micromechanics Research</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>618479</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanne D. Culbertson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Major Research Instrumentation award will support the acquisition of a 4-dimensional (4D) micro-computed tomography system with capability for fast time-resolved observation of three-dimensional (3D) internal structures at different length scales. While extensive equipment exists for morphology characterization at nano- and microscales, the University of Texas at Dallas lacks instrumentation to observe in-situ internal 3D microstructures, particularly under deformation. The proposed system will advance the institution's research capabilities by providing non-destructive time-resolved 3D structures, critical for development of new materials, and understanding the mechanical behavior under service conditions for critical load-bearing applications. The acquisition of the 4D micro-tomography system will enable a wide range of new research activities with impacts from aerospace to biomedical applications, including low-density high strength composites, bioinspired robots, and 3D printed shape memory polymers. This equipment will enhance the training of graduate and undergraduate students, including a substantial number of underrepresented minority and women students, and will support student science projects at nearby high schools. The proposed system will advance university research capabilities, leading to enhanced economic development in the fast growing Dallas/Fort Worth metropolitan area and the nation.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;The 4D computed micro-tomography system can be used on a range of materials from soft polymers, composites, metallic foams, to ceramics. The large scanning area allows a loading frame to apply high loads to a sample during in-situ scanning.  A fast computer allows control of the system, positioning of a sample, and 3D volumetric image reconstruction from radiographs.  The system provides unprecedented capability to observe internal structures with exceptionally high resolution without serial sectioning--allowing in-situ micro-tomography while a sample is deformed.  The system will enable fundamental research ranging from scalable nanomanufacturing processes for low-density and high strength composites using carbon nanotube sheets, to lighter, stronger bioinspired robots, and 3D printed polymer composites embedded with micro or nanoparticles to remotely trigger local heating and shape memory effects.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/15/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1726435</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ray</FirstName>
<LastName>Baughman</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ray.baughman@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yonas</FirstName>
<LastName>Tadesse</LastName>
<EmailAddress>yonas.tadesse@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hongbing</FirstName>
<LastName>Lu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hongbing.lu@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Walter</FirstName>
<LastName>Voit</LastName>
<EmailAddress>walter.voit@utdallas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Dallas</Name>
<CityName>Richardson</CityName>
<ZipCode>750803021</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9728832313</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 W. Campbell Rd., AD15</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>026E</Code>
<Text>STRUCTURAL MECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>027E</Code>
<Text>NANOMECHANICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
