<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>MRI:  Acquisition of a high performance matrix-assisted laser ionization dual time-of-flight (MALDI/TOF-TOF) mass spectrometer (MS)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>391186</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Carlos A. Murillo</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation (MRI) and the Chemistry Research Instrumentation Programs. Professor Carolyn Cassady from University of Alabama Tuscaloosa and colleagues Yuping Bao, Jason Bara, Marco Bonizzoni and Paul Rupar are acquiring a matrix assisted laser desorption/ionization time-of-flight mass spectrometer with collision induced dissociation (CID) capabilities (MALDI/TOF-TOF MS.) In general, mass spectrometry (MS) is one of the key analytical methods used to identify and characterize small quantities of chemical species in complex samples. MALDI TOF combines gentle ionization (ideal for producing intact ions of peptides, proteins, nucleic acids, carbohydrates, synthetic polymers, and other similarly sized species) with a detection mode that offers an excellent balance between sensitivity and accuracy across a wide mass range. This highly sensitive technique allows identification and determination of the structure of molecules in a complex mixture. The acquisition strengthens the research infrastructure at the university and regional area. The instrument broadens participation by involving diverse students with this modern analytical technique. It is also used in outreach activities, such as the annual Alabama Advanced Instrumental Techniques Colloquium (AITC), which exposes undergraduate students from throughout the region to state-of-the-art instrumentation.  Students in an NSF Research experiences for Undergraduates (REU) program in chemistry and materials science also use the MALDI/TOF-TOF MS.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This mass spectrometer enhances research and education at all levels. It aids researchers in developing techniques for the analysis and sequencing of acidic peptides using deprotonated ions and for characterizing structures, molecular weights and other properties of polymer-ionene hybrids.  The MALDI/TOF-TOF MS is used to examine iron oxide nanoparticle platforms for a variety of biomolecules and polymers. The instrumentation is also used for characterizing host-guest complexes of hyperbranched polyelectrolytes and analyzing polyimines produced by anionic ring opening polymerizations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/14/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1726812</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Carolyn</FirstName>
<LastName>Cassady</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cassadcj@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuping</FirstName>
<LastName>Bao</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ybao@eng.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Bara</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jbara@eng.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marco</FirstName>
<LastName>Bonizzoni</LastName>
<EmailAddress>marco.bonizzoni@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Rupar</LastName>
<EmailAddress>parupar@ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama Tuscaloosa</Name>
<CityName>Tuscaloosa</CityName>
<ZipCode>354870005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2053485152</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>801 University Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1189</Code>
<Text>MAJOR RESEARCH INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1938</Code>
<Text>CHEMICAL INSTRUMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
