<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Symposium IMS Connects - Teaching Experiences INSPIRE, Students ASPIRE, Hawaii Convention Center, Honolulu, HI</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>17215</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dominique M. Dagenais</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed project will support students and teachers, as well as Native Hawaiian/Pacific Islander and Native Alaskan college students (at both undergraduate and graduate levels) to participate in challenging and inspiring conference activities taking place at the 2017 International Microwave Symposium (IMS), which will be held in Hawaii Convention Center, Honolulu, HI, June 4-9, 2017. Support will be provided for an educational program called IMS Connect which was initiated at the 2014 IMS Symposium held in Tampa, FL, continued to be offered in follow-up events and will be expanded further this year. The proposed work will focus on exposing middle and high-school students and their teachers, as well as college students through the STEM Experiences for Students and Teachers Project, to exciting opportunities related to broad technology areas such as electronics and communications.  The students will learn about the science and engineering aspects related to the RF and Microwave field, including various aspects related to components, circuits, electromagnetic approaches, and novel concepts in high frequency techniques from microwaves to millimeter-waves and Terahertz. The project will assist in enhancing the recruitment and retention within STEM disciplines such as Electrical and Computer Engineering (ECE), with broader impacts on improving the engineering workforce base, with commensurate economic benefits to the country.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1727466</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cheryl</FirstName>
<LastName>Ishii</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ishiic@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Ohta</LastName>
<EmailAddress>aohta@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wayne</FirstName>
<LastName>Shiroma</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wayne.shiroma@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>097E</Code>
<Text>High Freq Devices &amp; Circuits</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
