<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research:   Stigma, Civil Society, and Well Being</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>24725</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Deborah Winslow</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Burgeoning scholarship in a variety of international settings suggests causal connections between social stigma and decreased personal wellbeing. This decrease appears especially prominent in resource-poor settings where those of lower socioeconomic status are at greater risk. These detrimental consequences often affect not only individuals but also the wider communities in which they live. Recently, studies have begun to examine links between public activism and individual wellbeing, finding in some cases that participating in such engagement can have a positive effect on wellbeing. It is therefore important to study such civil society engagement through its specific links to social stigma. Does engagement with public activism to fight social stigma increase individual wellbeing?  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research will be carried out by Yale University anthropology doctoral student Elizabeth Berk, with guidance from Dr. Marcia C. Inhorn. The research will be conducted in Lebanon, a middle-income country with unreliable infrastructure. Unlike other countries in the region, Lebanon has had an active civil society sector for many decades, making it an ideal site from which to study stigma, activism, and wellbeing. For this project, she will be looking at the stigma associated with HIV/AIDS. She will employ a variety of qualitative research methods, including semi-structured interviews, participant observation, and textual analysis of a range of media documents, organizational information, and other materials. She will work with civil society organizations, and public and private service providers, such as hospitals and public health organizations, focusing on paid and volunteer individual service providers, those receiving services, and those outlining policy for such services. The researcher will evaluate whether involvement with these groups increases individual wellbeing, or if perhaps other factors, such as improvement in socioeconomic status or family support, play bigger roles in augmenting wellbeing. Findings from this research will provide urgently needed insights into the factors that structure stigma, what efforts have been successful in overcoming this stigma and improving individual wellbeing, and what methods might require rethinking.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/30/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1728061</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elizabeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Berk</LastName>
<EmailAddress>elizabeth.berk@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/30/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marcia</FirstName>
<LastName>Inhorn</LastName>
<EmailAddress>marcia.inhorn@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/30/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7605</Code>
<Text>DDRI Cult Anthro</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1390</Code>
<Text>CULTURAL ANTHROPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
