<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>A Lifespan Conceptual Model of Ethnic-Racial Identity</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>24369</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Chalandra Bryant</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will allow the University of Texas at Austin to host a two-day workshop that will bring together an interdisciplinary team of scholars to develop a lifespan conceptual model of ethnic-racial identity. Ethnic-racial identity (ERI) is a psychological construct that re&amp;#64258;ects the beliefs and attitudes that individuals have about their ethnic-racial group memberships, as well as the processes by which these beliefs and attitudes develop over time. Studies with adolescents show that aspects of ERI have protective effects on academic achievement and mental health in ethnic minority youth and adults.  Unfortunately, there is little knowledge about ERI before adolescence, despite evidence that it begins to develop as early as age 2 or 3 years. Because human development proceeds as a function of the continuous, ongoing, and dynamic interplay of environmental and individual factors across the lifespan, the study of ERI must be based on a cohesive and holistic view of development from early childhood into adulthood. To capitalize on the positive effects observed in studies with adolescents, a better understanding of ERI across ages is needed so that psychologists can effectively develop and implement prevention and intervention programs to promote healthy development in diverse children, youth, and adults.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To address this gap, the scholars involved in this workshop will conduct a critical analysis of ERI in early childhood, middle childhood, and adolescence, to establish when different components of ERI emerge, and to examine the processes through which these components emerge. Specific workshop activities will include a systematic review of the scientific literature; an in-depth discussion of developmental theories relevant to identity development; and consensus-building regarding key developmental processes that guide ERI across developmental stages. Collectively, these activities will serve to inform a lifespan conceptual model of ERI as a construct that develops throughout childhood and adolescence into adulthood. This model can then serve as a foundation for future research on ERI.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/24/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/24/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1729711</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adriana</FirstName>
<LastName>Umana-Taylor</LastName>
<EmailAddress>adriana_umana-taylor@gse.harvard.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Esther</FirstName>
<LastName>Calzada</LastName>
<EmailAddress>esther.calzada@austin.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Austin</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787595316</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5124716424</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3925 W Braker Lane, Ste 3.340</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1698</Code>
<Text>DS - Developmental Sciences</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1698</Code>
<Text>DEVELOP&amp; LEARNING SCIENCES/CRI</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
