<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Improving Vocabulary Learning through Working Memory Training: Examination of Causal Effects and Learning Trajectories</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Soo-Siang Lim</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>One of the biggest challenges in education is promoting oral language development. In particular, vocabulary learning is key for the development of higher-order oral language and literacy skills. New insights from theory and evidence-based approaches will help children build this foundational skill which in turn will ensure success in school. To this end, researchers will examine the extent to which vocabulary learning is influenced by a cognitive factor (i.e., working memory) and an environmental factor (i.e., input frequency and quality). The two primary goals are to develop and examine the feasibility of implementing working memory training for young children, and to develop working memory training on vocabulary learning, with the potential of mitigating effects of impoverished input often associated with children from low socio-economic (SES) backgrounds. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project focuses on the causal role of cognition (i.e., working memory) in vocabulary learning for young children. In the first year, the researchers will develop several child-friendly and engaging working memory training modules to examine whether working memory training improves vocabulary learning in general, as well as working memory for children from low SES backgrounds. In the second year, the training modules will be implemented in a small-scale pilot trial where children are randomly assigned to four conditions: (1) working memory training; (2) vocabulary training; (3) combined training on working memory and vocabulary; and (4) business-as-usual control.  The findings are expected to provide proof-of-concept for development of a causal model of working memory in vocabulary learning,  which can inform the development and design of interventions to improve vocabulary learning.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1729039</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Young-Suk Grace</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<EmailAddress>youngsk7@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martin</FirstName>
<LastName>Buschkuehl</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mbuschkuehl@mindresearch.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yaacov</FirstName>
<LastName>Petscher</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ypetscher@fcrr.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926173213</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>141 Innovation Drive, Ste 250</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>004Y</Code>
<Text>Science of Learning</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>059Z</Code>
<Text>Science of Learning</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
