<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Space Weather Workshop; Broomfield, Colorado; May 1-5, 2017</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>24999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020200</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>S. Irfan Azeem</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is to organize the 2017 Space Weather Workshop held May 1-5, 2017 at the Omni Interlocken Hotel in Broomfield, Colorado. This is a four-day workshop that focuses on the impacts of space weather and explores recent scientific advances in predicting and forecasting. Space weather originates from the sun, which is constantly emitting material and electromagnetic waves. When these impact the near-Earth space environment, there is a complex response including induction of geomagnetic storms, the aurorae, ionospheric disturbances, and a variety currents in space and on the ground. These phenomena as well as impacts to infrastructure such as satellite drag, disruptions to electronic components in space assets, induced currents in the power grid, and many others will be discussed at the workshop. The participants are expected to be (based on past workshops) a mixture of scientists, and representatives from industries impacted by space weather, including those from the electrical power industry, commercial airlines, satellite and navigation/ communication industries.  The workshop is intended to foster collaboration across academia, industry and government on space weather issues, and to promote an active forum among science, technology, economic, policy and security communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The steering committee is comprised of knowledgeable experts from the space weather research and applications communities and includes student representatives.  The steering committee identifies and recruits speakers for workshop sessions based on merit, educational career objectives, and potential contribution to the overall conference experience. The workshop is structured around plenary sessions, poster sessions, and round-table discussions. Undergraduate and graduate students are encouraged to participate and present posters at the workshop. Space Weather Workshop 2017 is co-sponsored by several agencies, including the NOAA, NASA, and NSF.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/14/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/14/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1733978</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hanne</FirstName>
<LastName>Mauriello</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hanne@ucar.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University Corporation For Atmospheric Res</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803012252</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034971000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3090 Center Green Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Space Weather Research</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8092</Code>
<Text>Space Weather Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
