<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference Support:  Trans-Atlantic ICT Technology and Policy</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>42373</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>David Corman</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The European Commission, under its Horizon 2020 program, launched a new project in 2016: "ICT Policy, Research and Innovation for a Smart Society: Towards New Avenues in EU-US ICT Collaboration" (the PICASSO project).  Under this proposal, NSF will provide co-funding for US researchers to participate in a symposium focused on identifying potential technologies for US / EU collaboration at the intersection of IoT (Internet of Things) and CPS (Cyber Physical Systems).  The workshop will address societally important objectives shared by US and EU funding research sponsoring organizations, research institutions, and other stakeholders. This workshop, "Trans-Atlantic Symposium on ICT Technology and Policy: 5G Networks, Big Data, Internet of Things and Cyber Physical Systems for a Smart Society," will be held at the University of Minnesota, June 19-20, 2017. The target audience for the symposium includes leaders in industry, academia, and government agencies.  The workshop will result in greater awareness of shared EU/US priorities and needs in ICT technology and policy and in enhanced collaborations.  Attendance of approximately 100 is anticipated.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop is focused on thematic ICT (Information and Communication Technology), and topics that are of high priority for both EU and the US: Cyber-physical systems (CPS), Internet of Things (IoT), big data, and 5G networks. ICT policy specifically targeting these technical topics is a cross-cutting activity. The PICASSO Symposium will include keynote lectures and dedicated sessions in all these areas. The PICASSO project has produced "Opportunity Reports" in these topics, and these will also be presented.  The workshop will provide inputs to help define opportunities for US/ EU collaboration in these emerging and important areas of research.  The agenda also includes sessions on smart society topics, including smart cities, clean energy, intelligent transportation, and intelligent manufacturing. A final report will be prepared for NSF and the European Commission.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1733876</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tariq</FirstName>
<LastName>Samad</LastName>
<EmailAddress>tsamad@umn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Minnesota-Twin Cities</Name>
<CityName>Minneapolis</CityName>
<ZipCode>554552070</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6126245599</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>200 OAK ST SE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033y</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>ENERGY,POWER,ADAPTIVE SYS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
