<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Scholars Award: What Ought the Public Understand about Science?</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>210060</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick M Kronz</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports research to address deeply relevant questions about how to structure goals for scientific literacy. There are yawning gaps between the scientific consensus on a variety of issues (such as human-caused global warming and the safety of common childhood vaccines) on the one hand, and what the American public believes about such issues on the other. The PI will synthesize recent work in philosophy of science and social epistemology in the context of much social scientific research on science education and communication in order to formulate a framework for thinking about scientific literacy. He will propose a framework in which scientific literacy is construed as a certain kind of understanding of science as a collective enterprise, which has the advantage of emphasizing the role that scientific literacy can play in enabling members of the public to recognize the significance of consensus in science. The results of this project will disseminated so as to capture the interest of science communicators (including scientists, educators and journalists), and to guide discussions about science-based policy and science education, especially in the context of democratic deliberation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the main contributions of the project will be to connect recent work in the philosophy of science on understanding with recent work in social epistemology concerning testimony. Since social epistemology has primarily concerned the transfer of knowledge, little has been done to consider understanding in a social context or apply these accounts to the concept of scientific literacy. At the same time, much of the social scientific work on scientific literacy has been at a remove from relevant philosophical discussions of understanding and its distinctive epistemological role. In making intellectually significant progress on these theoretical issues, this project is poised to promote synergistic interactions between pertinent research projects in several other fields of research including science communication, science education, and science policy.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/15/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1734616</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Slater</LastName>
<EmailAddress>matthew.slater@bucknell.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bucknell University</Name>
<CityName>LEWISBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>178372111</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5705773510</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One Dent Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, TECH &amp; SOCIETY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1353</Code>
<Text>Hist &amp; Philosophy of SET</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7567</Code>
<Text>SOC STUDIES OF SCI, ENG &amp; TECH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
