<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Organizing a Workshop Series on Future Research Directions for Mobile Computing and Wireless Networking Systems</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>49999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Monisha Ghosh</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project is to host a series of two workshops during 2017, at the IEEE Infocom 2017 conference and the ACM MobiCom 2017 conference respectively. The workshops are expected to bring together about 40 members of the wireless networking and mobile computing community for an integrated workshop spanning a half-day, to be held at these two venues. The IEEE Infocom event will tentatively be held on May 5, 2017 in Atlanta, Georgia, USA and the ACM MobiCom event will be held in mid to late October 2017 in Salt Lake City, Utah.  The workshops will help influence future research and development in wireless networking and mobile computing systems. The award outcomes will fuel inter-disciplinary collaborations between members of various communities (e.g., wireless communications, application developers, systems, security, etc.). The reports generated by the workshop can also educate the general public on the importance of wireless research, the challenges, and the enormous potential. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Attendees at the workshops organized as part of this project will discuss and debate the critical challenges in wireless networking and mobile computing systems, and articulate a vision for conducting fundamental and inter-disciplinary research in the area. A tangible outcome of the workshops will be reports that will (i) identify major issues affecting future wireless research; (ii) expose the research community to new and exciting interdisciplinary problems; and (iii) stimulate far-reaching future research initiatives, and collaborations that would help along the evolution of the wireless research community. A core group of participants will be invited individually in each workshop, will the rest will be picked through an open call-process. The workshop will have a combination of researchers and practitioners, across core wireless and mobile systems areas, as well as from some application areas. Invitees will also include a combination of junior, mid-level, senior researchers from academia, industry, and government agencies, with women and underrepresented members of the community being especially encouraged to attend and contribute to the workshop.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1734151</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Suman</FirstName>
<LastName>Banerjee</LastName>
<EmailAddress>suman@cs.wisc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-Madison</Name>
<CityName>MADISON</CityName>
<ZipCode>537151218</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6082623822</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>21 North Park Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7363</Code>
<Text>Networking Technology and Syst</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
