<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Science Policy Research Report: Facilitating the Use of Evidence in Science Policy Making</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>44823</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>cassidy sugimoto</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Results from the SciSIP program provide fundamental science policy insights useful to Congress and science funding agencies yet often connections between academic researchers and policy makers are under developed.  Useful evidence is published in academic articles and is not available in an accessible form.  This project aims to increase the diffusion of new insights in science and innovation policy by providing evidence based recommendations about the most effective ways to enhance the use of academic research in the policy making process.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;This policy report develops insights into the communication of results to policy makers and aims to facilitate the use of science policy evidence in government decision making.  This report focuses particularly on the role of research integrators who aim to bridge academic researchers and policy makers.  The report reviews lessons learned in the earlier evidence based medicine movement to provide recommendations on processes that will minimize known obstacles in application of evidence in professional practice. Four case studies of academic research that had an impact on science policy making are analyzed to ascertain diffusion design elements that increase policy impact. The lessons learned will be integrated into recommendations aimed at facilitating use of evidence in science policy making.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1734579</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Diana</FirstName>
<LastName>Hicks</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dhicks@gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberley</FirstName>
<LastName>Isett</LastName>
<EmailAddress>isett@gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
