<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NRT-UtB: Science of learning, from neurobiology to real-world application: a problem-based approach</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>2999806</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Graduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Laura Regassa</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Learning is the basis of human mental development and the process of learning continues throughout our lives. Perhaps more than anything else, how and what we learn shapes who we are. This project has the dual aims of achieving a deeper scientific understanding of learning, and communicating a deeper understanding of the science of learning to scientists and the public. Over several decades, diverse fields including genetics, neuroscience, linguistics, education, and psychology have generated a wealth of knowledge about myriad aspects of how humans learn, but a grand challenge remains: to integrate that knowledge into a unified understanding of learning based on these diverse fields, and on scales ranging from the gene to the neuron, brain, and human behavior. This National Science Foundation Research Traineeship (NRT) award to the University of Connecticut will help prepare the next generation of researchers to meet this challenge. The traineeship, focusing on the science of learning, will train fifty (50) PhD students, including twenty-five (25) funded trainees, from education, genetics, linguistics, psychology, neuroscience, and speech-language-hearing sciences. By emphasizing a problem-based approach (learning by doing), embracing collaboration across a broad a spectrum of disciplines, and integrating hands-on training in communication and leadership skills that enable effective multidisciplinary project design, management, and scientific discovery, this program will offer trainees unique preparation for a range of careers in academia, industry, and the public sector. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The training program has five major components: an intensive one-year seminar that surveys the science of learning across all participating fields, a hands-on practicum where trainees learn to design and implement multidisciplinary research, faculty-student research interest groups that serve as brainstorming launch pads for new scientific challenges, data stewardship modules, and integrated training in outreach and communication. The seminar provides a cross-disciplinary introduction to the science of learning and the challenge of technical communication, while the practicum emphasizes practical skills crucial in academic and nonacademic careers that graduate education too often lacks: project design and management, budgeting and resource allocation, and external communications. The research interest groups, which will evolve as promising research proposals emerge from the practicum, serve as both focal point for research and organizational structure for the participants. From their first day in the program, students face the challenge of how to clearly and effectively share ideas without assuming prior knowledge or relying on technical jargon, a skill that not only enables excellence in research, but empowers trainees to become ambassadors for their work to society as a whole. This program will also promote diversity in careers requiring advanced training through best practices in recruitment and retention.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The NSF Research Traineeship (NRT) Program is designed to encourage the development and implementation of bold, new potentially transformative models for STEM graduate education training. The Traineeship Track is dedicated to effective training of STEM graduate students in high priority interdisciplinary research areas, through comprehensive traineeship models that are innovative, evidence-based, and aligned with changing workforce and research needs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/21/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/21/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1735225</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Snyder</LastName>
<EmailAddress>william.snyder@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Magnuson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>james.magnuson@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dorothy</FirstName>
<LastName>McCoach</LastName>
<EmailAddress>betsy.mccoach@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stormy</FirstName>
<LastName>Chamberlain</LastName>
<EmailAddress>chamberlain@uchc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Timothy</FirstName>
<LastName>Miller</LastName>
<EmailAddress>timothy.miller@uconn.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Connecticut</Name>
<CityName>Storrs</CityName>
<ZipCode>062691133</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8604863622</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>438 Whitney Road Ext.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1997</Code>
<Text>NSF Research Traineeship (NRT)</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7261</Code>
<Text>PROGRAM EVALUATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>059Z</Code>
<Text>Science of Learning</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7252</Code>
<Text>Perception, Action and Cognition</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7433</Code>
<Text>CyberInfra Frmwrk 21st (CIF21)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8089</Code>
<Text>Understanding the Brain/Cognitive Scienc</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
