<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Reconstructing Hurricane Activity in the Northern Gulf of Mexico: A Multi-Proxy Approach Using Biomarkers and Stable Isotopes</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>15806</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sunil Narumalani</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This doctoral dissertation research will utilize multiple sedimentary and organic geochemical proxies to develop a high-resolution record of past hurricane activity at two sites on the northern coast of the Gulf of Mexico.  The research will provide a better understanding about the hydrologic processes that influence deposition during hurricanes, as well as serve a proxy for marine incursion events independent of overwash sand layers.  When applied on a regional level, the research has the potential of providing new mechanisms for investigating past storm activity in regions that presently lack paleohurricane reconstructions.  Findings from this research will be used for coastal management and risk assessment, and will be directly relevant to environmental managers, community planners and coastal emergency management officials.  As a Doctoral Dissertation Research Improvement award, this award will provide support to enable a promising student to establish a strong independent research career.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Reconstruction of past hurricane activity is largely reliant on sedimentary proxies of overwash due to hurricane storm surge. A primary objective of this project is to develop a new proxy of pre-historic hurricane activity by determining the source(s) of organic matter associated with hurricane overwash deposits. The project will collect sedimentary cores and perform multiple laboratory analyses including chronological, sedimentary, geochemistry, isotopic and biomarker analysis.  The combination of stable isotope and biomarker analyses would provide a sensitive indicator of storm events and will be used to assess whether such overwash deposits contain organic matter derived from marine sources.  This method will also provide information about the complex interactions of storm surge and in-shore flooding processes which are not yet well understood. Determining the relationships between these processes is necessary for predicting the response of coastal environments to future storm impacts, and are important considerations for coastal resource management.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/14/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/14/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1735723</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kam-biu</FirstName>
<LastName>Liu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kliu1@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marianne</FirstName>
<LastName>Dietz</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mdietz2@lsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Louisiana State University &amp; Agricultural and Mechanical College</Name>
<CityName>Baton Rouge</CityName>
<ZipCode>708032701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2255782760</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>202 Himes Hall</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1304</Code>
<Text>EARTH SYSTEM HISTORY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1324</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE VARIABILITY AND PREDICTABILITY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9278</Code>
<Text>HUMAN DIMENSIONS OF GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
