<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Science Policy Research Reports: Educational Videos on Science Technology Innovation</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>cassidy sugimoto</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Conveying scientific research findings on topics related to science and innovation which have relevance to policy remains a challenge in today?s world. This project aims to bring together experts skilled in communicating science and innovation to broad audiences. They will focus on how to produce videos which summarize research findings in an accessible and straightforward manner and consider how computer animation could be useful to illustrate and convey the findings. The aim of the videos is to synthesize, summarize, and clarify scientific evidence and increase its accessibility and utility for those who deliberate over policy. This project will enhance the national interest by providing analytically-based information based on evidence and provide an opportunity to test the effectiveness of state-of-the-art videos to disseminate research findings. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project initiates research that will be presented at a workshop in January of 2018. The workshop has three focuses.  The first includes funding team science, the infrastructure required for interdisciplinary projects, the use of research portfolios in policy-making, and facilitating the use of evidence in science making policy. A second topic centers on innovation and examines the effects of patents on innovation, diffusion, and access; employee non-compete agreements; the use of innovation prizes in government; and regulation, deregulation, and technical innovation. A third focus addresses workforce issues such as entrepreneurial career opportunities for science and engineering postdoctoral researchers and the scientific workforce. The videos will highlight the key points, animate them as appropriate and refer to the written Science Policy Research Reports for further information.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1735409</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Deborah</FirstName>
<LastName>Stine</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dstine@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7626</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE OF SCIENCE POLICY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
