<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Oscillatory phase dynamics coordinate cognitive neural networks</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>481377</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Uri Hasson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>One of the most fundamental questions in neuroscience is how the 86 billion neurons in the&lt;br/&gt;human brain can coordinate their activity to give rise to our amazing cognitive abilities. With&lt;br/&gt;support from the National Science Foundation, Dr. Voytek and his research team at UC San&lt;br/&gt;Diego will examine the role that rhythmic fluctuations in the brain's electrical activity, namely neural&lt;br/&gt;oscillations or 'brain waves', play in shaping how the brain processes information and how&lt;br/&gt;groups of neurons communicate with one another. Using a sophisticated blend of human&lt;br/&gt;electrophysiology and innovative brain-state-dependent stimulus presentation, these projects&lt;br/&gt;will test how neural oscillations route the flow of information influence the brain's activity and,&lt;br/&gt;therefore, impact learning and memory. The results of these projects have broad implications&lt;br/&gt;ranging from age-related cognitive decline to cognitive enhancement. Additionally, this award&lt;br/&gt;will provide the resources for building open source methods and tutorials for analyzing complex,&lt;br/&gt;non-linear neural data, as well as support Dr. Voytek's extensive work in science&lt;br/&gt;communication and outreach. These open science, science communication, and diversity&lt;br/&gt;outreach initiatives will be distributed freely online with code and other materials and, ultimately,&lt;br/&gt;may be expanded into a Summer School focused on training students how to analyze oscillatory&lt;br/&gt;neural data and how to communicate their research to the public.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;These projects will extend our understanding of oscillatory phase as a neural communication&lt;br/&gt;mechanism. This is critical, as oscillations have been implicated in healthy cognitive functioning&lt;br/&gt;by allowing for efficient information transmission, top-down attentional control, cognitive control,&lt;br/&gt;and working memory maintenance, among many other functions. By extension, dysfunctional&lt;br/&gt;phase dynamics may underlie a variety of cognitive disruptions such as those seen in normal&lt;br/&gt;aging, as well as in psychiatric and neurological disease. These projects will significantly&lt;br/&gt;advance our understanding of network phase dynamics in human cognition specifically, and as&lt;br/&gt;a general a computational mechanism in general. This award will also support the development&lt;br/&gt;of a suite of computational tools, open source methods, and code for analyzing oscillatory&lt;br/&gt;phase networks and their computational capacity. Additionally, it will support continued&lt;br/&gt;development of a system for real-time, phase-triggered stimulus presentation, which will open&lt;br/&gt;entirely new avenues of cognitive research.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/11/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1736028</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bradley</FirstName>
<LastName>Voytek</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bvoytek@ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930621</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1699</Code>
<Text>COGNEURO</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1699</Code>
<Text>COGNEURO</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9251</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRAD-SUPPLT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
