<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Next generation submersible flow cytometry for plankton studies: Extended dynamic range and orthogonal imaging</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>600938</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kandace S. Binkley</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Microbes account for most of the primary productivity and biomass in the ocean, and their community structure determines in large part that of higher trophic levels. A fundamental understanding of the factors that regulate community structure requires detailed and sustained observations of the microscopic organisms. This project will fill an important gap by enhancing instrumentation for automated in situ monitoring of marine plankton. The research will contribute new observational technologies that are likely to have broad impact, not only within the ocean research community, but also for local, state, and federal resource managers. In light of on-going environmental change and related projections of increased human impact on coastal zones, there are many new challenges for marine ecosystem-based management and mitigation of human health risks, such as those associated with harmful algal blooms. Strategies informed by scientific understanding and observations are critical and there is growing recognition of the value of detailed biological data sets. Such data sets, as will be enabled by this project, will provide society the information needed to sustain natural ecosystems that humans rely upon for food, water, energy, and climate regulation. The project includes multilevel education and outreach efforts. Research experiences for undergraduates will help promote diversity in ocean science. K-12 teachers, drawn from communities with high diversity and proportion of low income households, will engage in professional development activities designed to promote science literacy in middle and high school curricula.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The researchers will produce the next generation of automated submersible flow cytometers with expanded capabilities for observing microscopic plankton. The work will build directly on their previous experience developing two in situ flow cytometric instruments: one that measures individual-cell light scattering and fluorescence properties (targeting the tiny cyanobacteria common in coastal waters and the smallest eukaryotic phytoplankton cells), and a second instrument that captures images of larger cells, which allows automated image analysis to determine taxonomic affiliation. Two objectives involve enhancing the imaging instrument design: (1) combining the functions of the two current instruments, so that a single instrument can study nearly the entire phytoplankton community; and (2) increasing the power of image-based automated characterization by capturing two images (front and side views) of the larger cells. Both approaches will take advantage of acoustic focusing, a technique by which cells are positioned in flow, to process water samples faster than would otherwise be possible. A third objective is to evaluate the new instruments' capabilities through field tests in Woods Hole Harbor and then to acquire high-resolution spatial-temporal observations on the Northeast US Shelf through cruises-of-opportunity and deployments at the Martha's Vineyard Coastal Observatory.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1736510</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Olson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rolson@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Heidi</FirstName>
<LastName>Sosik</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hsosik@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
<CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082893542</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>183 OYSTER POND ROAD</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1680</Code>
<Text>OCEAN TECH &amp; INTERDISC COORDIN</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5418</Code>
<Text>OCE SPECIAL PROGRAMS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
