<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Student and Junior Researcher Travel Grant for 2017 Computational Geometry Week (CG Week 2017)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>35000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Rahul Shah</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in the 33rd International Symposium on Computational Geometry, July 4-7, 2017. SOCG is a focused conference that considers how to develop algorithms to solve problems best stated in geometric form. Research presented at previous SOCG conferences has had significant impact on the US economy in diverse areas that include algorithms for geometric data processing, computer vision, geographic information systems, manufacturing, graphics and visualization, optimization, computer-aided design, and networks. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award aims to increase the impact of this conference on students, particularly those &lt;br/&gt;from under-represented groups, by encouraging and enabling their participation, especially in cases &lt;br/&gt;where travel expenses would otherwise preclude their attendance. Participation in a top-level event &lt;br/&gt;such as SOCG can be educating, motivating, and useful for networking, both with other students &lt;br/&gt;and with more senior scientists. This support dovetails nicely with the Young Researchers &lt;br/&gt;Forum, a successful satellite event added to the conference in 2012 to encourage and promote &lt;br/&gt;computational geometry research by students and postdocs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/02/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/02/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1737939</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joseph S.</FirstName>
<LastName>Mitchell</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jsbm@ams.sunysb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/02/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Stony Brook</Name>
<CityName>Stony Brook</CityName>
<ZipCode>117940001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6316329949</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>WEST 5510 FRK MEL LIB</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7796</Code>
<Text>ALGORITHMIC FOUNDATIONS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7929</Code>
<Text>COMPUTATIONAL GEOMETRY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
