<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Travel Grant:  MESA USA National Engineering Competition</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>49978</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Paige Smith</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Diversifying STEM is a national priority in which the United States' government has devoted immense resources. Because of this priority, many coalitions and consortia have been developed, involving major foundations, companies, universities, and organizations, to increase student access, engagement, and success in engineering and other STEM-related fields. Mathematics, Engineering and Science Achievement (MESA) USA is a national consortium, founded to focus on increasing diversity in STEM careers by providing underrepresented, secondary students with high-quality engineering and science education experiences. For nearly 50 years, this consortium has been recognized as a national model for promoting inclusion and equity in STEM. One of MESA's signature activities is its annual National Engineering Design Challenge. The main objective of this grant proposal is to create a Travel Grant Program for MESA USA, high school participants to attend the annual challenge in 2018 and 2019. The national competition is the culminating event, held annually in June and attended by many state delegations: a middle school team (4 students/1 teacher), a high school team (4 students/1 teacher), state MESA director and members of the national Engineering Design Challenge planning committee.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;More than 50 percent of MESA USA students come from disadvantaged, first-generation or English as a second language backgrounds, where there are few immediate family members or key adults to foster, support, and/or transmit their engineering career outlook. The proposed travel grant will presents an opportunity for MESA USA students to share and present their passion for engineering by attending and competing in the National Engineering Design challenge and without the struggle and difficulty of finding the needed financial resources to attend such a meeting.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/15/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1737748</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamie</FirstName>
<LastName>Bracey</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jamie.bracey@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>110E</Code>
<Text>EDUCATION RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7680</Code>
<Text>ENG DIVERSITY ACTIVITIES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
