<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SCC-Planning: Smart, Connected, Engaged Senior Communities</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This S&amp;CC planning grant brings together researchers from three institutions (Arizona State University, Drexel University and University of Alabama) and seven disciplines (system engineering and health informatics, community development, transportation systems, computer science, mechanical engineering, electrical engineering and architectural engineering) to understand the unique challenges in senior communities. Fundamental research questions from six research themes are to be studied. The six themes are: (1) community with social connection; (2) smart transportation; (3) health mentors; (4) smart homes; (5) smart sensors; and (6) data management and integration. With strong engagements from senior communities, this project will enable knowledge discovery for design and development of smart, connected and engaged senior communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project includes: (1) Developing a fundamental understanding of the challenges facing senior communities. This project is the precursor to design smart, connected and engaged senior communities (SECSCs). This planning project requires multidisciplinary efforts including social science, computer science and engineering. A significant fraction of the planning effort will focus on community engagement, survey development to identify seniors' needs and critical challenges. (2) Progressive ideas from the fields of transportation, health, and smart buildings will be explored and presented to different stakeholders in senior communities to develop design guidelines for SCESCs. (3) To facilitate the customized solutions for senior communities, novel sensor and data management solutions will be studied and synthesized for developing a smart cyberinfrastructure for SCESCs. What is targeted is an improved fundamental understanding of senior communities, and the customization and use of smart cyberinfrastructures and associated smart technologies to improve seniors' physical mobility, access to information, and living environment. The baby boomer population is reaching its peak in the next decade. While the need for long-term senior care services increases, there will not be enough facilities to accommodate the large number of new seniors. Going from "aging in place" to "aging well with smart technology" will improve the overall health of seniors, which not only directly effects their quality of life but should broadly decrease their medical care expenses, whether provided by themselves or by the government agencies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1737454</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Teresa</FirstName>
<LastName>Wu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>teresa.wu@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jin</FirstName>
<LastName>Wen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jinwen@drexel.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pitu</FirstName>
<LastName>Mirchandani</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pitu@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zheng</FirstName>
<LastName>O'Neill</LastName>
<EmailAddress>zoneill@eng.ua.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Richard</FirstName>
<LastName>Knopf</LastName>
<EmailAddress>richard.knopf@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
