<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>International Solar Fuels II - Young: A Conference for Scientific and Professional Development of the Next-Generation of Solar Fuel Researchers</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>9069</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The award will provide funding in support of participation by U.S. graduate students, post-doctoral scholars, and early-career researchers at the 2nd International Solar Fuels Young meeting immediately preceding the second convening of the International Solar Fuels conference (ISF2).  The "Young" meeting (ISF2-Young) will take place July-5-6, 2017 at the University of California - San Diego in La Jolla, California. ISF2-Young will expose a new generation of scientists and engineers to the latest international research advances in the area of solar fuel science and engineering.  International exchanges of this type are essential for ensuring that U.S. scientists and engineers maintain leadership in areas of critical importance to the environment, sustainability, and manufacturing. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The ISF2-Young meeting (together with the follow-on ISF-2 conference) brings together researchers to share latest research advances in the cross-disciplinary area of solar fuels.  Emphasis is placed on technologies that utilize solar energy (either directly or indirectly) to convert abundant feedstocks such as water and CO2 to liquid chemical fuels.  The disciplines needed to carry out these transformations are highly diverse and encompass many different areas including materials science, molecular catalysis, synthetic biology, metabolic engineering, photovoltaics, and electrochemistry.  The ISF2-Young meeting provides an opportunity for young researchers to present their work in the form of poster presentations and engage in related research discussions with both their young colleagues and senior researchers in the field.  Participation by young researchers will aid in developing the next generation of academic and industrial scientists and engineers needed to ensure a sustainable energy future based on energy from the sun rather than from fossil fuels.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/16/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1737728</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Fenning</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dfenning@eng.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930621</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
