<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SCC-Planning: Designing an Integrated Mobile Application and Case Management Tool to Promote Behavioral Change in Criminal Populations Supervised in the Community</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>99408</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sara Kiesler</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The purpose of this project is to plan the design of next generation probation and parole supervision technology. The goal is to develop a blueprint for BEACON (Behavioral Economics Application with Correctional Opportunities Notifications), which is intended to serve as a community-based offender supervision system that will leverage advances in smartphone-based behavior sensing and predictive analytics, and integrate them with evidence-based correctional treatment and supervision practices to reduce recidivism of criminal offenders being reintegrated into the community. BEACON advances community supervision capabilities by promoting offender change rather than control alone and provides efficient and effective support to enhance offender reintegration opportunities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The plan involves direct engagement of stakeholders from the local criminal justice community to explore both the technical feasibility and functional desirability of the new technology from multiple perspectives, including correctional departments, probation officers, offenders, and service providers. The technical innovations adapted for the BEACON system include low-power smartphone sensing system that captures multi-dimensional behavioral signals and predictive learning algorithms that generate prompts to nudge offenders into appropriate behavioral adherence. When integrated with insights from advances in correctional treatment practices and behavior change theories for probationers and parolees, a comprehensive, interdisciplinary supervision system emerges that offers considerable rehabilitative value and promotes community safety. The results of the project will provide insights and guidelines on how to deploy advanced mobile technologies to the target community, which serves as a foundation for the design, development, and deployment of the BEACON system in the near future.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/24/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1737583</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tingjian</FirstName>
<LastName>Ge</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ge@cs.uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/24/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
<LastName>Corbett</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ronald_corbett@uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>April</FirstName>
<LastName>Pattavina</LastName>
<EmailAddress>April_Pattavina@uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Guanling</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>glchen@cs.uml.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>04/24/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Massachusetts Lowell</Name>
<CityName>Lowell</CityName>
<ZipCode>018543643</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9789344170</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>600 Suffolk Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>033Y</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart &amp; Connected Commun</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042Z</Code>
<Text>S&amp;CC: Smart and Connected Communities</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
