<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2017 INFORMS Applied Probability Society Conference; Evanston, Illinois; July 10-12, 2017</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>7500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Georgia-Ann Klutke</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The objective of this conference is to bring together researchers and students working in the field of applied probability, addressing design and operation of systems that involve random phenomena.  The conferences brings together researchers in engineering, statistics, mathematics, and computer science and covers a broad range of topics, from methodological (queuing theory, dynamic programming, Markov decision process, discrete event dynamic systems, point processes, large deviations, reliability) to applications (energy, healthcare, online services), This award will support the participation of graduate students who will become the next generation of leaders in the applied probability community. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will be held at Northwestern University in Evanston, Illinois, from July 10-12, 2017. It is organized by four leading researchers in applied probability and brings together intellectual leaders from a variety of fields. The workshop organizers have identified three plenary talks and 75 invited and contributed sessions.  The participants will present and reflect upon emerging research in these areas and identify important directions for future research. The conference will be broadly promoted through major professional societies such as the Institute for Operations Research and the Management Sciences (INFORMS) and its Applied Probability Society (APS) and Manufacturing and Service Operations Management Society (MSOM).</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1738406</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ohad</FirstName>
<LastName>Perry</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ohad.perry@northwestern.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northwestern University</Name>
<CityName>Evanston</CityName>
<ZipCode>602013149</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8474913003</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 Maple Ave.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>006Y</Code>
<Text>OE Operations Engineering</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>072E</Code>
<Text>NETWORKS &amp; QUEUING SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
