<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  EW: Champion Air Tracker (CAT)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>750000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project is significant. On the commercial front, this project introduces a disruptive technology in motion tracking. The technology can benefit a broad customer base, including gaming, VR/AR and smart appliances. On the societal front, the motion tracking technology enables new ways of controlling virtually everything around us, which can lead to new ways of education, telepresence, health care, and scientific experiments. Moreover, the novel algorithms developed in the project significantly advance the state-of-art in localization and motion tracking technology. Through its internship program, the project provides exciting hands-on research experience opportunities for students and teaches them how to transfer research into products. Such experience will train them as leaders in future research &amp; development roles.&lt;br/&gt;  &lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project develops accurate motion tracking and gesture recognition systems using acoustic signals to offer four distinct advantages: (i) high tracking accuracy; (ii) low-cost and easy deployment without the need for additional hardware; (iii) easy to use; and (iv) the ability to function under a wide range of scenarios. The technology can potentially revolutionize gaming, VR/AR, and the smart appliance industry, and opens the door to new applications. In addition to designing accurate motion tracking systems, the project will create a software development kit (SDK) and several significant applications that take advantage of the accurate tracking capability.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/22/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1738525</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lili</FirstName>
<LastName>Qiu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lili_qiu@hotmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>09/22/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yichao</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>yichao0319@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/22/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hauoli, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Austin</CityName>
<ZipCode>787201271</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5122035244</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>PO Box 201271</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
