<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The 6th Midwest Workshop on Control and Game Theory; Ann Arbor, Michigan</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>12000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Radhakisan S. Baheti</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Networked control systems or cyber-physical systems, such as those seen in smart grid systems or intelligent transportation systems, and also e-commerce and social networking platforms, are some examples of societal networks that are widely used in our modern information age. The networked control system methodology has even broader applicability with the techniques and ideas aiding in the understanding of opinion spread in a population or the emergence and prevalence of fads. Conceiving and engineering these systems involves in-depth, inter-disciplinary, and collaborative efforts by experts drawn from controls, game theory, optimization, economics, applied probability and computation. This forms the basis for organizing the 6th Midwest Controls and Game Theory Workshop on April 22 - 23,&lt;br/&gt;2017 in Ann Arbor, MI, where we will be bringing together leading academic experts on controls, optimization, game theory, economics and computation from the mid-western states to foster an exchange of ideas as well as research interactions and collaborations between these researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop aims to promote extensive research discussions, collaborations and open exchanges of ideas among all the participants, and to provide mentoring and feedback to the young researchers in the mid-west. The workshop will host two plenary speakers, fifteen invited speakers from other mid-western institutions, and three invited speakers from the University of Michigan, Ann Arbor. All the speakers are leading academic experts in the fields of controls, game theory, optimization, economics, applied probability and computation. They will be presenting their current research work and discussing their research visions. The plenary speakers will also be providing a broader viewpoint of issues and research problems in their talks. The workshop will be open to graduate students and post-doctoral researchers from all the mid-western universities, and these young researchers will be presenting poster and talks on their recent work. The invited speakers list will also reflect the diversity of the organizing committee in terms of involving women and minorities, as also the commitment and efforts of the University of Michigan to promote it. As another refection of the broader scope we will also be targeting an increased overall participation for this workshop from all the mid-western institutions. Strong graduate student and post-doctoral researcher participation will be solicited from all Midwestern institutions, and from all areas in the theme of the workshop.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1738207</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vijay</FirstName>
<LastName>Subramanian</LastName>
<EmailAddress>vgsubram@umich.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Michigan Ann Arbor</Name>
<CityName>Ann Arbor</CityName>
<ZipCode>481091274</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7347636438</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3003 South State St. Room 1062</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7607</Code>
<Text>ENERGY,POWER,ADAPTIVE SYS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>092E</Code>
<Text>Control systems &amp; applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9102</Code>
<Text>WOMEN, MINORITY, DISABLED, NEC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
