<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CT4EDU: Broadening Pathways into Computing by Developing Computational Thinking Competencies in Elementary Classrooms</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>998737</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Janice E. Cuny</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Michigan State University, in partnership with the Oakland Intermediate School District and the American Institute for Research, proposes a project--CT4EDU--that will design, implement, and assess a high-quality, integrated curriculum, and professional development that supports elementary school teachers in embedding computational thinking (CT) into  their classrooms. Currently exposure to CT is too often limited to students participating in an accelerated curriculum (i.e. gifted and talented) or in after school activities (i.e. coding clubs). This is a highly inequitable system in which only those students who have the resources and access can build on CT in their elementary years. By embedding CT into 3rd to 5th grade, in-school science and mathematics curriculum, this project aims to give all students early access to computing.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal will establish a Research Practitioner Partnership (RPP) using a Network Improvement Community approach to identifying problems of practice and points of opportunity in curriculum/teaching practices where CT can intersect with science and mathematics at the elementary level.  Teachers, curriculum directors, and researchers will co-design CT activities and lesson plans in the context of their elementary school classrooms. They will also collaborate in addressing equity issues around engaging historically underrepresented students in CT, focusing on student participation in classroom discourse during CT activities. Finally, the researchers will examine the impact of the CT curriculum on student thinking and teacher practices around computing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/08/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1738677</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aman</FirstName>
<LastName>Yadav</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ayadav@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Christina</FirstName>
<LastName>Schwarz</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cschwarz@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Niral</FirstName>
<LastName>Shah</LastName>
<EmailAddress>niral@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Bouck</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ecb@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>005Y</Code>
<Text>STEM + Computing (STEM+C) Part</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>023Z</Code>
<Text>Computer Science for All (CS for All)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
