<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase II:  Termite-derived enzymatic tree bio-herbicides</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>600000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Brady-Estevez</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact and commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer and Research (STTR) project is a method to control invasive or otherwise unwanted trees and shrubs in an ecologically friendly manner with a biodegradable product. This will reduce the quantity of synthetic herbicides and/or synthetic herbicide adjuvants currently applied to control woody plants. This is especially needed near waterways where vegetation managers must choose between expensive mechanical removal or potential harm to sensitive ecosystems. Homeowners, landscapers, farmers, conservationists, utilities, and other customers will have a new product to control invasive trees and shrubs consistent with a mission to be good stewards of the environment.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This STTR Phase II project proposes to follow initial successful Phase I demonstrations of an enzymatic bio-herbicide or herbicide adjuvant following the principles of termite biomimicry. The objectives of this Phase II project are to identify the mode-of-action, develop high- and medium-throughput bioassays in vitro and in planta, optimize the product formulation, and demonstrate efficacy on various invasive species in the field such as bush honeysuckle (Lonicera maackii), tree of heaven (Ailanthus altissima), glossy buckthorn (Frangula alnus), bamboo (Phyllostachys aurea), and potentially others.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/13/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/13/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1738503</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Scharf</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mscharf@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Bargiel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jbargiel@entobio.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/13/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Ento Bio LLC</Name>
<CityName>Chagrin Falls</CityName>
<ZipCode>440221375</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4124913158</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4230 Lander Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1591</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1591</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8030</Code>
<Text>Chemical Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
