<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the 2017 International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA-44)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yuanyuan Yang</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project will enable students to defray the costs of traveling to and attending the 44th International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA-44), to be held June 24-28, 2017, in Toronto, Ontario, Canada. ISCA is a premier forum for presenting, discussing and debating new and innovative architectural ideas and techniques for advanced computing and communication systems. This symposium brings together researchers in fields related to processor architecture, compilers, chips, and systems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will have two primary broader impacts. First, the ISCA conference will be strengthened as a result of the greater attendance that this travel support will enable. Second, those students receiving travel support will personally benefit from the opportunity to interact with peers and experts, as well as establish connections that will help their professional careers. More broadly, we expect additional indirect impacts. First, the available support will be widely advertised in order to attract women and under-represented minority groups (through postings on computer architecture web-sites and mailing lists). Second, by focusing on students, the project will help foster the mentoring of subsequent generations of computer architects.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1738358</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Tushar</FirstName>
<LastName>Krishna</LastName>
<EmailAddress>tushar@ece.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7941</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER ARCHITECTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
