<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Phase II IUCRC Villanova University: Center for Energy-Smart Electronic Systems (ES2)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andre Marshall</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Data centers are an integral part of life, providing services ranging from social networking, e-commerce and entertainment to cloud infrastructures that provide storage and computing capabilities for individuals and enterprises. Data centers consume over 2% of the nation's electricity, generated mostly from fossil sources.  The Center for Energy-Smart Electronic systems (ES2) was established to develop tools and methodologies for improving the energy efficiency of electronic systems, primarily data centers. Much of the energy expended by data centers is wasted due to operating inefficiencies, including operating more servers than are needed to handle the workload and overcooling the IT equipment, or deploying sub-optimal cooling and IT technologies.  ES2?s research focusses on developing intelligent and fully automated techniques for operating data centers to match the IT and cooling resources to the workload demands, avoiding energy waste while maintaining service quality.  ES2 research benefits society by: (a) providing solutions to reduce the demand on the electrical grid and the carbon footprint and enabling the growth of data center-based services in an energy-efficient way and (b) developing human resources by training engineers and computer scientists in high-demand skills. ES2?s research therefore enables the nation to maintain competitive, agile and energy-efficient cyber services and infrastructures.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of ES2 research is to develop systematic methodologies for operating electronic systems, including data centers, as dynamic self-sensing and regulating cognitive systems that are predictive and verified in real time. At the Villanova site, algorithms and systems are being developed to enhance and control cooling and to assist expert system schedulers being developed at our partner site to schedule or migrate workload in a holistic manner in order to achieve optimal energy consumption. Advanced strategies for cooling data centers using hybrid air-liquid cooling and single and two-phase liquid cooling are being developed and optimized.  These advanced cooling methods anticipate ever increasing thermal densities in data center equipment. Our research is leading to the development of improved methods and metrics for utilizing Dynamic Hybrid Cooling Systems which can be used to deliver efficient on-demand cooling where and when it is needed.  The Villanova site is investigating methods for the conversion of Waste Heat from electrical power consumed in a data center to useful Energy.  More than 90% of electrical power supplied to a data center is dissipated as waste heat, hence our research will have significant impact on the overall energy sustainability of data center systems.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1738782</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yogendra</FirstName>
<LastName>Joshi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>yogendra.joshi@me.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kanad</FirstName>
<LastName>Ghose</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ghose@cs.binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bahgat</FirstName>
<LastName>Sammakia</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bahgat@binghamton.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Amy</FirstName>
<LastName>Fleischer</LastName>
<EmailAddress>afleisch@calpoly.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dereje</FirstName>
<LastName>Agonafer</LastName>
<EmailAddress>agonafer@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Villanova University</Name>
<CityName>Villanova</CityName>
<ZipCode>190851676</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6105196000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>800 Lancaster Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5761</Code>
<Text>INDUSTRY/UNIV COOP RES CENTERS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8040</Code>
<Text>Energy and Environment</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
