<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CONFERENCE: 2017 The Intersociety Conference on Thermal and  Thermomechanical Phenomena in Electronic Systems Orlando, FL</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>9000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jose Lage</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ITherm is a leading international conference for scientific and engineering thermal, thermo-mechanical and emerging technologies related with electronic devices, packages, and systems. Recent progress on electronics thermal management has been motivated in part by increase in microprocessor power densities, power semiconductor lasers, and radar amplifiers.  As the performance density of high-power electronic systems is severely limited by their cooling systems, their need for sophisticated cooling mechanisms increases concomitantly. The conference targets the electronics thermal management community by organizing five specific technical talks on critical topics including Aerospace Thermal Management, ICE-Cool: Intrachip/Interchip Enhanced Cooling, Advanced Cooling Solutions for Photonics, Embedded   Inter/Intra-chip, Cooling, and Microfluidics. Also, there will be six technical panels about Light-emitting diode (LED) Packaging, Thermal Issues for Mobile Devices, Micro-Two-Phase Liquid Cooling Systems, Design Challenges in Internet of Things (IoT), X-ray Characterization of Highly Conductive Materials, and Data Centers and Emerging Technologies. The focused characteristic of the conference is an additional attractive point, especially to young researchers interested in cooling of electronics.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference will launch the formation of the Women and Diversity Chapter for ITherm providing an excellent opportunity for an annual gathering that serves to establish invaluable networking opportunities within this niche community. While improving female participation at the ITherm conference is the direct target of the proposal, this effort should lead also to increasing attendance from the Hispanic, African-American, and disabled engineer groups. The requested support will allow undergraduate, graduate students, post-doctoral fellows, and young faculty to participate in the conference, with special consideration given to minorities and women. &lt;br/&gt;</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/02/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/02/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1740393</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yoonjin</FirstName>
<LastName>Won</LastName>
<EmailAddress>won@uci.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/02/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anahit</FirstName>
<LastName>Raygani</LastName>
<EmailAddress>anahit@nm2-ew.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/02/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Irvine</Name>
<CityName>Irvine</CityName>
<ZipCode>926173213</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9498247295</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>141 Innovation Drive, Ste 250</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1406</Code>
<Text>THERMAL TRANSPORT PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
