<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Belmont International Sustainability Fellows Program: Sustainability in the Human Age, Across Disciplines, Cultures, and Borders</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>206465</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>ICER</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maria L. Uhle</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports a cohort-based, undergraduate program that seeks to help develop the next generation of sustainability science leaders.  This collaborative fellowship program connects undergraduates with today's sustainability science leaders and seeks to provide the students with cooperative research opportunities.  This program seeks to help the students develop essential skills in generating and applying knowledge and developing actions that speed the transition toward a more globally sustainable future.  The students will work directly with established research teams, and engage in activities that will build substantive connections with each group of fellows.  The structure will help to build the next-generation international sustainability science leaders, equipped to collaborate and innovate across cultures, disciplines, and nationalities. The program will produce multimedia educational materials focused on building role models and expanding the diversity of narratives represented in global change research and sustainability science. The program will broaden the STEM diversity in some of urban development's most pressing issues and build greater capacity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1740856</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kirsten</FirstName>
<LastName>Rowell</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kirsten.rowell@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jon</FirstName>
<LastName>Padgham</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jpadgham@start.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1679</Code>
<Text>INTERNATIONAL COORDINATION ACT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1679</Code>
<Text>INTERNATIONAL COORDINATION ACT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7313</Code>
<Text>REGIONAL INST FOR GLOBAL CHANG</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>EGCH</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENT AND GLOBAL CHANGE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
