<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps Node (Track 2):  New York City Regional Innovation Node (NYCRIN)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2022</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>900000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Cooperative Agreement</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The New York City Regional Innovation Node (NYCRIN) will increase the breadth and depth of the national entrepreneurial mindset by mentoring I-Corps teams and training new I-Corps faculty.  State-of-the-art experiential and digital learning methods are utilized at NYCRIN national, regional, and local I-Corps team training events.  Special emphasis will continue on expanding NYCRIN's diversity to all regional underrepresented groups.  NYCRIN will continue to serve as a repository for technology innovation development, data, and outcomes for the NYC region.  Research and execution of innovative and original models based on the data collected enables NYCRIN to effect change in how entrepreneurship is encouraged and brought to fruition throughout the U.S. and around the world.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project represents a continuation and expansion of the NYC Regional Innovation Node (NYCRIN) activities.  NYCRIN serves the greater NYC metropolitan area and portions of the mid-Atlantic region involving Delaware, Pennsylvania, New Jersey, New York, Connecticut, and select other domains.  NYCRIN is a highly collaborative I-Corps Node providing innovation infrastructure, training, and research for the National Innovation Network entrepreneurship ecosystem.  Led by a collaboration of CUNY, Columbia, and NYU, NYCRIN creates and maintains a culture of innovation dedicated to the advancement and teaching of technology entrepreneurship across its region.  NYCRIN operates as an interactive regional network that coordinates and cooperates with all of its regional I-Corps Sites and neighboring Nodes. NYCRIN strives to provide innovators throughout the U.S. with a structured portal for accessing the NYC region's unique combination of world-class universities, venture capital investment resources, and one of the nation's fastest growing technology-startup cultures.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1740622</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Vita</FirstName>
<LastName>Rabinowitz</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Vita.Rabinowitz@cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/26/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Blaho</LastName>
<EmailAddress>john.blaho@mail.cuny.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/26/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Chris</FirstName>
<LastName>Wiggins</LastName>
<EmailAddress>chw2@columbia.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/26/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kurt</FirstName>
<LastName>Becker</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kurt.becker@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/26/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>CUNY City University of New York</Name>
<CityName>New York</CityName>
<ZipCode>100175706</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6466648910</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>205 East 42nd Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8045</Code>
<Text>I-Corps - Nodes</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
