<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Midwest Women in Mathematics Symposium</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>25271</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports participation in the Sixth Annual Midwest Women in Mathematics Symposium (WIMS) to be held on April 7, 2018 at Purdue University. The aim of WIMS is: (i) to highlight the scholarly contributions of female mathematicians in the Midwest region, and (ii) to stimulate collaborations, networking, and mentoring relations among female mathematicians in the Midwest region. WIMS has been established as an annual event that rotates among colleges and universities in the Midwest. The Symposium brings together female mathematicians from across the Midwest at all stages of their careers. Based on attendance at previous WIMS, 120 participants are anticipated in 2018.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Symposium features two hour-long plenary lectures by distinguished senior female faculty members and fifteen thirty-minute invited lectures by promising female junior faculty and postdoctoral researchers. The topics of the academic sessions at WIMS 2018 are Analysis, Applied Math, Geometry, and Topology. Graduate students and recent Ph.D.s have the opportunity to present their work and work in progress at the open problem sessions. Informal lunch time discussion gives useful career advice for both academic and industrial research jobs to young people. The meeting work will naturally lead to follow-up visits among the participants at other Midwest institutions and new long-term collaborations.  More details about the symposium can be found at http://www.math.purdue.edu/calendar/conferences/mwims18/.  This award is jointly funded by the Infrastructure, Analysis, Applied Math, Topology, and Probability programs within the Division of Mathematical Sciences at NSF.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1740959</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Monica</FirstName>
<LastName>Torres</LastName>
<EmailAddress>torres@math.purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keiko</FirstName>
<LastName>Kawamuro</LastName>
<EmailAddress>keiko-kawamuro@uiowa.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1260</Code>
<Text>INFRASTRUCTURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1263</Code>
<Text>PROBABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1281</Code>
<Text>ANALYSIS PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
