<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF Student Travel Grant for 2017 ACM Conference on Information and Knowledge Management  (CIKM)</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Maria Zemankova</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This National Science Foundation award funds Student Travel Fellowships for US students attending CIKM 2017, the 2017 ACM International Conference on Information and Knowledge Management, which brings together researchers and practitioners from the knowledge management, information retrieval, and database communities. The Student Fellowships help cover the travel costs for US students, enabling them to participate in CIKM and interact with other attendees of the conference.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Through the publication, presentation, and discussion of applied and theoretical research findings, CIKM attendees shape the future by identifying challenging problems facing the creation of advanced knowledge and information systems, and by providing insightful solution approaches for those problems. CIKM 2017 has broad and interdisciplinary programs including workshops, tutorials, industry speakers, keynote speakers, research papers and posters, demonstrations, competitions, and other special events.  Students will also benefit from activities designed especially to appeal to them, including a Hackathon, an Industry Networking Day; a resume circulation service; and three data analytics competitions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1741803</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marianne</FirstName>
<LastName>Winslett</LastName>
<EmailAddress>winslett@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7364</Code>
<Text>INFO INTEGRATION &amp; INFORMATICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
