<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Achieving Change in our Communities for Equity and Student Success (ACCESS) in STEM</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>03/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>649994</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Keene</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With funding from the NSF Scholarships in Science, Technology, Engineering, and Mathematics (S-STEM) Track 1 program, the Achieving Change in our Communities for Equity and Student Success (ACCESS) in STEM program will recruit high-achieving, low-income students to become STEM majors at the University of Washington at Tacoma. The program will support the retention and academic success of 36 students by providing focused mentoring, a living-learning community, course-based undergraduate research experiences, and two years of targeted scholarship support. Mentoring activities will include group and one-on-one faculty mentoring in three 12-person cohorts, skills workshops, and a focus group on equity and inclusion in STEM to help develop a sense of community, identity, and empowerment. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Taken together, this ACCESS program will provide supports and experiences that enable more low-income, academically high achieving students to graduate with STEM degrees, bringing a pipeline of talented and skilled professionals into the workforce. In addition, using their increased cultural competencies, the ACCESS research experience will engage students in an interdisciplinary, community-use inspired study of environmental pollution that affects a local Native American tribe. The aim is to prepare ACCESS scholars to help transform the STEM workplace into a more inclusive and welcoming environment. The program team will quantitatively and qualitatively assess the effectiveness of equity- and inclusivity-focused mentoring, that is coupled with community-engaged, socially relevant, early research experiences.  The results of this research may inform other institutions seeking to support the success of low-income students in STEM.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/29/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/19/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1741595</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mary Pat</FirstName>
<LastName>Wenderoth</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mpw@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Erica</FirstName>
<LastName>Cline</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ecline@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joyce</FirstName>
<LastName>Dinglasan-Panlilio</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jdingpan@u.washington.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Emily</FirstName>
<LastName>Cilli-Turner</LastName>
<EmailAddress>emilyct@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marc</FirstName>
<LastName>Nahmani</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mnahmani@uw.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/29/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Washington</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2065434043</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4333 Brooklyn Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
