<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>60th IEEE International Midwest Symposium on Circuits and Systems:  Support for Student Participation, August 6 - 9, 2017. Tufts University, Boston, MA</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed project will support junior researchers from the US to attend the 60th IEEE International Midwest Symposium on Circuits and Systems (MWSCAS) to be held at Tufts University from August 6 - 9, 2017.  The Symposium will provide a platform for the exchange of research-driven ideas in all aspects of integrated circuits and systems, including circuit theory, design and implementation. The technical areas addressed include: Analog and Mixed-Signal Circuits and Systems, Digital Circuits and Systems, Communications Circuits and Systems, RF and Wireless Circuits and Systems, Sensor Circuits and Systems, Biomedical Circuits and Systems, Converter Circuits and Systems, Signal and Image Processing, Power Management, Power Harvesting and Power Electronics, Nano-electronics Technology, and Hardware Security. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A diverse group of academic and industry professionals will be brought together on the occasion of the Symposium and will have the opportunity to discuss a wide range of topics such as wireless communications, radar systems, robotics, biosensors, cyber-physical systems, and security. Emphasis will be given on participation of junior researchers from under-represented groups. The Symposium announcements will be distributed to student chapters of various organizations and will be announced to relevant academic departments at minority-serving institutions.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1741996</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Valencia</FirstName>
<LastName>Koomson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>vkoomson@ece.tufts.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Tufts University</Name>
<CityName>Boston</CityName>
<ZipCode>021111817</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6176273696</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>136 Harrison Ave</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
