<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Point-of-Care Physiological Assessment</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>04/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cindy WalkerPeach</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to transform health, wellness, and disease assessment and monitoring by developing a simple, cost-effective method of exhaled air analysis. This technology can be used in diverse scenarios, including in the hospital, primary care settings, in the field, and directly by the end-user. The long term potential impact of this technology is the ability to collect physiological measurements frequently, non-invasively, and deliver results instantaneously. Infrequent measurements or delays in diagnostic results can lead to avoidable morbidity, mortality, and direct emergency/terminal care costs. This technology is capable of addressing unmet monitoring and diagnostic needs in a wide variety of clinical and health &amp; wellness applications, representing a multibillion dollar value creation opportunity impacting stakeholders throughout the value chain.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project aims to develop a technology platform that will enable accurate and cost effective breath gas analysis at the point-of-care.  The breath test is made possible by carbon nanotube chemiresistor sensor scheme and device integration advancements. This project has a novel approach to selective detection of gases at part-per-billion concentrations using a smartphone and near field communication tags modified with a simple two-step process. The technology platform consists of a circuit design, data transfer method, fabrication process, and chemiresistor formulations to enable molecularly-specific detection of biomarkers at biologically relevant (part-per-billion) concentrations in exhaled breath.  This technology produces a chemically-specific, concentration-dependent electrical output without compromising on the pattern recognition benefits of 'electronic nose' solutions. This work may also yield general advancements in chemical sensor performance optimization and thin-film electronics roll-to-roll manufacturing techniques.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1741052</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roman</FirstName>
<LastName>Lubynsky</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rml@mit.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/03/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Massachusetts Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>Cambridge</CityName>
<ZipCode>021394301</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6172531000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>77 MASSACHUSETTS AVE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
