<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Supporting Science Students through Scholarships, Academic and Social Activities, and Reflective Journaling</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>649901</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Teles</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With funding from the National Science Foundation's Scholarships in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (S-STEM) program, this project at Joliet Junior College is designed to address the ever-increasing need in Illinois and surrounding areas for highly qualified STEM professionals. It will add to the local, regional, and national understanding of learning as it enhances student retention, performance, graduation, and peer support networks. A structured research study will be used to determine the impact of course specific tutoring, mentoring, and reflective journaling among students in STEM courses. The project will also assess and track the metacognitive skills that students use to advance their scientific thinking. Data reflecting the activities will be used to improve the program for all participants, as well as inform the academic community through conference papers and presentations at national and regional conferences. Each of these areas will be evaluated by an external evaluator using surveys, rubrics, and performance in specific courses to gather both quantitative and qualitative information about the project. Due to the demographics of the institution and the targeted recruitment of women and other underrepresented groups from both high schools and the college, the project will help to diversify the workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;To increase the number of academically talented students with demonstrated financial need who begin and complete a STEM program of study, the college will integrate scholarships and academic support with STEM faculty mentoring, reflective journaling, social cohorts, hands-on experiential learning through relevant research projects, and exposure to industry leaders and topics to provide scholars a pathway to success in STEM fields. Involvement in STEM classes, increased faculty mentoring geared to specific student needs, and reflective journals will encourage students to embrace the STEM community and find their own identity within it, while simultaneously learning how to mentor the next generation of scientists. Information gathered during classes, mentoring, reflective journals, student evaluations will inform the wider STEM community at the college, as well as increase awareness of student group building within the college student academic and support programs.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/09/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/09/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1741934</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cathleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Dobbs</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cdobbs@jjc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>11/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrew</FirstName>
<LastName>Morrison</LastName>
<EmailAddress>amorriso@jjc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>11/09/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Joliet Junior College</Name>
<CityName>Joliet</CityName>
<ZipCode>604318938</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8152802240</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1215 Houbolt Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
