<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2017 Interdisciplinary Biomass Burning Initiative (IBBI) Workshop; Boulder, Colorado; July 10-12, 2017</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia A. Edgerton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This effort supports a workshop that brings together a group of atmospheric chemistry researchers from universities, government laboratories, and private research institutes, to promote awareness within the international community of scientific research to improve the understanding of emissions from open biomass burning around the world. This activity is part of the Interdisciplinary Biomass Burning Initiative (IBBI) sponsored by the International Global Atmospheric Chemistry (IGAC) Project.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of the workshop are to (1) bring awareness to the international biomass burning community of upcoming US-led field campaigns to study wildfires; (2) Identify ways in which the international community can apply the methods and results from US wildfire studies to other regions; (3) Identify existing observational databases on wildfires that can be analyzed as part of a larger synthesis effort; and (4) Determine ways in which the US led field campaigns can contribute to improvements in the models and observations of fire behavior and the links between wildfires, air quality, and climate change. The workshop will also provide an opportunity for young scientists to meet, network, and exchange ideas with leaders in the field of atmospheric sciences.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1741152</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Megan</FirstName>
<LastName>Melamed</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Megan@igacproject.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
