<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshops to Broaden the Participation of HBCU STEM Faculty in NSF's Education Research-focused Programs</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>559471</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Claudia M. Rankins</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This conference project at the Quality Education for Minorities (QEM) Network will coordinate and oversee two workshops and a series of webinars about research on science, technology, engineering and mathematics (STEM) education for faculty from Historically Black Colleges and Universities (HBCUs). Workshops will focus on enhancing the ability of faculty to focus on preparing proposals for the rigorous study and broad dissemination of the critical pedagogies and culturally sensitive interventions that contribute to the success of HBCUs in educating African American STEM undergraduates. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshops will involve a minimum of 90 STEM faculty from HBCUs. Webinars for pre and post workshop activities are expected to involve up to 500 faculty.  Critical to this capacity-building effort will be a focus on understanding the current research context and expectations for competitive participation in STEM education opportunities, such as proposals for the Broadening Participation Research, EHR Core Research and Faculty Early Career Development programs offered by the National Science Foundation.  Workshops and webinars will provide intensive training to help faculty from HBCUs to fully participate in and contribute to national STEM education goals. This aligns with the Foundation's strategic direction for broadening participation in STEM through innovation and research. Project-related materials will be made available online to ensure broad dissemination of information.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/23/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1741718</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>IVORY</FirstName>
<LastName>TOLDSON</LastName>
<EmailAddress>itoldson@qem.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>QUALITY EDUCATION FOR MINORITIES NETWORK</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200362406</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2026591818</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1818 N ST NW</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
