<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The Price of STEM Success: Explaining the Impact of Need-Based Financial Aid on STEM Student Behavior</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/23/2016</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>921542</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040200</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Connie K. Della-Piana</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This four-year mixed methods research project is investigating whether, how, and why need-based financial aid affects the behavior and success of undergraduate students in STEM programs.  The primary goal of the study is to estimate the causal effects of financial aid on choice of and success in a STEM program or major.  The project tracks and compares 1,800 low-income students (900 students randomly selected to receive additional financial support with 900 students with similar economic backgrounds who do not receive additional support).  The randomized control study tests three hypotheses associated with the assumption that financial aid assists in student degree completion.  Hypothesis One:  Additional financial aid will reduce the number of hours spent working and the number of students working more than 20 hours per week will decline.  Hypothesis Two:  An increase in financial aid will stimulate an improvement of the quality of study time and that this will lead recipients to attempt more credits in STEM and achieve higher grades.  Hypothesis Three: Additional funding will permit recipients to increase their participation in STEM enrichment activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/04/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1741786</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
<LastName>Goldrick-Rab</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sgr@temple.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Temple University</Name>
<CityName>Philadelphia</CityName>
<ZipCode>191226003</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2157077547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1801 N. Broad Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
