<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: The effects of soil moisture on fungal weathering, diversity, and abundance.</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>29816</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Richard Yuretich</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>ABSTRACT&lt;br/&gt;   &lt;br/&gt;A non-technical description explaining the broader significance of the project&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Soil is arguably the most important physical resource that exists at the Earth's surface. It is essential for the growth and development of our food supply and soils help regulate the composition of the atmosphere. Despite this central role, knowledge of the processes of soil formation is still very rudimentary. Microbial activity has a principal role in breaking down rocks into fertile soil and identifying the major mechanisms and types of microorganisms is an ongoing research activity. Fungi are a class of these microbes that have received little attention, but likely are very important contributors to soil generation. This project will take a close look at the abundance and distribution of fungi in soils, their activity as a function of moisture availability, and the possible role they play in soil formation under a variety of climatic conditions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;A technical description of the project&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will explore the relationship between moisture content of soils and fungal weathering of igneous rocks, estimate fungal weathering rates, and identify and quantify the fungal community. The study will examine responses of the fungal community to decreasing soil moisture content (drought) and the processes facilitated by mycorrhizal fungi to help plants cope with water stress. These will be tested by collecting soil samples along a climate gradient, and then interrogate these samples by using DNA and aquaporin (integral membrane proteins) analyses, and microscopic and spectroscopic techniques. The project will use the Catalina-Jemez Critical Zone Observatories and the Landscape Evolution Observatory at Biosphere 2 of University of Arizona, which provide opportunities to study processes along a climate gradient. Four undergraduates from a Primarily Undergraduate Institution will assist with the project and the results will be used to augment general science education.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1742941</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Zsuzsanna</FirstName>
<LastName>Balogh-Brunstad</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Balogh_brunZ@hartwick.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hartwick College</Name>
<CityName>Oneonta</CityName>
<ZipCode>138204020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6074314990</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One Hartwick Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7693</Code>
<Text>CZO: CRITICAL ZONE OBSER SOLIC</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7273</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL RESEARCH &amp; EDUCA</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7693</Code>
<Text>CZO: CRITICAL ZONE OBSER SOLIC</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
