<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Creative Programming for K12 Technology Education</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>0</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to create replicable methods to equip as many students as possible with advanced technical skills to contribute to the most technologically advanced generation in human civilization. Skillsets learned through programs implemented may stimulate a desire for students to dive deeper into technology, empower schools to educate students through hands-on and applied learning methods, and provide students with the skills to become programmers, freelancers, entrepreneurs, and other professionals requiring a certain level of technology sophistication.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is focused on the implementation of creative and unique kid-friendly content that teaches students applied technology skillsets, distinguishing them from their peers. This project is testing and collecting feedback on a variety of methods for curriculum delivery of the program, including school partnerships, school licensing, and direct-to-consumer delivery. Student participants as young as 4 years old undertaking these specific tech programs gain the insight and motivation to pursue technologically advanced skills.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1742967</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Runge</LastName>
<EmailAddress>janet.runge@unlv.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nevada Las Vegas</Name>
<CityName>Las Vegas</CityName>
<ZipCode>891541055</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7028951357</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4505 MARYLAND PARKWAY</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nevada</StateName>
<StateCode>NV</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
