<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Biology Transitions</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>961151</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>rupa iyer</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With funding from the National Science Foundation's Scholarships in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (S-STEM) program, the Biology Transitions program is providing support to low-income students with demonstrated financial need and academic promise to succeed in STEM disciplines at Lewis University. The project is funding 28 scholarships over 5 years for transfer students who are pursuing bachelor's degrees in biological sciences. The program will expose students to a learning model that emphasizes critical thinking and problem solving, while providing support to transfer students as they transition to a 4-year institution from community college. The supports developed to help transfer students overcome barriers to graduation will have a broad impact on an array of disciplines.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Lewis University's Biology Transitions program will increase the number of underrepresented, economically disadvantaged students who complete 4-year degrees and enter the STEM workforce directly or after completing a graduate program, helping to advance scientific knowledge and provide needed, qualified STEM professionals. Biology Transitions will establish a sustainable and replicable model of communication between area community colleges and Lewis University and develop effective programming between them, providing a supportive pathway for underrepresented, economically disadvantaged transfer students to be successful in a 4-year university environment. In addition to scholarships, the program will incorporate intensive mentoring, academic support, and undergraduate research opportunities to ensure that at least 80% of Biology Transitions participants will persist to graduation.  Professional guidance in the internship, graduate, and professional school application processes will advance students toward STEM professions and increase the number of graduating scholars who continue in a STEM field through employment or graduate school.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/10/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/10/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1742094</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marne</FirstName>
<LastName>Bailey</LastName>
<EmailAddress>baileyma@lewisu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/10/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Pifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Jeanette</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Piferje@lewisu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/10/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lauren</FirstName>
<LastName>Rentfro</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rentfrla@lewisu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/10/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Lewis University</Name>
<CityName>Romeoville</CityName>
<ZipCode>604462200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8158365129</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One University Parkway</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1536</Code>
<Text>S-STEM:SCHLR SCI TECH ENG&amp;MATH</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
