<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: 2019 AGEP National Research Meeting</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>99876</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11060000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Human Resource Development</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mark H. Leddy</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Alliances for Graduate Education and the Professoriate (AGEP) program funds research and the development, implementation, and investigation of models to transform the dissertation phase of doctoral education, postdoctoral training and/or faculty advancement of historically underrepresented minorities (URMs) in Science, Technology, Engineering and Mathematics (STEM) and/or STEM education research.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference convening will bring together nearly 200 principal investigators who have been funded by AGEP to develop, implement and test models of graduate education, postdoctoral scholar training and faculty professional advancement with historically underrepresented minorities in STEM disciplines and STEM education research fields.  The goals of the conference are to: (1) Serve as a forum for presenting model components from AGEP awardees for transforming graduate education, postdoctoral training, and faculty advancement in STEM that show the greatest potential for reproducibility, scalability, and sustainability across our Nation?s postsecondary institutions; (2) Provide professional development opportunities to advance participant knowledge of the academic and professional preparation for diverse STEM CAREER pathways into the professoriate; and (3) Provide professional development about NSF strategic priorities, policies, and procedures that foster broadening participation in STEM doctoral programs and the professoriate.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The two and half-day conference is scheduled for May of 2019.  In addition to research panels, presentations and poster sessions, there will be opportunities for highly interactive discussions and activities, keynote addresses and plenary sessions.  Discussions will be focused on the AGEP Alliances and models, and on those model components with the greatest intellectual merit potential for reproducibility, scalability and sustainability.  The proposed work includes both evaluation and dissemination plans for broader impacts.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/30/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1742346</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lori</FirstName>
<LastName>Carris</LastName>
<EmailAddress>carris@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lori</FirstName>
<LastName>Carris</LastName>
<EmailAddress>carris@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/30/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/25/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>William</FirstName>
<LastName>Andrefsky</LastName>
<EmailAddress>and@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/30/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>08/25/2017</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kelly</FirstName>
<LastName>Ward</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kaward@wsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/30/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Washington State University</Name>
<CityName>PULLMAN</CityName>
<ZipCode>991641060</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5093359661</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>280 Lighty</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1515</Code>
<Text>AGEP</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1515</Code>
<Text>MINORITY GRADUATE EDUC ACTIVIT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8816</Code>
<Text>Workforce Development</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
