<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Mesoscale Vortex Dynamics in Tropical Weather Systems</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>116346</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nicholas F. Anderson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Tropical cyclone development remains a difficult forecast problem.  The objective of this research project is to study the complex motions that occur in a tropical weather system and how they interact to either assist or hinder tropical cyclone development.  The impact of the project will be to help improve tropical cyclone forecast models that are relied upon for public safety.  The project also includes an internship opportunity to enhance workforce development. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project is focused on the nature and consequences of complex mesoscale vortex interactions that occur in tropical weather systems.  The research activities will advance knowledge of the mechanisms that control mesoscale vortex merger and alignment under various scenarios, when oceanic surface fluxes, cloud processes and radiation have the potential to strongly affect the dynamics.  Idealized numerical modeling using the Cloud Model 1 model will comprise the bulk of the study and is intended to help answer the main two research questions:  1) How do mesoscale vortex interactions influence tropical cyclone development? 2) How do diabatic mesoscale vortices interact, and what controls the nature of their interaction?&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/02/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/02/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1743854</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Schecter</LastName>
<EmailAddress>schecter@nwra.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/02/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>NorthWest Research Associates, Incorporated</Name>
<CityName>Redmond</CityName>
<ZipCode>980525164</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4255569055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4118 148th Ave NE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL &amp; DYNAMIC METEOROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
