<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: Dawn III: What's next for Gravitational Wave Astronomy?  workshop to be held in Syracuse, NY, July 6-7 2017</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Pedro Marronetti</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the observation of the first two confirmed gravitational-wave events by LIGO during its first observation run, and with the second observation run ongoing, gravitational-wave astronomy has become a reality. The workshop supported by this award, entitled "DAWN III - What's Next for Gravitational Wave Astronomy?" aims at forging a global strategy on how to proceed with the next generation gravitational wave detectors and host facilities. This workshop, the third in the annual DAWN series, also follows the 8th Einstein Telescope Symposium: "Toward a global 3G GW network", held at the University of Birmingham on March 27/28 2017, which highlighted the need for further international collaboration.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop will be held in Syracuse, NY, at the Marriott Syracuse Downtown hotel on July 6-7, 2017. The two-day program will focus on the global strategy for third-generation (3G) gravitational wave observatories and detectors, and their science case. Of particular interest is the proper coordination between the European effort proposing to build an observatory detailed by the "Einstein Telescope" design study, and the U.S. proposal of a similar class observatory, named "Cosmic Explorer". About 60 participants from around the world are expected. As in the case of the previous DAWN workshops, the outcome of the meeting will be summarized in a report that will be made publicly available.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/18/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1743270</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stefan</FirstName>
<LastName>Ballmer</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sballmer@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Manuela</FirstName>
<LastName>Campanelli</LastName>
<EmailAddress>manuela@astro.rit.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1252</Code>
<Text>LIGO RESEARCH SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
