<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel funding for 2017 Logic Mentoring Workshop (LMW) at (LICS); Reykjavik, Iceland; June, 2017</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>14630</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nina Amla</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant will enable students to attend the Logic Mentoring Workshop (LMW 2017) which will be co-located with the International ACM/IEEE Symposium on Logic in Computer Science (LICS) to be held in Reykjavik (Iceland), June 2017. LICS is one of the premier conferences in computer science, dedicated to the advancement of the logic and semantics. The purpose of Logic Mentoring Workshop is to provide mentoring and career advice to early-stage graduate students, to attract them to pursue research careers in the area of computer-aided verification. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Attending a conference can be a transformative experience for young researchers. It exposes them to cutting-edge research and can help them make connections to other students and senior researchers in the area. The funded students will attend LICS, a top conference where they will learn about current research problems and interact with leaders in the field, and the LMW workshop which will focus on mentoring and career advice specific to early-stage graduate students who aim to pursue research careers in the area of computer-aided verification.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/15/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1743546</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Koskinen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>eric.koskinen@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7943</Code>
<Text>PROGRAMMING LANGUAGES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8206</Code>
<Text>Formal Methods and Verification</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
