<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Travel Grant to Attend Big Data in Software Engineering Track</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>10880</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sol J. Greenspan</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This grant supports participants to attend the Big Data in Software Engineering track of the Midwest Big Data Summer School. The Midwest Big Data Summer School series is a 5-day training activity for Early Career Researchers. The 2017 edition of the event will be held on July 10-14, 2017 in Ames, Iowa. This summer school is a one-week, intensive curriculum aimed at early career researchers to get them started in data-driven research.  The school includes full-day lectures on topics ranging from data acquisition, data preprocessing, exploratory data analysis, descriptive data analysis, data analysis tools and techniques, visualization and communication, ethical issues in data science, reproducibility and repeatability, and understanding of domain/context. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In the field of Software Engineering, big data analytics for empirical research has expanded as a research area. The Big Data in Software Engineering track at the Summer School will train researchers on the skills, tools and techniques to perform this research. Overall, it is a community building activity that may stimulate research collaborations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/05/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/05/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1743070</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hridesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Rajan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hridesh@iastate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/05/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Iowa State University</Name>
<CityName>AMES</CityName>
<ZipCode>500112207</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5152945225</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1138 Pearson</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Iowa</StateName>
<StateCode>IA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7944</Code>
<Text>SOFTWARE ENG &amp; FORMAL METHODS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
