<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<rootTag>
  <Award>
    <AwardTitle>Week of the Arctic International Conference</AwardTitle>
    <AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
    <AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
    <AwardAmount>70000</AwardAmount>
    <AwardInstrument>
      <Value>Standard Grant</Value>
    </AwardInstrument>
    <Organization>
      <Code>06090100</Code>
      <Directorate>
        <LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
      </Directorate>
      <Division>
        <LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
      </Division>
    </Organization>
    <ProgramOfficer>
      <SignBlockName>Marc Stieglitz</SignBlockName>
    </ProgramOfficer>
    <AbstractNarration>This grant is to give partial support to convene the 2017 Week of the Arctic in Fairbanks, Alaska, USA. This event will be a gathering of researchers, policy makers, and stakeholders from around the Arctic and the world, to share their observations and intentions, their understandings, and their challenges so that we may make greater scientific advances, more informed decisions, and better use limited research and planning resources. This event will occur at the time when the chairmanship of the international Arctic Council changes from the US to Finland and will provide an appropriate opportunity to profile the many products and accomplishments attained under US chairmanship, while planning and engaging in the coordination of future research efforts in this dynamic region of the planet.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;There will be dozens of activities associated with this meeting, and each will advance some aspect of Arctic science, engineering, technology and/or policy. The event is designed to optimize interpersonal communications that are often the essential precursor to new collaborations, new positions for students, and greater understanding for all.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Arctic Council Ministerial draws ministerial level officials, and consequently a very large press contingent. This effort will take full advantage of this access to international journalists to maximize outreach and promote science further that documents the importance of the Arctic</AbstractNarration>
    <MinAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
    <MaxAmdLetterDate>05/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
    <ARRAAmount/>
    <AwardID>1743312</AwardID>
    <Investigator>
      <FirstName>Larry</FirstName>
      <LastName>Hinzman</LastName>
      <EmailAddress>lhinzman@alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
      <StartDate>05/10/2017</StartDate>
      <EndDate/>
      <RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
    </Investigator>
    <Institution>
      <Name>University of Alaska Fairbanks Campus</Name>
      <CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
      <ZipCode>997757880</ZipCode>
      <PhoneNumber>9074747301</PhoneNumber>
      <StreetAddress>West Ridge Research Bldg 008</StreetAddress>
      <CountryName>United States</CountryName>
      <StateName>Alaska</StateName>
      <StateCode>AK</StateCode>
    </Institution>
    <ProgramElement>
      <Code>5202</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RES &amp; POLICY SUPPORT PR</Text>
    </ProgramElement>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>1079</Code>
      <Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
    <ProgramReference>
      <Code>7556</Code>
      <Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
    </ProgramReference>
  </Award>
</rootTag>
