<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Graduate Student Travel Support Program for the 2017 V.M. Goldschmidt Conference in Paris, France, August 13-18, 2017</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Earth Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Enriqueta Barrera</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support participation by graduate students in the 2017 V.M. Goldschmidt Conference in Paris, France, during August 13-18, 2017. This travel grant will enable the best and brightest students from the US and US Territories, students who might otherwise be unable to attend due to financial constraints at their home institutions, to benefit from all the advantages this meeting has to offer at this turning point in their respective careers. The Goldschmidt conference is the premier venue for geochemistry and the chosen students will be exposed to the latest advances in the field of geochemistry. The conference offers an excellent opportunity for networking of students who are close to graduation and will be entering the workforce. In addition to oral and poster presentation in 19 theme sessions, students can participate in field trips and workshops associated with the conference. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Applications will be collected from the students, then reviewed and ranked by a volunteer committee of scientists. Twenty-four students, who are presenting their work at the conference, will receive $1,250 each toward travel expenses. Considerations for the award are the preparation of the application package, the demonstrated need for the funds, the selection of a diverse pool of applicants based on gender,representation and geographical distribution. Every effort is made to encourage underrepresented minorities and people with disabilities to apply for funding.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/07/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/07/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1743086</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Munir</FirstName>
<LastName>Humayun</LastName>
<EmailAddress>humayun@magnet.fsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/07/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>The Geochemical Society</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200151305</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024788836</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Carnegie Institution for Science</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7295</Code>
<Text>GEOBIOLOGY &amp; LOW TEMP GEOCHEM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
