<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Resin mini-extruder for additive manufacturing</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cindy WalkerPeach</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project involves providing significantly lower operating costs, broader material variety, and faster speeds than currently available with the fused-deposition modeling (FDM) additive manufacturing process. As additive manufacturing transitions from a prototyping tool to manufacturing solution, the demand for fast, inexpensive, and dynamic 3D printing solutions will continue to grow. The Resin Mini-Extruder is capable of integrating with existing 3D printer electro-mechanical systems and processing raw plastic pellets (resin) directly into a final part, unlike existing FDM technologies that require a filament feedstock. Raw pelletized plastics are typically a tenth to hundredth the cost of comparable filaments, which allow for significantly lower costs per print. In addition, the proposed solution is capable of printing a wide variety of plastics that are very difficult to print with existing extruders, including thermoplastic elastomers and polymer composites. The Resin Mini-Extruder is capable of significantly faster production than existing FDM technologies, which will enable high turnover of design prototypes and production parts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project is based on prior NSF-funded research involving a design framework for biomimetic elasto-fluidic systems. The research inspired the invention of a novel technology for manufacturing elasto-fluidic actuators, which forms the basis of this I-Corps project. The technology, the Resin Mini-Extruder for additive manufacturing, is a screw-driven extrusion system, which includes a novel screw-drive extruder and dynamic control system. The intent is to implement the extruder with existing 3D printer electro-mechanical systems in a FDM additive manufacturing process. The invention of the Resin Mini-Extruder was motivated by the need to print materials that existing FDM technologies are incapable of processing, namely thermoplastic elastomers. A goal of this I-Corps project is to determine whether customers demand broader material variety from FDM and if so, which materials and composites are preferred. The I-Corps process will also be used to determine the extent at which the other technology advantages are valued among customers, including cost per print and print speed, in particular applications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/24/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/24/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1743948</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cjk019@bucknell.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bucknell University</Name>
<CityName>LEWISBURG</CityName>
<ZipCode>178372111</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5705773510</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One Dent Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
