<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Geometric and Asymptotic Group Theory with Applications 2017</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>20040</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Swatee Naik</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This National Science Foundation award provides partial support towards travel and accommodation of U.S. based students and early career researchers attending the Geometric and Asymptotic Group Theory and Applications (GAGTA) conference 2017, being held at the University of the Basque Country in Bilbao, Spain, July 3-7, 2017. The annual conferences in this previously funded series attract the world's leading researchers in geometric and asymptotic group theory. This year, for the first time there is a pre-conference week for students and young researchers that features three mini-courses by experts, several talks by young researchers themselves, and time for informal interaction, with the goal to prepare these early career researchers for full participation in the conference the following week.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The GAGTA conferences cover a variety of areas in geometric and combinatorial group theory, including asymptotic and probabilistic methods, as well as algorithmic and computational topics involving groups. Specific areas of interest include group actions, isoperimetric functions, growth, asymptotic invariants, random walks, algebraic geometry over groups, algorithmic problems and their complexity, generic properties and generic complexity, and applications to non-commutative cryptography. Like its predecessors, GAGTA 2017 will bring people from group theory and computer science together and strengthen the connections each field has with the other. The conference homepage is at https://sites.google.com/site/gagta2017/</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/29/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/29/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744834</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Gilman</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rgilman@stevens.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/29/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stevens Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>HOBOKEN</CityName>
<ZipCode>070305991</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2012168762</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CASTLE POINT ON HUDSON</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1265</Code>
<Text>GEOMETRIC ANALYSIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
