<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Grant for RTSS'17 Ph.D. Student Poster Forum on Real-Time Aspects of Internet of Things and Cyber-Physical Systems</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>15000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>M. Mimi McClure</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>IEEE Real-Time Systems Symposium (RTSS) is the premier conference in the area of real time systems, presenting innovations in the field with respect to theory and practice. RTSS provides a forum for the presentation of high-quality, original research covering all aspects of real-time systems theory, design, analysis, implementation, evaluation, and experiences. RTSS 2017 will continue making RTSS an expansive and inclusive symposium, looking to embrace new and emerging areas of real-time systems research.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal is to organize, in conjunction with the symposium, a Ph.D. student poster forum (i) to discuss the set of interdisciplinary research problems that arise in the context of IoT and CPS, (ii) to determine commonalities and fundamental differences between the IoT and CPS domains, (iii) to identify novel applications that become feasible due to the integration of local vs. hosted computing, local vs. hosted storage, communication, and interaction with the physical world at scale, and (iv) to define an initial system architecture that addresses some of these research problems. The primary goal is to help students (and the real-time community) recognize that IoT and CPS systems are different from each other as well as historically over-engineered real-time embedded systems of the past, and to provide a forum by which students can discuss their proposal for addressing the complicated aggregate systems issues that arise in this context. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Forums of this sort have significant educational value for graduate students.  It encourages the students to begin seriously thinking about their personal future research agenda and opens pathways to burgeoning ideas.  There is a plan to reward best submissions as well as encourage students with financial difficulties to participate, both merit-based and need-based stipends will be provided to offset participation costs.  The project includes broadening participation criteria as part of the recruitment strategy.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744221</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frank</FirstName>
<LastName>Mueller</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mueller@cs.ncsu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>North Carolina State University</Name>
<CityName>RALEIGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>276957514</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9195152444</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>CAMPUS BOX 7514</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>North Carolina</StateName>
<StateCode>NC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7354</Code>
<Text>Computer Systems Research (CSR</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
