<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF INCLUDES DDLP: IM STEM</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>299994</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060400</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bernice T. Anderson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The National Alliance for Partnerships in Equity Education Foundation (NAPE) will partner with a diverse group of organizations from six states (CO, ID, NM, NV, UT, and WY) to form the Intermountain STEM (IM STEM) project, an NSF INCLUDES Design and Development Launch Pilot project focused on the goal of increasing the participation and closing achievement gaps in STEM education, including career and technical education. These organizations whose programs impact the formal STEM education system include: Departments of Education; Higher Education agencies; governor supported STEM Action Centers; universities; secondary school districts; community colleges; Department of Energy National Labs; businesses, non-profits and others. The partners in this effort will identify effective practices focused on the common set of objectives and create a model to bring them to scale by employing a collective impact approach. Through the project, the participating organizations will create a common agenda, identify shared metrics, implement mutually reinforcing activities, and maintain continuous communication. This effort addresses directly the lack of diversity of the STEM workforce; a societal challenge of significant magnitude because of its impact on innovation, national security, environmental safety, and income inequality in the US. The IM STEM?s mission to increase the diversity of students who are successful in STEM education will create a more STEM literate society, ensure the contributions of a diverse STEM workforce, and level the playing field for entrance into high wage STEM careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The capacity of IM STEM to bring large well-resourced organizations to bear on the broadening participation challenges in STEM will advance the knowledge of how creative social innovations, like collective impact, can create transformative institutional and cultural change. The collection, evaluation and scaling of effective research-based solutions to close equity gaps in STEM will advance inclusion in STEM. Initially, the IM STEM project will pilot the scaling of NAPE's professional development (PD) programs - Program Improvement Process for Equity and Micromessaging to Reach and Teach Every Student - that have proven to impact equity gaps in STEM and career and technical education (CTE). The six participating states are interested in scaling their current small scale implementation of NAPE's PD programs and will also incorporate selected emerging practices. This design and development launch pilot will provide the vehicle for identifying support mechanisms for scaling of the PD and the identification of additional scaling opportunities with other effective practices of the participating partners. These efforts have the potential to develop a model for expansion to other states wanting to scale effective practices.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744472</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alexander</FirstName>
<LastName>Carter</LastName>
<EmailAddress>acarter@coloradoedinitiative.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Angela</FirstName>
<LastName>Hemingway</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Angela.Hemingway@STEM.Idaho.gov</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Jakle</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ajakle@unm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Mimi</FirstName>
<LastName>Lufkin</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mimilufkin@napequity.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Susan</FirstName>
<LastName>Thackeray</LastName>
<EmailAddress>Susan.Thackeray@uvu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Alliance for Partnerships in Equity Education Foundatio</Name>
<CityName>Gap</CityName>
<ZipCode>175279579</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7174075118</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>91 Newport Pike</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>NSF INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>029Z</Code>
<Text>Launch Pilots INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
