<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Providing Self-recording Temperature and Attitude Loggers for Hydrothermal Vent Fluid Monitoring at Seafloor and Lacustrine Study Sites</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Ocean Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>James S. Holik</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed work involves purchase of ten (10), new model, high-temperature (high-T), deepsea hydrothermal vent fluid loggers for use in short- and long-term deployments by scientists in the US oceanographic community involved in Ocean Observing Initiative (OOI), International Ocean Discovery Program (IODP), National Deep Submergence Facility (NDSF) and NSF-EAR research programs. These vent fluid loggers have been developed and improved upon over the past 25 years by the PI and WHOI engineers through the WHOI-MISO Facility (http://www.whoi.edu/miso). These instruments have provided the longest time series records of mid-ocean ridge (MOR) hydrothermal vent fluid temperatures, and key information that enhances understanding of hydrothermal fluid flow processes, linkages to magmatism and tectonism at mid-ocean ridge study sites, and shallow ocean crustal permeability. The new model MISO high-T loggers are now manufactured by EP Oceanographic, LLC (EPO), an oceanographic instrumentation company in Pocasset, MA (USA), as part of a collaborative effort to develop small-business innovation and transfer new technologies and ideas needed for oceanographic research to the private sector.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744097</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Daniel</FirstName>
<LastName>Fornari</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dfornari@whoi.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Woods Hole Oceanographic Institution</Name>
<CityName>WOODS HOLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>025431041</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5082893542</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>183 OYSTER POND ROAD</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5415</Code>
<Text>OCEANOGRAPHIC TECHNICAL SERVCE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
