<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF INCLUDES DDLP American STEM Alliance Network Improvement Community</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>299979</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060400</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Cynthia Phillips</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The NSF INCLUDES Design and Development Launch Pilot: American STEM Alliance Network Improvement Community focuses on the broadening participation challenge of providing equitable access to STEM education in high-need, majority Hispanic and Native American communities.  The project will apply both collective impact and network improvement community collaborative change strategies in their effort with three school districts in the Southwest serving majority Hispanic and Native American communities (San Antonio, TX, Farmington, NM, and Andarko, OK).  The proposed model of collaborative change for this project combines the stakeholder engagement focus of collective impact with the strategic, iterative improvement emphasis of the networked improvement community approaches.  The American Institutes of Research (AIR) and the American STEM Alliance (ASA) provide leadership for this effort.  A key feature of this project is that it brings new ways of community engagement, data driven decision making, and institutional collaboration to an existing Alliance with an established reputation with the target population.  The rapid cycle study design proposed by this project will contribute to understanding how communities can develop stronger, more evidence based approaches to addressing the grand challenge of broadening participation across a variety of contexts.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this project is to develop and test a contextually, and culturally relevant approach to addressing inequities in STEM education. The project proposes to promote equitable access to a coherent continuum of support in STEM education pathways.  The Carnegie STEM Excellence Pathway provides the tools and resources for the participating districts to identify a problem of practice and create an intervention to address that problem using a data-driven framework, proven tools/techniques, and continuous feedback.  The project evaluation focuses on documenting the collaborative change strategies, continuous improvement cycles, and their contribution to the changes in institutional policy and practice required to create increased access to rigorous STEM courses for Hispanic and Native American high school students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/08/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744455</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Melissa</FirstName>
<LastName>Dodson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mmdodson@air.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Toney</FirstName>
<LastName>Begay</LastName>
<EmailAddress>tbegay@nmmesa.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Raul</FirstName>
<LastName>Reyna</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rreyna@utsa.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Adam</FirstName>
<LastName>Chavarria</LastName>
<EmailAddress>addamm2020@aol.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Marder</LastName>
<EmailAddress>marder@chaos.ph.utexas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>American Institutes for Research in the Behavioral Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200073835</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2024035000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1000 Thomas Jefferson Street, NW</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>NSF INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>029Z</Code>
<Text>Launch Pilots INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
