<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop on the Dynamic Interaction of Embodied Human and Machine Intelligence; Marconi State Historic Park, Marshall, California; June 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>49995</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert Scheidt</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award will support an interdisciplinary workshop to study how humans and intelligent machines, such as robots, may behave while physically interacting with each other, in contrast to situations where they only exchange information. These questions will become increasingly important as humans begin to come into frequent physical contact with intelligent machines, such as when navigating shared spaces, riding in or walking near autonomous vehicles, or interacting with caregiving or physical therapy robots.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop will gather experts from cognitive neuroscience, behavioral science, dynamics and control, robotics, optimization, and computer science to define key challenges in analyzing the dynamic behavior of systems of embodied human and machine intelligences. Due to rapidly developing capabilities in machine learning, and wide scale deployment of autonomous and intelligent robotic systems, humans in the near future will regularly find themselves physically interacting with intelligent technology. Such intelligent technology might include home assistance robots, physical therapy robots, autonomous vehicles, and smart buildings. The dynamics of physically coupled of humans and intelligent machines have so far received little study, despite the potential for unexpected behavior.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744637</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ramesh</FirstName>
<LastName>Balasubramaniam</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ramesh@ucmerced.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California - Merced</Name>
<CityName>Merced</CityName>
<ZipCode>953435001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2097566405</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5200 North Lake Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>058Y</Code>
<Text>M3X - Mind, Machine, and Motor</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7252</Code>
<Text>PERCEPTION, ACTION &amp; COGNITION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>030E</Code>
<Text>CONTROL SYSTEMS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>034E</Code>
<Text>Dynamical systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>063Z</Code>
<Text>W-HTF Work at the Human-Technology Front</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7252</Code>
<Text>Perception, Action and Cognition</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8024</Code>
<Text>Complex Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
