<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: BRAIDING: Braiding Majorana bound states in atomic chains on a superconducting island</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>300000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Tomasz Durakiewicz</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Non-technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;Majorana bound states are localized at the edge of a one-dimensional topological superconductor. These excitations are viewed as a starting point for topological quantum information processing. This award supports experimental research activity aiming to address the key challenges related to establishing control of Majorana bound states. This particular implementation avoids technical challenges related to physically moving Majorana bound states and, due to the small size of the superconducting island, has intrinsic protection against errors. If successful, this research activity has a potential to make transformative breakthrough in the field of quantum science and technology. The research aspect of this project is accompanied by a multifaceted educational program for graduate and undergraduate students as well as outreach program targeting high-school students and science teachers from the Pasadena School District. The research advances of the project will be broadly disseminated through research articles, seminars, courses and public lectures. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Technical Abstract:&lt;br/&gt;This award supports experimental efforts aiming towards a demonstration of a topological quantum bit based on Majorana bound states realized in magnetic atomic chains placed on a superconducting island which is integrated into a mesoscopic interferometer circuit. In this scheme, reading out the quantum information encoded in Majorana states and performing quantum logical operations can be done by measuring electron parity using interferometry. This particular implementation combines the advantages of theoretical proposals which avoid technical challenges related to physically moving Majorana bound states with intrinsic protection against the quasi-particle poisoning which is considered to be major limiting factor for the coherence times of topological quantum systems. In order to realize this experimental platform several approaches for integration of atomic assemblies accessible using scanning probe microscopy into a nano-fabricated mesoscopic interferometer device will be explored. If successful, this highly focused research activity has a potential to make transformative breakthrough in the fields of quantum science and technology. The research aspect of this project is accompanied by a multifaceted educational program for graduate and undergraduate students as well as outreach program targeting high-school students and science teachers from the Pasadena School District. The research advances of the project will be broadly disseminated through research articles, seminars, courses and public lectures.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/28/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/28/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744011</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Stevan</FirstName>
<LastName>Nadj-Perge</LastName>
<EmailAddress>s.nadj-perge@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/28/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1710</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER PHYSICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1712</Code>
<Text>DMR SHORT TERM SUPPORT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1765</Code>
<Text>CONDENSED MATTER &amp; MAT THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1775</Code>
<Text>ELECTRONIC/PHOTONIC MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>053Z</Code>
<Text>Quantum Leap Materials</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
