<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Transformation groups 2017</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>12500</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthew  Douglass</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The conference Transformation Groups 2017 will be a meeting of mathematicians specializing in various aspects of transformation group theory. The conference will be held on December 14-19, 2017, at the Independent University of Moscow. The speakers will be leading experts in various aspects of transformation groups who are making major contributions to this and related fields. The conference will be a major event, attracting a large segment of the mathematical community working in various aspects  of transformation group theory. The broad spectrum and great current interest in the topics to be discussed at  the conference will make it especially useful for early-career mathematicians.   &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Transformation group theory plays an important role in various areas of mathematics, from algebraic geometry to  representation theory to analysis. The aim of the conference is to present current progress on the following related topics: algebraic groups and geometric invariant theory including the theory of spherical varieties;  transformation groups in differential geometry, analysis and topology; structure and representation theory of Lie algebras and their generalizations, such as affine and vertex algebras or W-algebras; and discrete subgroups of Lie groups and discrete transformation groups. More details about the conference are available at https://www.mccme.ru/tg2017/.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/24/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/24/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744157</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ivan</FirstName>
<LastName>Loseu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>i.loseu@neu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/24/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Northeastern University</Name>
<CityName>BOSTON</CityName>
<ZipCode>021155005</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6173733004</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>360 HUNTINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Massachusetts</StateName>
<StateCode>MA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1264</Code>
<Text>ALGEBRA,NUMBER THEORY,AND COM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
