<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Interfacial Fenton Chemistry on Aqueous Organic Aerosols</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>643604</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia A. Edgerton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This research is focused on the study of how gas-phase species are converted to and processed in tropospheric aerosols. The proposed experiments represent an innovative approach to understanding the nature of the chemical interactions between reactive gases and organic matter in the presence of transition metal ions at air-aqueous interfaces. The results are expected to provide new information on the formation and evolution of tropospheric aerosols, especially those that are known to have adverse health impacts.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This effort includes a systematic study of gas-liquid reactions taking place on the surface of aqueous and aqueous/water soluble organic solutions of selected substrates, exposed to the major gaseous O3, H2O2 and NO2 oxidants in ambient air under experimental conditions relevant to the troposphere. The central aim is to map the dependence of the extent of Fenton chemistry on: (1) pH, (2) the nature of typical organic substrates, either alone or in synthetic mixtures, (3) the presence of ligands representative of those found in secondary organic aerosol, as well as sequestering ligands, and (4) the presence of Cu ions.  The project will provide new data to improve models of interfacial reactions on organic material in the atmosphere.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/21/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/21/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744353</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Michael</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoffmann</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mrh@caltech.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>California Institute of Technology</Name>
<CityName>PASADENA</CityName>
<ZipCode>911250600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6263956219</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1200 E California Blvd</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
