<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Sino-US Forum/Workshop on Environment-Enhancing Food, Energy and Water Systems,  June 13 - 15, 2018, Beijing China</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1744775 (Zhang). This workshop will focus on the paradigm of Environment-Enhancing Food, Energy and Water Systems (EE-FEWS) that addresses critical problems by generating significant amounts of bioenergy and food via bio/chemo/thermo conversion and multicycle reuse of nutrients and wastewater in the biowaste stream. At the same time, EE-FEWS seeks to enhance environmental quality by capturing carbon and cleaning wastewater. The U.S. has an estimated 79 million dry tons of sustainably collectable livestock manure and food processing waste. Through the EE-FEWS approach, this biowaste stream has the potential to be amplified via multi-cycle nutrient and wastewater reuse to 240-800 million tons of mixed algal-bacteria feedstocks that can be converted into 120-400 million tons of biocrude oil via hydrothermal liquefaction (HTL), while cleaning an estimated 7.9 billion tons of wastewater. Additionally, food would be produced without the need for additional reactive fertilizer or water. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This workshop is targeted to contribute significant advancements in sharing and advancing knowledge of the following: utilizing readily available biowaste and biomass inputs; improving efficiency for biowaste/biomass conversion (including thermochemical, biochemical and biological); demonstrating that nutrients in the original biowaste can be efficiently separated in the conversion process and reused multiple times, thus amplifying biomass to produce unprecedented amounts of biocrude; and establishing that the chemicals of environmental concern in the original biowaste can be substantially removed/converted through conversion and wastewater treatment processes. The workshop will involve a broad range of education and outreach opportunities from K-12 to graduate studies, for under-represented minorities, industry and the general public. The educational goal is to educate a new generation of scientists and engineers equipped with a solid foundation and broad perspectives for addressing issues related to the nexus of Food-Enegy-Water (FEW). By recycling nutrients and extracting hydrocarbons in waste streams, producing high value foods, capturing carbon and cleaning water by growing algae, the goal is to be able to produce needed energy and food, and, at the same time, reuse water and enhance the quality of the environment. The dissemination plan is to utilize a workshop website, email lists, professional contacts, etc. to reach out and enhance the awareness of the (FEW) nexus challenge, to develop relevant technologies, and to contribute to the sustainability of society. The workshop is scheduled to be held June 13-15, 2018 in Beijing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744775</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuanhui</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>yzhang1@illinois.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
