<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Rocket Launch System</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2017</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Steven Konsek</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project will be to enable cost-effective deployment of multiple small satellites, which can provide greater utility than a small number of large satellites. Lack of launch capacity has created a substantial and rapidly growing backlog of unlaunched small satellites. Providing low cost and increased capacity for launch of miniaturized satellites will enable important scientific and communication capabilities that larger satellites are unable to cost-effectively perform. These include low data rate communications, network constellations to gather data from multiple points, in-orbit inspection of larger satellites, and university related research. This will enable more university atmospheric-based research and, since low-orbit satellites pass over a specific geographic area more frequently than large satellites, they can be used for rapid response to disasters or to gather timely information relating to telemedicine, environmental management, and asset tracking. as well as enhanced communication capability in remote regions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project will contribute to addressing the technical and logistical challenges associated with the deployment and altitude control of balloons as platforms for launching small satellites. The architecture is broken into key subsystems. Initially, research and development was focused on the Launch Orientation and Control System (LOC). Subsequently, development focused on building and testing several subsystems that can execute suborbital launch. This includes the continued development of the LOC System, design and integration of a wireless communication system, and a robust flight system capable of testing at low altitudes under tethered control. Two successful tests were conducted, including a tethered flight integration test and third launch test. The team will continue address technical hurdles have yet to be resolved, including safe tethering connection and handling of the rocket, a semi-controllable buoyancy system, quick deflation method, central skeletal structure integration, and remote communication.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/12/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744393</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Lynall</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mlynall@purdue.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Purdue University</Name>
<CityName>West Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>479072114</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7654941055</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Young Hall</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Indiana</StateName>
<StateCode>IN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
