<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: Navigating The New Arctic: Bridging Science, Art, and Community</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>100000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diane McKnight</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Part 1: The activities of the proposed workshop will consider the intersections of the natural, built, and social-cultural environments in the changing Arctic.  The ways in which building design, art, and music can be a bridge between scientific data and understanding will be explored in the context of Arctic landscape change.  The workshop will consist of one-day symposium, followed by a three-day workshop, both taking place at the University of Virginia. A post-workshop activity will take place in Utqeagvik (Barrow, AK) to present and discuss outcomes.  The workshop organizers will engage with the next generation of Alaska Native youth through the intersection of science, engineering, architecture and music.&lt;br/&gt;Part 2: The proposed workshop and associated activities will explore the intersections of the natural, built, and social-cultural environments in the changing Arctic.  In this proposed workshop, the investigators will explore how building design, art, and music can be bridge between scientific data and understanding, both academic and Indigenous, of Arctic landscape change. The investigators hope to develop creative and truly interdisciplinary approaches for understanding landscape change and refining questions about the effects of these changes.  The workshop will consist of one-day symposium, followed by a three-day workshop, both taking place at the University of Virginia. A post-workshop activity will take place in Utqeagvik (Barrow, AK) to present and discuss outcomes.  In addition, the workshop organizers are promoting the idea of engaging the next generation of Alaska Native youth through the intersection of science, engineering, architecture and music, hoping that they will become interested in pursuing these fields for the ultimate benefit of their own communities.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/23/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/23/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744413</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Burtner</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mburtner@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Leena</FirstName>
<LastName>Cho</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lsc7t@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Howard</FirstName>
<LastName>Epstein</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hee2b@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Jull</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mj5kh@virginia.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/23/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Virginia Main Campus</Name>
<CityName>CHARLOTTESVILLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>229044195</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4349244270</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>P.O.  BOX 400195</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5293</Code>
<Text>AON IMPLEMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5293</Code>
<Text>AON IMPLEMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
