<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>The 14th U.S.-Korea Forum on Nanotechnology: Internet of Things Including Nanosensors and Neuromorphic Computing, To Be Held September, 11-12, 2017, in Washington, DC</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>38960</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The proposed project for a Forum seeks financial support for scientists and engineers in the nanotechnology area with an objective to recommend new paradigms in this area and promote collaborative initiatives between the US and Korea, two countries.  The "14th U.S.-Korea Forum on Nanotechnology: Internet of Things (IoT) including Nanosensors and Neuromorphic Computing" will host 8 senior presenters and 8 additional early-career presenters (underrepresented minorities will be strongly encouraged) and an approximately equal number of Korean presenters. It will actively encourage partnerships in nanotechnology for breakthroughs in various topics in IoT including nanosensors as well as novel computing architecture in information technology, in addition to strengthening achievements and assessing the progress on recommendations made during the previous meetings of this type.&lt;br/&gt;The Forum will play a key role in identifying new directions for research on IoT technologies and neuromorphic computing addressing long-term challenges in nanotechnological fundamentals and its application for the mutual benefit of both the US and Korea. The meeting proceedings and findings will be published in a booklet form by the National Nanotechnology Policy Center, Korea and on Carnegie Mellon?s website, which will be available to a broader public.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/19/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744340</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Myung</FirstName>
<LastName>Jhon</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mj3a@andrew.cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Elias</FirstName>
<LastName>Towe</LastName>
<EmailAddress>towe@cmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carnegie-Mellon University</Name>
<CityName>PITTSBURGH</CityName>
<ZipCode>152133815</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4122689527</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>5000 Forbes Avenue</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7681</Code>
<Text>ENG NNI SPECIAL STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8028</Code>
<Text>Sensor Technology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
