<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Convergence NNA: Adaptive Capacity and Resilience in the New Arctic: Identifying Pathways to Equitable, Desirable Outcomes for People and Nature Through Convergence</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>99864</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Diane McKnight</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The investigators will conduct a series of workshops that will employ a complex systems framework to gain insight into system dynamics and overall resilience in the Arctic region. Resilience represents the capacity of a community to buffer and adapt to stress and shocks, and thus navigate and even shape change. The workshops will integrate resilience theory and research methods with Indigenous community observations and practice. This integration is needed to address the societal concerns associated with the rapid pace of environmental change in the 'New Arctic.'   Diverse expertise will be represented, and the workshop participants will include Arctic Indigenous scholars and community members from climate-affected Alaskan communities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This series of workshops will employ a complex systems framework to gain insight into system dynamics and overall resilience, which can be defined as the capacity to buffer and adapt to stress and shocks, and thus navigate and even shape change. The workshop will integrate resilience theory and research methods with Indigenous community observations and practice, which is needed to address the societal concerns in the 'New Arctic.'  Merging expertise from multiple disciplines through a complex system approach is a robust way to conduct convergent research on a Pan-Arctic scale. Further, the iterative structure of the workshops with local community inclusion and the plan to integrate knowledge from six themes will enhance the convergent outcomes of the workshops.  The meaningful inclusion of Indigenous scholars and community members in the workshops makes the project more convergent in that it is not only transdisciplinary science but seeks out issues and information important to Arctic and mid-latitude Tribal communities. This project promotes convergence by addressing the societal concern of achieving resilience for Arctic communities and by integrating diverse fields of science through a complex systems approach and through engagement with Indigenous scholars and community members. The range of expertise represented by the participants includes ecosystem science, social science, climatology and system science.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1744417</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Martha</FirstName>
<LastName>Shulski</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mshulski3@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Craig</FirstName>
<LastName>Allen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>allencr@unl.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hannah</FirstName>
<LastName>Birge</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hannah.birge@huskers.unl.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Nebraska-Lincoln</Name>
<CityName>Lincoln</CityName>
<ZipCode>685031435</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4024723171</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>151 Prem S. Paul Research Center</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Nebraska</StateName>
<StateCode>NE</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1352</Code>
<Text>GEOGRAPHY AND SPATIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, TECH &amp; SOCIETY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7699</Code>
<Text>ICER</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8078</Code>
<Text>INSPIRE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>060Z</Code>
<Text>Convergent Research</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
