<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>2017 North Pacific Arctic Conference: Building Capacity for a Sustainable Arctic in a Changing Global Order</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>6458</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anna Kerttula de Echave</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award support travel for four early career scientists to the North Pacific Arctic Conference (NPAC) as panelists and participants in the 2017 conference titled "Conference on Building the Capacity for A Sustainable Arctic in a Changing Global Order."  The short-term objectives of the proposed project is 1) to tie promising next generation scientists from the Arctic region into existing knowledge and leadership networks; 2) to provide them with the additional knowledge, experience, inspiration, and opportunity they need to become future leaders of the region; and 3) to ensure the early career scientists represent the diversity of the region by including women and Indigenous participants. In the longer-term, the project aims to develop these early career scientists so that they will be able to step into future regional leadership roles. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The East-West Center will fulfill its objectives by bringing four high-caliber, pre-selected early career scientists to the two-day NPAC conference, August 9-11, 2017. They will be included as full participants in the conference proceedings, first as panelists; second as contributors to the published NPAC 2017 conference proceedings; and third as participants in high-level virtual networks associated with the NPAC community.  Upon the conclusion of the conference, they will continue on as participants in these virtual networks and also be given the opportunity to contribute their written works the East- West Center's Asia Pacific Bulletin and Asia Pacific Issue publications.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/10/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/10/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1745893</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nancy Davis</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewis</LastName>
<EmailAddress>LewisN@eastwestcenter.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/10/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Center For Cultural&amp;Tech Interchg East&amp;West</Name>
<CityName>Honolulu</CityName>
<ZipCode>968481601</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089447504</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1601 East-West Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5221</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC SOCIAL SCIENCES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
