<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Turbulent Mixing and Beyond - Non-Equilibrium Transport Across the Scales, Trieste, Italy, August 14-18, 2017</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ronald Joslin</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Funding is provided to support the Turbulent Mixing and Beyond symposium which will be held at The Abdus Salam International Centre for Theoretical Physics in Trieste, Italy on the 14th through 18th of August, 2017. The funds will be used to cover expenses associated with travel for 15 U.S. graduate students. The international meeting is soliciting invitees that are world renowned experts in the study of physics and control of turbulent shear flows. The 5 day symposium will include approximately 60 keynote presentations and 180 participants from a range of individuals including students, young scientists and established researchers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The broader impact will be to increase the dissemination of studies associated with the Turbulence mixing physics among students, young scientists and established researchers. Although NSF funds will not be used for international participants the international nature of those attending the symposium will further broaden the exposure and impact of the research presented at this meeting. In addition, the papers from the symposium will be posted online, the symposium will be video recorded, and papers from the symposium will be submitted for journal publication.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1745694</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Katepalli</FirstName>
<LastName>Sreenivasan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>katepalli.sreenivasan@nyu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>New York University</Name>
<CityName>NEW YORK</CityName>
<ZipCode>100121019</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2129982121</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>70 WASHINGTON SQUARE S</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1415</Code>
<Text>PARTICULATE &amp;MULTIPHASE PROCES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1443</Code>
<Text>FLUID DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
