<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>14th International Conference on Mid-IR Optoelectronics: Materials and Devices; October 7 - 10, 2018, Flagstaff, Arizona, USA</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dominique M. Dagenais</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The 14th International Conference on Mid-IR Optoelectronics: Materials and Devices provides a prominent international forum for reporting new developments in the area of fundamental and applied optoelectronic materials and devices.  This activity benefits society by advancing the knowledge base of the infrared materials and devices needed for present and future engineering grand challenges, including emitters and detectors necessary for homeland security, pollution detection, information and communication technology, and sustainable energy conversion.  The proposed activity advances discovery and understanding while promoting teaching, training, and learning by bringing together researchers and students with broad areas of expertise to understand and discover the fundamentals of infrared materials and the novel devices enabled by these materials.  Moreover, the proposed activity enhances science and technology through broader dissemination and understanding via face-to-face interaction at the conference.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The conference activity advances knowledge by bringing together experts, junior researchers, and students from all over the world to interact and exchange ideas in the area of mid-infrared optoelectronic materials and devices.  The conference provides a distinguished international forum for reporting new developments in the areas of infrared emitters and detectors; interband and intersubband materials and devices; infrared optoelectronic devices, components, and systems; fundamental and applied infrared optoelectronic materials development, growth, and characterization; novel architectures based on new materials and low-dimensional structures; and non-linear infrared optoelectronics.  The technical program will integrate oral sessions, poster presentations, and social activities, providing numerous opportunities for discussion and interaction between high-ranking researchers, junior researchers, and students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1745167</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yong-Hang</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>yhzhang@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shane</FirstName>
<LastName>Johnson</LastName>
<EmailAddress>shane.johnson@asu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arizona State University</Name>
<CityName>TEMPE</CityName>
<ZipCode>852816011</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4809655479</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>ORSPA</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Arizona</StateName>
<StateCode>AZ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>091E</Code>
<Text>Light generation &amp; detection</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
