<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student Travel Support for the 50th IEEE/ACM Symposium on Microarchitecture</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>20000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division of Computing and Communication Foundations</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Yuanyuan Yang</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The project will enable students to defray the costs of traveling to and attending the 50th Annual IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO-50), to be held October 14-18, 2017, in Boston, Massachusetts, USA. MICRO is the premier forum for presenting, discussing, and debating innovative microarchitecture ideas and techniques for advanced computing and communication systems. This symposium brings together researchers in fields related to microarchitecture, compilers, chips, and systems for technical exchange on traditional microarchitecture topics and emerging research areas.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will have two primary broader impacts. First, the MICRO conference will be strengthened as a result of the greater attendance that this travel support will enable. Second, those students receiving travel support will personally benefit from the opportunity to interact with peers and experts, as well as establish connections that will help their professional careers. More broadly, we expect additional indirect impacts. First, the available support will be widely advertised in order to attract women and under-represented minority groups (through postings on computer architecture web-sites and mailing lists). Second, by focusing on students, the project will help foster the mentoring of subsequent generations of computer architects.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1745359</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>David</FirstName>
<LastName>Wentzlaff</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wentzlaf@princeton.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Princeton University</Name>
<CityName>Princeton</CityName>
<ZipCode>085442020</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6092583090</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Off. of Research &amp; Proj. Admin.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7798</Code>
<Text>SOFTWARE &amp; HARDWARE FOUNDATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7941</Code>
<Text>COMPUTER ARCHITECTURE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
