<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Post-Quantum Cryptography in Resource-Constrained Devices</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Peter Atherton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project is to deliver state of the art cryptography and cybersecurity solutions to Internet of Things (IoTs) and embedded device designers, enterprise hardware and software vendors, and government contractors against the attack of classical and quantum computers. It has been widely accepted that quantum computer attacks on today's security are expected to become a reality within the next decade. Some progress towards constructing quantum computers has been made, although no quantum computers with serious computing power have yet been built. Nevertheless, we believe it is prudent to plan ahead for future needs as it normally takes many years to change cryptosystem deployments due to network effects. This project plans to implement quantum-safe solutions which will require the integration of quantum-safe software and/or hardware cryptographic solutions on resource-constrained devices used in embedded systems.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project will design, develop, and implement cryptographic algorithms that are suitable for small and resource-constrained devices employing hard and complex mathematical assumptions known to be classical- and quantum-safe. All post-quantum cryptography candidates need to be evaluated in terms of performance while the target applications are resource-constrained devices. Long-term and lightweight security are two main parameters that need to be considered while deploying quantum-safe cryptographic algorithms in these devices. We plan to employ a special class of quantum-safe algorithms based on maps on elliptic curves to achieve the required performance and security. Cryptosystems based on these maps on the elliptic curves are known to provide the smallest possible key sizes and their security level is determined by a simple choice of a single parameter in comparison to the other quantum-safe candidates. The hardware designs are taken through VLSI design flow to realize the integrated circuits that are evaluated for energy/power, area/performance, and security. The project will generate new insights and results about how to be safe and secure in the quantum era. This project will also contribute to the ongoing standardization effort by the US government and other international organizations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1745882</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Brandon</FirstName>
<LastName>Langenberg</LastName>
<EmailAddress>brandon.langenberg@pqsecurity.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>PQSecure Technologies, LLC</Name>
<CityName>Boca Raton</CityName>
<ZipCode>000033431</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2018445743</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>901 NW 35th Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
