<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STTR Phase I:  Accelerating the dissemination of healthcare interventions that improve care for high-need/high-cost patients</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nancy Kamei</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Technology Transfer (STTR) Phase 1 project includes: accelerating the pace of healthcare improvement by making information on high-need/high-cost patients instantly accessible and individually tailored to health care providers; transforming health intervention databases into active and dynamic learning communities about caring for high-need/high-cost patients; reducing the burden on safety net providers to sort and sift through dozens of information sources about delivering care to high-need/high-cost patients. Health Information Networking Tool (HINT) will be a unique combination of customized algorithms that will fill in critical gaps in knowledge, especially around health disparities, the social determinants of health and underserved conditions; boost opportunities for safety net providers to connect with peers to engage in collaborative problem-solving; reduce duplication and repetition of errors and failed interventions across safety net healthcare organizations; increase public recognition for safety net institutions that develop promising interventions; and enable technical advancements in machine learning to suggest models of care for high-need/high-cost patients. The commercial impact for HINT includes: reducing the cost and improving the quality of care delivered to high-need/high cost populations; and creating opportunities for safety net institutions and providers to market their expertise on caring for complex, underserved patients.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed project was conceived on the belief that ingenious solutions in caring for society's most vulnerable populations occur daily across the safety net health system; that HINT will accelerate innovation by bringing an unprecedented resource to disseminate voluminous and constantly changing healthcare information; that the proposed information network will reduce the fragmentation of information and duplication in errors and failed interventions that currently occur; and finally that unlocking and disseminating innovations and advice from peers - in similar institutions and caring for similar patients - will accelerate successful practices to improve the health of high-need/high-cost patients. HINT proposes to develop unique crawling, clustering, text mining, collaborative filtering, bipartite matching, and ranking algorithms. The team will integrate the six algorithms into a customized social content management system, and address challenges around design and functionality.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/23/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/23/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1746142</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fei</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lifei@cs.gmu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Bianca</FirstName>
<LastName>Finkelstein</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bianca.finkelstein@healthnetworkresearch.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/23/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Health Network Research Group</Name>
<CityName>Herndon</CityName>
<ZipCode>201704425</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5618628064</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11597 Cedar Chase Ro</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Virginia</StateName>
<StateCode>VA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1505</Code>
<Text>STTR PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>Health Care Enterprise Systems</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8032</Code>
<Text>Software Services and Applications</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8042</Code>
<Text>Health and Safety</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
