<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Improving Indoor Air Quality using a Biosilica Based Functional Paint &amp; Coatings Photocatalyst</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Debasis Majumdar</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Small Business Innovation Research Phase I project will develop a material which when added to commercial paint and coatings can improve indoor air quality by actively removing and degrading Volatile Organic Compounds (VOCs). Indoor air quality is generally five times worse than outdoor air quality and VOCs are prevalent in indoor environments, being emitted from typical household items like electronics, cleaners, and flooring. People spend 90% of their lives in indoor environments, making poor indoor air quality a more acute health risk. VOCs are known to cause and worsen allergic diseases such as asthma and eczema, which combined, costs the United States approximately $56 billion in medical spending and lost work productivity every year. Alleviating the discomfort and financial burdens posed by allergic diseases can improve the standard of living of over 60 million affected Americans in the United States. Low- and zero-VOC paints ($9 billion market) are the fastest growing segment of architectural paints ($62 billion market). This technology has the potential to dramatically improve indoor air quality and make everyday living better for children, the elderly, and adults suffering from allergic diseases.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project will further the understanding of using diatoms in conjunction with a photocatalyst to harvest light as an energy source for the removal of pollutants from environments. Diatoms have been shown to increase the collection of ultraviolet, blue and red wavelengths of light. As a substrate for photocatalysts which utilize these wavelengths, diatoms may provide a superior light collection capability, increasing the effectiveness of photocatalysts. The proposed aim is to show an increase in the photocatalytic rate of VOC degradation which could help to make metal oxide photocatalysis a more viable option for air treatment. The proposed research makes the following contributions: 1) advancement of efficient visible light photocatalysis with a diatom-based additive; 2) understanding integration of photocatalytic paint additives into base paint and coatings mixtures, optimized for minimal paint substrate degradation and maximal photocatalytic degradation of indoor air-pollutants; and 3) long-term improvement of indoor air quality. Overall it is expected that this Phase I will show diatoms, as substrates, can increase the rate of photocatalysts up to two times under typical irradiation sources. This project targets cleaner indoor environments through pollutant removal activity without increased energy usage.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/18/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1746759</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nicholas</FirstName>
<LastName>Day</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nick@diatomixcorp.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Diatomix, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>Beaverton</CityName>
<ZipCode>970086414</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5033193096</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>8195 SW Nimbus Ave</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>123E</Code>
<Text>CENTERS: ADVANCED MATERIALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
