<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaborative Research: Increasing Understanding of 30-60 Sec Resolution Satellite Observations with Respect to Convective Initiation and Improving Microphysical Parameterizations</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>149414</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020105</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nicholas F. Anderson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The United States launched a new observational satellite in 2016 called the Geostationary Operational Environmental Satellite, commonly referred to as GEOS-16.  This satellite contains a package of instruments that greatly improves the remote sensing of clouds and lightning.  In this award, researchers will make use of the rapid scan features of GOES-16 to study physical processes occurring in cumulus clouds.  The research has the potential to improve short time-frame convective forecasts, which are of economic and public safety interest.  The project will also train the next generation of scientists, ensuring an educated and prepared workforce.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The research team will use new super rapid scan (SRS) observations from the GOES-16 Advanced Baseline Imager (ABI) to examine physical processes occurring in growing and mature convective clouds.  SRS observations will be combined with radar, lightning, and model data to address the two main questions of the research project:  1) How do we maximize the value of high-time frequency SRS cloud-sensitive IR observations for understanding physical processes occurring in cumulus clouds? and 2) How do we extend the use of SRS datasets in combination with radar and NWP data to obtain longer predictive lead times for convective storms?  The specific basic science research goals are to gain understanding about in-cloud processes, especially updraft magnitude, evolution and size, factors influencing parcel buoyancy, and hydrometeor fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/05/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/28/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1746119</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xuanli</FirstName>
<LastName>Li</LastName>
<EmailAddress>xuanli@nsstc.uah.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/05/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Mecikalski</LastName>
<EmailAddress>johnm@nsstc.uah.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/05/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Alabama in Huntsville</Name>
<CityName>Huntsville</CityName>
<ZipCode>358051911</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2568246120</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>301 Sparkman Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alabama</StateName>
<StateCode>AL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL &amp; DYNAMIC METEOROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
