<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Improvement Award: The Role of Material Culture in The Establishment of Centralized Authority</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>25099</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>John E. Yellen</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Through this Doctoral Dissertation Improvement award Ms. Lingyi Zeng under the direction of Dr. Anne Underhill of Yale University will collect data for her PhD thesis. Thus the project, in addition to the knowledge it will produce, will further the intellectual development and career path of a promising and highly competent young scientist. The central question which this research addresses is: how do large, geographically extensive social entities, which include multiple ethnic groups speaking many languages, become integrated into effectively functioning units for extended periods of time? Ms. Zeng choses as her example the Mongul empire which was established in the beginning of the 13th century and at its height extended from Eastern Europe to the Pacific coast of China. She focuses on the production of centrally produced symbols of power which, she believes were carefully distributed to reinforce the authority of delegated officials and confer status on them. The archaeological approach adopted permits development and modification of this system to be studied over a time period measured in centuries and provide insight not attainable though a brief snapshot of time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Ms. Zeng will examine the production, consumption, and distribution of two kinds of porcelains in the Mongol Empire (13th-14th centuries). She hypothesizes that at the beginning of the Mongol Empire, the rulers deliberately created these two types of porcelains as new kinds of prestige goods, and they controlled the production and distribution of their new products. Later in time, these two types of porcelains became more common and available to intermediate elites of the empire who were pursuing higher social status. She will employ a variety of approaches including not only fieldwork in the well-known porcelain production center in Jingdezhen, China, but also SEM-EDS analysis of excavated ceramics and collections from other areas of the Mongol Empire, including Inner Mongolia and Mongolia. She will investigate different strategies of production and distribution used by both the central government and local agents, and how they changed over time. The organization of production and the reasons for technological choices will also be considered.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/04/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/04/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1746779</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Lingyi</FirstName>
<LastName>Zeng</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lingyi.zeng@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anne</FirstName>
<LastName>Underhill</LastName>
<EmailAddress>anne.underhill@yale.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/04/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Yale University</Name>
<CityName>New Haven</CityName>
<ZipCode>065208327</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2037854689</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Projects</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Connecticut</StateName>
<StateCode>CT</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7606</Code>
<Text>DDRI Archaeology</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1391</Code>
<Text>ARCHAEOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
