<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: Designed Quantum Materials Workshop; To be Held at The National Institute of Standards and Technology, in Gaithersburg, MD January 23-24, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>16032</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Dimitris Pavlidis</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Designed Quantum Materials Workshop will play a key role in identifying new directions for research on next generation electronic devices. It will promote interactions between leading researchers, will explore new device concepts and technologies and will focus on the technical challenges and barriers of transitioning such research results into nanomanufacturing. The highlights of the symposium will be accessible through a report on the workshop and its findings that will be published in a readily accessible public medium.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This grant provides funds to support graduate student and invited researcher participation, as well as conference organization expenses in a workshop to be held January 23-24, 2018, at the National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) in Gaithersburg, Maryland. The Designed Quantum Materials Workshop will address the questions of precise placement of dopants in semiconductors for better spin-orbit coupling, as well as the study of two-dimensional (2D) properties and related nanomanufacturing aspects. Approaches to be considered include (1) improved accuracy of dopant placement for Hubbard model experiments; (2) study of designed 2D materials and verification of various solid state physics models; (3) development of concepts that generate technologically relevant nanomanufacturing approaches.  New types of fundamental physics studies and the possible development of new regimes of metamaterials will be discussed and explored along these lines. These will also be considered in terms of innovative technologies for the nanomanufacturing of new devices and materials.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/12/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/25/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1747578</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>John</FirstName>
<LastName>Randall</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jrandall@zyvexlabs.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joshua</FirstName>
<LastName>Ballard</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jballard@zyvexlabs.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wiley</FirstName>
<LastName>Kirk</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kirk@uta.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Texas at Arlington</Name>
<CityName>Arlington</CityName>
<ZipCode>760190145</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8172722105</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1 UNIVERSITY OF TEXAS AT</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1517</Code>
<Text>ELECT, PHOTONICS, &amp; MAG DEVICE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1788</Code>
<Text>NANOMANUFACTURING</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>100E</Code>
<Text>Novel devices &amp; vacuum electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>103E</Code>
<Text>Energy efficient electronics</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
