<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Low-Cost 2D and 3D Millimeter Wave Image Sensors</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>224957</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project includes a new, low-cost approach to 3D millimeter wave image sensors enabling non-destructive evaluation in construction, as well as other fields such as robotics, security, and quality control. Millimeter wave imaging uses human-safe, radio frequency signals to make high resolution images of objects that cannot be seen with conventional optical sensors. Because of their long wavelength, millimeter waves pass through many materials that are opaque to visible light, including common construction materials such as drywall, brick, tile, cement, and wood. For example, in the construction market, dramatic cost savings and faster, safer, and more accurate construction work could be achieved using millimeter wave imaging for structural evaluation as well as observing hidden utilities such as wiring and plumbing that should be avoided while drilling, and detecting hazards such as water leaks behind wall surfaces. This project will also provide entrepreneurial opportunity to a new generation of scholars/innovators as the technology matures toward commercial practice.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase I project aims to advance the state of the art in millimeter wave imaging and enable low-cost, standalone 3D millimeter wave imagers. Prior work in a laboratory environment has demonstrated the promise of millimeter wave imaging for applications such as structural analysis in construction, however commercialization requires an image sensor that is fast, portable, low power, and low cost. This project will enable low cost hardware/software platforms for millimeter wave imaging using commercial chipsets with novel general purpose graphics processing unit (GPGPU)-accelerated image reconstruction algorithms.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/21/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/21/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1747275</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>CLAIRE</FirstName>
<LastName>WATTS</LastName>
<EmailAddress>claire.marie.watts@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/21/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Thruwave LLC</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6179539597</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3000 Mason Rd</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
