<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>EAGER: High-Efficiency and Cost-Effective Electrocatalysts for the Direct Conversion of Methane to Methanol at Ambient Conditions</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>150000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robert McCabe</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Shale gas deposits contain enormous quantities of natural gas.  Transporting low density natural gas from remote shale deposit locations to its point of use is often uneconomical, so this "stranded gas" may be flared or burned for energy recovery on site, circumventing the need for transport.  Increasing the accessibility of this domestic energy supply would decrease fuel prices, increase energy security, and reduce the environmental footprint of this resource.  One strategy is to extract the larger fuel molecules from natural gas, and compress them into an easily transportable dense liquid.  The majority of natural gas is methane, though, which requires high energy to compress into liquid form. Thus, a promising alternative strategy is the chemical conversion of gaseous methane into liquid methanol. However, this chemical conversion is extremely difficult using known methods, and the remote location of the shale deposits relative to chemical manufacturing facilities increases the challenge.  This research project seeks to develop novel electrochemical catalysts that will more efficiently, effectively, and economically convert stranded gaseous methane into liquid methanol.  Such methods are compatible with small-scale, modular, manufacturing units that are deployable to remote locations. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research project rationalizes the use of surface orientation and adatom decoration of electrocatalysts to promote electrocatalytic oxidation of methane to methanol. The use of high-index facets of metallic catalysts and the role of mobile oxygen interstitials on oxide supports is being explored. The potential for higher-index planes to lower the activation barrier for methane adsorption and partial oxidation is being examined using Ni (310) and Ni (760). In-situ Fourier-transform infrared spectroscopy coupled with impedance spectroscopy is being used to probe the role of surface facets, nonstoichiometry, and adsorption sites in the activated chemisorption and transformation of methane to adsorbed hydrogen and adsorbed methyl. Given the recalcitrance of methane as a chemical reactant, successful demonstration of this process would increase the economic feasibility of using stranded methane and reduce the environmental impact of a vast domestic energy supply.  The research project also involves training both graduate and undergraduate students.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/31/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/31/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1747603</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Xiao-Dong</FirstName>
<LastName>Zhou</LastName>
<EmailAddress>zhou@louisiana.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/31/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Louisiana at Lafayette</Name>
<CityName>Lafayette</CityName>
<ZipCode>705032701</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3374826203</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>104 University Circle</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1401</Code>
<Text>Catalysis</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7916</Code>
<Text>EAGER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
