<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Computing and Intersectionality (The Social and Behavioral Structures at Play for Black Women in the Computing Sciences):  An Inclusive Agenda for Computing</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>464640</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Computer and Network Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Fay Payton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Computing and Intersectionality builds on the growing focus on gender equity in computing in the United States. The disproportionate underrepresentation of women in computing fields is an ongoing national challenge. Within that larger dialogue on inclusion, there exists a growing body of work and focus on the intersectional factors that affect women of color within the larger population of women.  The underrepresentation of women of color is more acute than the underrepresentation of women generally and the factors that contribute to that warrant exploration.  Computing and Intersectionality is timely work and addresses this phenomenon directly.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of the work is to establish a standing national conference that directly addresses issues associated with women of color within the computing sciences. It is a standing meeting to explore the particular dynamics of their experiences and to assess and determine effective institutional strategies to overcome the current challenges.  Concurrent with the establishment of a standing meeting, Computing and Intersectionality develops a journal of scholarly research for both social scientists and computer scientists, to focus on the intersectional factors that affect women of color. Results from this project will inform the broadening participation and STEM+C communities on specific factors of recruiting, retention, and graduation associated with women of color in computing. It is an important complement to the larger effort on gender equity, which cannot be entirely successful if women of color are not equally successful.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/17/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/17/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1747756</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jamika</FirstName>
<LastName>Burge</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jamika.burge@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/17/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>GPRA Strategic Management, Inc.</Name>
<CityName>White Plains</CityName>
<ZipCode>206954428</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2405188667</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3929 Shaftsbury Court</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1714</Code>
<Text>SPECIAL PROJECTS - CISE</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7482</Code>
<Text>BROADENING PARTIC IN COMPUTING</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
