<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase I:  Production of natural sun-protective compounds</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>225000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Ruth M. Shuman</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) project is the development of sustainably produced, effective natural sunscreen compound found in marine organisms for skincare applications.  The World Health Organization estimates that one in every three cancers diagnosed is a skin cancer.  The prevalence of skin cancer, and the threat of photoaging, is driving growth in the global market for sun protection products, which is predicted to reach over $7 B by 2020.  However, many chemical sunscreen ingredients on the market today have been shown to be harmful to the environment and/or to have adverse health effects.  The goal is to produce a previously identified marine sunscreen compound, gadusol, in an economical and sustainable yeast biomanufacturing system, and replace problematic sunscreen ingredients in current use. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This SBIR Phase I project proposes to develop a sustainable means of producing a natural, marine-based sunscreen ingredient for skincare applications. This project focuses on increasing yields and recovery of gadusol, a fish-derived UV-B-absorbing sunscreen, by using the tools of microbial fermentation and synthetic biology. The gadusol biosynthetic pathway was recently introduced into yeast.  The key technical objectives of his project are to improve gadusol yields, evaluate yeast-produced gadusol use in skin care products, and develop methods for purification that will be applicable to large-scale production.  The anticipated outcome of this project is a new and underutilized sunscreen compound derived from natural sources that has the potential to provide UV protection without the health and environmental risks associated with current commercial ingredients.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/19/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/15/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1747347</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>Bradford</LastName>
<EmailAddress>c.samuel.bradford.ii@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/19/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/15/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Khaled</FirstName>
<LastName>Almabruk</LastName>
<EmailAddress>khaled@gadusollabs.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/15/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Seaceuticals Inc</Name>
<CityName>Corvallis</CityName>
<ZipCode>973334335</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5416025119</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>750 SW C Avenue Apt 4</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Oregon</StateName>
<StateCode>OR</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5371</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE I</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8038</Code>
<Text>Biotechnology</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
