<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Breakthroughs 2030:  A workshop to be held October 2-5, 2017 at the Beckman Center, Irvine CA</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>99000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Integrative Organismal Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anne Sylvester</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Breakthroughs 2030 workshop will be held October 2-5, 2017 at the Beckman Center at the University of California in Irvine, California. The workshop brings together a cross-disciplinary group of scientists to discuss the future of food and agriculture science.  The workshop is part of a year-long study organized by the National Academies of Sciences, Engineering and Medicine (NAS) to identify critical gaps and discover breakthrough research areas to advance food and agriculture in the U.S. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop is designed to stimulate creative thinking, catalyze new research directions, build partnerships and attract research input from disciplines not typically associated with food and agriculture.  The workshop will consider seven science focal areas selected after a significant public input period during the summer of 2017. During the input period, a public website will gather ideas, which will be synthesized as the seven focus areas through Town Hall meetings in August 2017, and will culminate in the Breakthroughs 2030 workshop. The facilitated and public workshop will include diverse participation from across disciplines and demographics. Workshop attendees will discuss the bottlenecks and future approaches needed to accelerate progress in each of the seven focus areas related to food and agriculture. Outcomes will be a final report to be published by the NAS in 2018 as a guiding blueprint to advance food and agriculture into the next decades.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/06/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1747820</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roberta</FirstName>
<LastName>Schoen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rschoen@nas.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>National Academy of Sciences</Name>
<CityName>Washington</CityName>
<ZipCode>200012721</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2023342254</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 FIFTH STREET NW</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>District of Columbia</StateName>
<StateCode>DC</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1329</Code>
<Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH PROJECT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7577</Code>
<Text>PLANT GENOME RESEARCH RESOURCE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9109</Code>
<Text>AGRICULTURAL BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>BIOT</Code>
<Text>BIOTECHNOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
