<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Travel Support for Early Career Scientists for the Chapman Conference on Non- Volcanic Stratospheric Aerosol; Tenerife, Canary Islands, Spain; March 18-23, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>29977</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia A. Edgerton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project supports student travel to the American Geophysical Union's Chapman Conference entitled, 'Stratospheric aerosol during the past 20 years: Processes sustaining the aerosol, interactions with climate and chemistry, and importance for historical analogues.'  This conference provides a venue for the world's leading observational and modeling experts in stratospheric aerosol and precursor gases to present and discuss results focused on major science questions related to the character and processes controlling stratospheric aerosol during the quiescent to mildly volcanic period of 1996 to the present. The broader impacts of the conference will derive from the exchange of ideas that will help focus the research community on the processes controlling stratospheric aerosol, and provide an opportunity for young scientists to meet, network, and exchange ideas with leaders in the field. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual challenges addressed by the meeting participants include: (1) Comparing and resolving measurements of stratospheric aerosol and gas phase sulfur from different platforms; (2) Deriving aerosol surface area, cross section, and asymmetry parameter from remote satellite measurements of optical properties; (3) Establishing the accuracy of the geophysical quantities derived from remote optical measurements; and (4) Extrapolating measurements of aerosol and gas phase climatologies to regions and time periods not measured. Topics at this meeting will contribute significantly to establish confidence in the aerosol climatologies used and in providing a basis against which models with intrinsic aerosol can be tested.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/11/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/11/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1747683</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Terry</FirstName>
<LastName>Deshler</LastName>
<EmailAddress>deshler@uwyo.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/11/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5113</Code>
<Text>ANTARCTIC OCEAN &amp; ATMOSPH SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5740</Code>
<Text>CLIMATE &amp; LARGE-SCALE DYNAMICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4444</Code>
<Text>INTERDISCIPLINARY PROPOSALS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
