<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>US-Japan Workshop on Advances in Organic/Inorganic Hybrid Materials</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>8000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Andrew J. Lovinger</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>TECHNICAL AND NON-TECHNICAL SUMMARY:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award provides partial support for the 2018 US-Japan Workshop on Advances in Organic/Inorganic Hybrid  Materials. The workshop is co-organized by researchers from both the US and Japan and will take place on the Newark Campus of Rutgers, The State University of New Jersey from June 17 to 21, 2018. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The  technical portion of the workshop will highlight major current advances and also point to important  future directions in the fast-growing field of hybrid materials. The workshop will assemble ca. 25-30 individuals each from Japan and the US who are on the forefront  of the synthesis and characterization of hybrid materials and their implementation in new application fields. The presentations of the U.S. and Japanese speakers will be alternated and the talks organized so  that the topics are similar. The idea is to learn about commonalities that can be expected to foster  cooperative research. Sessions on the following specific topical areas are envisioned: New Synthetic  Approaches to Organic-Inorganic Hybrid Materials; Conjugated Hybrid Materials for Optoelectronic  Applications; Nanomaterials and Nanocomposites;  Materials and Device Applications; Self-Assembly  and Biomedical-Related Applications. Leading experts in the field from Japan and the US will discuss the  latest developments in each of these areas of research.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;One of the major aims of the workshop is to offer opportunities for technical exchange of information and  professional interactions between researchers from Japan and the US. High profile scientists at varying  career stages, ranging from new investigators to highly established senior researchers, will have an  opportunity for detailed discussions on the frontiers of inorganic-organic hybrid materials. Further, the  format of the conference will encourage international cooperation by pairing speakers from the US with  colleagues from Japan in focused sessions on topical areas of mutual interest.  This workshop will also serve as an important platform for allowing young scientists (i.e., untenured  faculty, graduate students and postdoctoral fellows) to broaden their professional network and establish  new international collaborations.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/18/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1747702</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Frieder</FirstName>
<LastName>Jaekle</LastName>
<EmailAddress>fjaekle@andromeda.rutgers.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Rutgers University Newark</Name>
<CityName>Newark</CityName>
<ZipCode>071021896</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9739720283</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Blumenthal Hall, Suite 206</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New Jersey</StateName>
<StateCode>NJ</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1762</Code>
<Text>SOLID STATE &amp; MATERIALS CHEMIS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1773</Code>
<Text>POLYMERS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7504</Code>
<Text>NSF-INTERNAT COOP IN MATERIALS RES-OTHER</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
