<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Biodegradable Airway Stent for Tracheal Stenosis Management</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anita J. LaSalle</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this ICorps project is to prevent complications developing from the use of non-degradable permanent implants and ultimately reduce redo/replacement procedures in the healthcare field. The introduction of a novel family of biodegradable medical implants meets this intention. There is a sizeable market for biodegradable devices to treat various health conditions and address issues from existing therapeutics. The global biodegradable stent market is expected to grow significantly over the next ten years.  Mortality from heart diseases and cancer is projected to increase through the year 2020. However, with appropriate minimally-invasive intervention, the number of deaths can potentially be reduced significantly.  The high cost of follow-up procedures due to insertion of permanent stents urges healthcare industry to seek better alternatives. The ultimate goal is to boost the position of the United States as a leader in the global absorbable device market.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project focuses on a biomaterial, a novel biodegradable magnesium based alloy that can be used to design and develop the biodegradable medical devices. Magnesium is already present in the human body and simply degrades safely from the stents over time. The invention provides a material composition for medical device like stents. The invented material exhibits high ductility and corrosion resistance acceptable for all medical devices requiring plasticity and ductility exceeding that of conventional magnesium alloys. Many disease complications in adults constrict or block a passage within the body, causing symptoms and wellness deterioration. Although surgical correction is preferred when technically feasible and permitted by the clinical status of patient, stenting is often a reliable alternative. Recent research has indicated that innovative technology platform points to safe and cost-effective biodegradable metallic stents, and will solve the problems caused by existing stents made of permanent materials like silicone, nitinol and polymers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/17/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/17/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1748674</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Prashant</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumta</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pkumta@engr.pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>11/17/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Pittsburgh</Name>
<CityName>Pittsburgh</CityName>
<ZipCode>152132303</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4126247400</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>University Club</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
