<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference: No Boundaries: Groups in Algebra, Geometry, and Topology</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>30000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joanna Kania-Bartoszynska</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The conference titled "No Boundaries: Groups in Algebra, Geometry, and Topology" will be held October 27-29, 2017 at the University of  Chicago. No Boundaries: Groups in Algebra, Geometry, and Topology is a conference that highlights the significant impact of the field of geometric group theory on several related mathematical fields.  The conference also aims to promote further fundamental discoveries in geometric group theory and the related fields.  This conference will expose attendees to the highest caliber of mathematics, presented by some of the field's best expositors. Through the recorded videos, mathematicians at a wide variety of institutions will gain valuable exposure to these ideas. The organizers expect that the conference will serve as inspiration for a new generation of researchers to develop both depth and breadth in their work.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The aims of the conference are to highlight current mathematical advances at the various interfaces of geometric group theory, low-dimensional topology, representation theory, dynamics, number theory, and algebraic geometry; examples include the development of the theory of representation stability and the resolution of many long-standing conjectures in the theory of 3-manifold topology and the theory of mapping class group groups.  There will be plenary lectures by top experts in a variety of related fields. The conference will have several sessions of lightning talks, affording junior researchers a high-profile stage in which to present their results, and ample time to discuss their work with experts during breaks. The conference will also feature a problem session, the output of which will shape the direction of research in these areas for years to come. Ore information can be fund at the conference website&lt;br/&gt;http://people.math.gatech.edu/~dmargalit7/noboundaries/index.shtml</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/16/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/16/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1748107</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dan</FirstName>
<LastName>Margalit</LastName>
<EmailAddress>margalit@math.gatech.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/16/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Georgia Tech Research Corporation</Name>
<CityName>Atlanta</CityName>
<ZipCode>303320420</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4048944819</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Georgia</StateName>
<StateCode>GA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1267</Code>
<Text>TOPOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
