<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Workshop: Mobilizing a Global Science of Learning to Address Future Challenges; Alexandria, VA;  2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>49883</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>SBE Off Of Multidisciplinary Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Soo-Siang Lim</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A primary purpose of this workshop proposal is to leverage the strengths of global scientific communities with substantial expertise in human, animal, neuromorphic, and machine learning. It seeks to leverage NSF investments in Science of Learning to develop a network of US and international researchers who are committed to interdisciplinary and integrative research in the study of learning and its implications for societal challenges in education, technology innovation and workforce preparation. The workshop will purposefully mobilize and engage US and international partners to identify shared interests and needs (expertise, infrastructure/organization) that can create new research opportunities with meaningful international experiences for students and faculty.  Funds will be used for planning and coordination activities to culminate in a consensus building workshop with the following goals: 1) Identify research priorities (and/or associated societal challenges) for which networks of scientists are poised to work together; 2) identify and build a community infrastructure that allows teams to quickly re-configure in response to research and societal challenges/opportunities; 3) identify ways to address learning in the growing divide between societies with and without science and technology resources, while maintaining important cultural features; and 4) Co-convene a International Science of Learning Summit meeting in tandem with the Science of Learning Awardees meeting to identify priorities in training needs and knowledge domains for science of learning.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The successful fostering of a global community in the science of learning enables access to a large expertise base, and accelerated sharing and dissemination of knowledge across a broad spectrum of disciplines.  It builds capacity of interdisciplinary groups to collaborate, and strengthens and builds new partnerships for US researchers to work with international partners.  This in turn, enables greater fluidity and cooperation for student exchange and training in international laboratories</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/25/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1748614</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Andrea</FirstName>
<LastName>Chiba</LastName>
<EmailAddress>chiba@cogsci.ucsd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-San Diego</Name>
<CityName>La Jolla</CityName>
<ZipCode>920930621</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8585344896</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Contract &amp; Grant Admin</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>004y</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>059Z</Code>
<Text>Science of Learning</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
