<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Sustainable Nanotechnology Conference, November 5 - 7, 2017 in Marina del Rey,  California</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>25000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nora Savage</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Sixth Annual Conference of the Sustainable Nanotechnology Organization will be held in November 5 - 8, 2013 in Marina Del Rey, California. The objective of this sixth conference is to bring together scientific experts from academia, industry, and government agencies from around the world to present and discuss current research findings on the subject of sustainability of nanotechnology.  Sustainable development has been defined as the balance of economic success, environmental protection and social responsibility. Sustainable nanotechnology strives to ensure that industrial growth is sustainable while maximizing societal benefits. The current challenge however, is that many existing nanotechnology products are not sustainable due to their dependence on large quantities of energy, water, and materials. In addition to being resource and energy intensive, some existing nanomanufacturing processes utilize non-renewable materials. Also, their impacts on human health are not clearly understood. The conference program will address the critical aspects of sustainable nanotechnology such as life cycle assessment, green synthesis, green energy, environmental and biological fate, economic and societal aspects of nanotechnology, and the overall sustainability of engineered nanomaterials.  In principle, this involves fundamental/applied research on the chemistry of producing new green nanomaterials and the eco-manufacturing processing of nanomaterials and products. The conference will also foster new collaborations between academic and industrial participants. This community of users, researchers and developers of engineered nanomaterials will provide a long-term, scientific assessment of where the science of nanotechnology, its future, and propose activities which academics, government agencies and others can engage in to achieve sustainability goals.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This conference considers two main aspects: how to make nanotechnology more sustainable in terms of its environmental, social and economic implications, and how to use nanotechnology to improve the sustainability of human activities. Of particular interest is the use of nanotechnology to reduce carbon footprint, make energy and water use more efficient, and minimize human impacts. The conference brings together experts from different areas, such as academics, industry, regulators and other interested parties. The output of the conference is made publicly available through publications and press releases. The conference program will address the critical aspects of sustainable nanotechnology such as life cycle assessment, green synthesis, green energy, environmental and biological fate, economic and societal aspects of nanotechnology, and the overall sustainability of engineered nanomaterials.  In principle, this involves fundamental/applied research on the chemistry of producing new green nanomaterials and the eco-manufacturing processing of nanomaterials and products. The conference will also foster new collaborations between academic and industrial participants. This community of users, researchers and developers of engineered nanomaterials will provide a long-term, scientific assessment of where the science of nanotechnology, its future, and propose activities which academics, government agencies and others can engage in to achieve sustainability goals.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/25/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/25/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1748352</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Arturo</FirstName>
<LastName>Keller</LastName>
<EmailAddress>keller@bren.ucsb.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/25/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of California-Santa Barbara</Name>
<CityName>Santa Barbara</CityName>
<ZipCode>931062050</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8058934188</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Research</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7681</Code>
<Text>ENG NNI SPECIAL STUDIES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7237</Code>
<Text>NANO NON-SOLIC SCI &amp; ENG AWD</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
