<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Dense Phases in Neutron Stars</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>85000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bogdan Mihaila</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>With the exception of black holes, neutron stars are the densest objects in the Universe. Inside these objects, exotic particles such as hyperons and deconfined quarks that do not exist in a stable form anywhere else in the universe can be created. This project proposes an in-depth investigation of new kinds of matter inside neutron stars as well as the effects of incredibly strong magnetic fields, many orders of magnitude larger than the one present inside the Sun, on these phases of matter. The results of this research will be used by the astrophysics community to search for clear signals of stable exotic matter in neutrinos bursts and gravitational waves. The project involves the training of high school, undergraduate and graduate students in astrophysics research, and includes a series of seminars open for the community that highlights the role of female astrophysicists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project will pursue an extension of a realistic description of hadronic and quark phases in the core of neutron stars to include magnetic fields together with finite temperature effects. This will enable effects of strong magnetic fields to be studied in different regions of stars, not only for cold neutron stars but also for proto-neutron stars. For the latter case, this project will also study the effects of neutrinos and entropy per particle on the structure of phase transitions. With these ingredients in hand, complete data tables will be built from a realistic equation of state to be used by others in dynamical simulations of supernova explosions, compact binary mergers, and neutron star cooling, to answer a fundamental question in astrophysics: Do exotic degrees of freedom play a role in the above phenomena? Having the first extensive data table built from a single realistic description will be extremely useful and allow for more accurate dynamical calculations of astrophysical phenomena. The students involved in the project will make meaningful contributions to state-of-the-art research. Finally, this project will support a series of seminars open for the community that highlights the role of female astrophysicists.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>06/20/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/20/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1748621</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Veronica</FirstName>
<LastName>Dexheimer</LastName>
<EmailAddress>vdexheim@kent.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>06/20/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Kent State University</Name>
<CityName>KENT</CityName>
<ZipCode>442420001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3306722070</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF THE COMPTROLLER</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1285</Code>
<Text>NUCLEAR THEORY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>069Z</Code>
<Text>Windows on the Universe (WoU)</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
