<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Polar Data Planning Summit: Coordinating International Data Management, Mediation, and Sharing Activities in Support of Polar Observing, Science, Decision-making, and Arctic People</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>49547</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Jennifer Mercer</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Polar Regions are undergoing significant environmental and social change.  Changes in the Arctic in particular have implications for the prosperity, welfare, health, and national security of the United States and all nations. Understanding, adapting to, and possibly benefiting from these changes requires that scientists, governments, Arctic residents, and society as a whole work together to enhance understanding and generate action at scales from local to international. In support of understanding and action, the importance of polar data and its proper management are increasingly being recognized by governments, the science community, and society. The Polar Data Planning Summit will bring together key actors from around the world to contribute to the design and implementation of and integrated and well-defined polar network that enable access to high- quality data, expertise, and information. This will place the United States in a leadership role in developing a data network that will support enhanced scientific understanding, national security, meeting stakeholder needs, and improved agency operations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Polar Data Planning Summit will host more than twenty representatives from key polar data programs and projects from around the world. An international steering committee will work with the local organizing committee to establish and agenda that prioritizes concrete work planning and particularly the coordination of various activities being carried out under different projects. The result will be a collectively developed road map outlining a world-wide system that will provide researchers, Arctic residents, decision makers and others with access to the vast majority of polar data. This will include a coordinated, integrated work plan identifying goals, objectives, and associated existing and emerging funded projects and programs. The outcomes of the Summit will be disseminated at major meetings such as the POLAR 2018/Arctic Observing Summit 2018 meetings in Davos, Switzerland, and the next Arctic Science Ministerial expected in the Fall of 2018.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/14/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>06/08/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1749243</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Maribeth</FirstName>
<LastName>Murray</LastName>
<EmailAddress>msmurray@alaska.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Peter</FirstName>
<LastName>Pulsifer</LastName>
<EmailAddress>pulsifer@nsidc.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Colleen</FirstName>
<LastName>Strawhacker</LastName>
<EmailAddress>colleen.strawhacker@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/14/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate>06/08/2018</EndDate>
<RoleCode>Former Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Colorado at Boulder</Name>
<CityName>Boulder</CityName>
<ZipCode>803031058</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3034926221</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3100 Marine Street, Room 481</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Colorado</StateName>
<StateCode>CO</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5293</Code>
<Text>AON IMPLEMENTATION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1079</Code>
<Text>ARCTIC RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
