<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Doctoral Dissertation Research: Cross-linguistic activation of referential bias in second-language learners of English</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>16902</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Behavioral and Cognitive Sci</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joan Maling</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Bilingualism is the norm in many parts of the world. Understanding how bilingual speakers derive meaning in context is thus not only an interesting research question about how the human mind accommodates the regular use of two or more languages in daily life, but one that has direct implications for applied language professionals, such as interpreters, teachers, and speech-language pathologists working with bilinguals. Previous research has shown that bilinguals' knowledge of one language can affect how they say and interpret words and sentences in the other. This is called cross-linguistic activation. The goal of this dissertation research is to contribute to our understanding of how cross-linguistic activation affects how bilinguals make sense of language in context, that is, beyond understanding individual words and sentences.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The proposed research will provide insight into the effect of cross-linguistic activation at a word level on bilinguals' discourse level processing by investigating how the strength of referential biases associated with Korean predicates affects Korean-English bilinguals' referential processing in English. Verb-based implicit causality (IC) creates biases for who will be mentioned next; e.g., 'John threatened Bill' implies the subject ('John') was the cause of the 'threaten' event, making it the most likely next referent in the discourse. Korean, in addition to IC verbs, has a class of (subject-biased) syntactic causative (SC) constructions, best translated as 'causing X to be Y'. A preliminary study has shown that Korean speakers have stronger referential biases with SC constructions than with regular IC predicates in Korean. This project investigates the extent to which differences in bias strength associated with SC and IC predicates in Korean influence Korean-English bilinguals' offline and online reference processing in English. The project will collect data from Korean-speaking learners of English and native English speakers, using both written sentence completion (Experiment 1) and visual-world eye-tracking (Experiment 2) paradigms. In both experiments, potentially modulating effects of English language proficiency and learning experience on cross-linguistic activation in referential processing will be assessed.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/18/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/18/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1749240</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Hyunwoo</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hyunwoo2@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/18/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Theres</FirstName>
<LastName>Gruter Nell</LastName>
<EmailAddress>theres@hawaii.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/18/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Hawaii</Name>
<CityName>HONOLULU</CityName>
<ZipCode>968222234</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8089567800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2440 Campus Road, Box 368</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Hawaii</StateName>
<StateCode>HI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8374</Code>
<Text>DDRI Linguistics</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1311</Code>
<Text>LINGUISTICS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
