<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Student-Author Travel Grant for the International Conferences on Biomedical and Health Informatics and on Wearable and Implantable Body Sensor Networks 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>19970</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>05020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Computer &amp; Info Scie &amp; Enginr</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Information &amp; Intelligent Systems</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Wendy Nilsen</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project is to support doctoral student travel and participation for student travel support and participation in the doctoral mentoring program at International Conference on Biomedical and Health Informatics is now on its 5th edition, while the annual International Conference on Wearable and Implantable Body Sensor Networks. These collocated conferences provides a supportive scientific forum for students focusing on computing, health informatics and engineering in the area of human health.  The International Conference on Biomedical and Health Informatics and International Conference on Wearable and Implantable Body Sensor Networks will provide a forum for expert and peer critique of students' research with the goal of improving their science. Student participants will also have the opportunity to receive networking support and career advice from internationally-recognized experts. Overall, the travel support brings together students with experts who might not otherwise engage with one another and engage in multidisciplinary groups targeting science the area of human health. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This proposal supports doctoral students by providing a doctoral forum focused on encouraging students to learn from peers and experts from multiple perspectives to understand how innovative computing, informatics, engineering and biomedical science combine to make the most impact in the area of human health. In addition, student participation in a roundtable provided at the conference enables students to explore their science and see different career paths for researchers in this area. The International Conference on Biomedical and Health Informatics and International Conference on Wearable and Implantable Body Sensor Networks conference exposes participants to different scientific disciplinary approaches, supports networking with conference attendees and is designed to support the development of the next generation of scholars in this area and create a bridge between the scientific and health disciplines.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>07/26/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>07/26/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1749562</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Roozbeh</FirstName>
<LastName>Jafari</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rjafari@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/26/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jack</FirstName>
<LastName>Mortazavi</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bobakm@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>07/26/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798477635</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>TEES State Headquarters Bldg.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8018</Code>
<Text>Smart and Connected Health</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
