<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Fabrication of Composite Material Structures using Light-Induced Self Writing</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary M. Toney</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Faculty Early Career Development Program (CAREER) grant will promote the progress of science by contributing new knowledge related to a novel manufacturing process for fabricating composite materials for a variety of applications in the energy, infrastructure, aerospace, chemical and automotive industries. Composite materials are made by combining two or more materials, the combination of which provides enhanced electrical, mechanical, chemical, and/or surface properties. Understanding how to control the processing of composite materials enables customized performance for a broad range of critical applications. There are many manufacturing processes to make composite materials. However, most require multiple process steps and require the use of significant energy and chemicals, both of which are costly and wasteful. This grant supports fundamental research to provide new knowledge about a novel light irradiation process that will enable rapid, scalable, and controllable manufacturing of composite materials made from polymers and ceramics with lower cost and energy usage. This multidisciplinary research integrates manufacturing, chemistry, and materials science and will help broaden the participation of underrepresented groups in research and positively impact engineering education.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The light-induced self-writing of composite material architectures can overcome several limitations of existing manufacturing techniques, such as high cost, high energy usage, multiple steps, and lack of microscale control over morphology. However, some scientific barriers prevent the realization of the full application potential of light-induced self-writing for additive manufacturing of composite material architectures. This research aims to fill the knowledge gap on the processing-structure-property relationship and the microstructure formation mechanisms for self-writing polymer-inorganic composite material architectures. Experiments will be performed to establish relationships between process parameters and composite morphology to test the hypothesis that self-writing can regulate morphology evolution in terms of reaction and diffusion kinetics. A multi-physics model will be developed to simulate morphology formation and predict final structure as a function of process parameters. Application demonstrations will include materials for superhydrophobic surfaces, lithium-ion batteries, and ultra-light mechanical structures. The educational program will focus on secondary education by providing workshops for high school teachers and research experiences for high school students as well as Masters of Education graduate students, with a focus on recruiting from groups underrepresented in STEM.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/16/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/16/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1751621</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
<LastName>Hosein</LastName>
<EmailAddress>idhosein@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/16/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8092</Code>
<Text>Materials Eng. &amp; Processing</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>085E</Code>
<Text>POLYMER &amp; COMPOSITES PROCESSES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8021</Code>
<Text>Materials Engineering</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8025</Code>
<Text>Advanced Materials Processing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8037</Code>
<Text>Advanced Manufacturing</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
