<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>CAREER: Integrated Modeling of Hazard Mitigation Stakeholder Networks for Compassionate, Sustainable Risk Reduction</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>500000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07030000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Civil, Mechanical, &amp; Manufact Inn</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Robin Dillon-Merrill</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This Faculty Early Career Development Program (CAREER) project aims to advance natural hazard mitigation by examining decision-making carried out by local networks of stakeholders involved in risk reduction planning and implementation with the goal to further reduce property losses and social and economic disruptions from disaster events. The study of the interlinked networks of local public and private actors, including the champions who foster and maintain cohesion in the networks that translate knowledge and federal and state policy into action, is critically important, and will support NSF's mission to advance the nation's welfare in this case, following disaster events. This project develops, tests, and refines a new model which explicitly incorporates stakeholders' thoughts and emotions as factors that interact to enhance or constrain hazard mitigation decision-making. Anticipated contributions of the project include an improved process for more effective, sustainable hazard mitigation decision-making at the local level and expansion of a generation of hazard mitigation champions across multiple professional and academic disciplines. The integrated education and research program will foster dissemination of findings widely and cost-effectively, including to historically underrepresented populations.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project involves three research elements to test new hypotheses generated by the networks for compassionate and sustainable hazard mitigation model. Surveys, interviews, document review, multivariate regression modeling, case studies, and in-person observation will be used to apply analytical concepts and techniques from network science to understand local stakeholder decision-making. Testing a novel compassionate systems course for professionals will open new lines of research on analytical and deliberative techniques for identifying and prioritizing mitigation needs, goals, and actions. Interdisciplinary engaged learning modules involving strategically integrated sets of seminars, lecture, conferences, and graduate-level courses, will generate discrete and cumulative education and practical outcomes. Together, these strategically ordered and integrated elements will increase our understanding of the role of local hazard mitigation stakeholder networks and champions in the face of increasing natural hazard risks.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/05/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/05/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1751696</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ward</FirstName>
<LastName>Lyles</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wardlyles@ku.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/05/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Kansas Center for Research Inc</Name>
<CityName>LAWRENCE</CityName>
<ZipCode>660457568</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7858643441</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2385 IRVING HILL RD</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kansas</StateName>
<StateCode>KS</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1638</Code>
<Text>HDBE-Humans, Disasters, and th</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>041E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER REDUCTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>042E</Code>
<Text>HAZARD AND DISASTER RESPONSE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1045</Code>
<Text>CAREER: FACULTY EARLY CAR DEV</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
