<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>An Ethnography of a Brain Interface Device</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>12410</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Frederick M Kronz</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This project will advance our understanding of using technologies of the brain in interpreting the senses.  The project will engage in public participation in discussions regarding the development and use of brain machine interface devices. The study will identify how these technologies are brought to market, and experienced by individual users. It will be of interest to patients, doctors, policy makers, scientists and technology developers. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will bring together social studies of science, the neurosciences and translational medicine to investigate the ways in which brain machine interface (BMI) devices are being developed. It will explore questions about what subjects see when using BMI devices? What does it mean for a BMI device to "work"? The  study will  trace how institutional relationships involved in the production of a BMI device (i.e. the academic military- industrial complex) manifest in individual, perceptual experience. The project will use phenomenological and experimental methods that include computational modeling, psychophysics and behavioral tasks, as well as interviews and ethnography.  By combining institutional ethnography and critical phenomenological methods in the context of the neuroscience the result will contribute to our understanding of the processes of embodiment.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/19/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/19/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1753701</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>S. Lochlann</FirstName>
<LastName>Jain</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lochjain@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/19/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cordelia</FirstName>
<LastName>Erickson-Davis</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cred22@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/19/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
<ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7603</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, TECH &amp; SOCIETY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7567</Code>
<Text>SOC STUDIES OF SCI, ENG &amp; TECH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
