<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Enabling the Circular Economy through Sustainable Manufacturing: International Forum on Sustainable Manufacturing</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>24000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1753557 (Badurdeen). "Enabling the Circular Economy through Sustainable Manufacturing" will be theme for this Forum organized by the Institute for Sustainable Manufacturing (ISM) at the Lexington Convention Center, Lexington, Kentucky. The concept of Circular Economy promotes a restorative approach through regenerative design to concurrently pursue sustained economic growth, environmental protection, and societal wellbeing. Given that manufacturing is an engine of wealth generation in many economies, adopting sustainability practices in manufacturing is imperative to the Circular Economy vision. Sustainable Manufacturing to promote the Circular Economy is only feasible through a total and multi-lifecycle based approach to closed-loop material flow by adopting the 6Rs of Reduce, Reuse, Recycle, Recover, Redesign and Remanufacture. This Forum will bring together experts from academia, industry and government agencies to discuss opportunities and challenges to Enabling the Circular Economy through Sustainable Manufacturing. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The Forum will provide a venue for emerging and early career researchers as well as graduate students engaged in sustainable manufacturing to interact with prominent researchers and industry leaders in sustainable manufacturing. This will facilitate a greater dialogue in related areas and also facilitate increased awareness of others' research to foster more collaboration between different organizations. The dissemination of forum presentations through different channels and scholarly publications will also help increase understanding of how sustainable manufacturing can enable the Circular Economy. The Forum will include an Emerging Researcher Showcase with presentations from early-career researchers, and also a Student Poster Showcase.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1753557</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Fazleena</FirstName>
<LastName>Badurdeen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>badurdeen@engr.uky.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jeffrey</FirstName>
<LastName>Seay</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jeffrey.seay@uky.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Kentucky Research Foundation</Name>
<CityName>Lexington</CityName>
<ZipCode>405260001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8592579420</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>109 Kinkead Hall</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Kentucky</StateName>
<StateCode>KY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
