<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID:  Supporting Cloud Water Collection at Whiteface Mountain Research Observatory, Pilot Study to Assess Chemical Processing of Organics within Clouds</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>24930</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sylvia A. Edgerton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This is a pilot study to investigate the chemistry occurring within clouds that can lead to the formation of secondary organic aerosol in the atmosphere.  It is expected that chemical reactions taking place within fog and cloud droplets are responsible for much of the differences in the predicted and measured mass of atmospheric organic aerosol.  The results of the project will lead to a better understanding of how clouds can affect air quality. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The primary hypothesis of the study is that organic compounds within cloud-processed aerosols will be more soluble as a result of oxidation reactions and that cloud droplet residuals (the aerosols remaining after cloud droplets evaporate) will be higher in organic mass than aerosols being drawn into clouds from below the cloud-base. The results of this study will lead to improved modeling of the heterogeneous chemical processing of organics within clouds.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/18/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>08/18/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1753278</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sara</FirstName>
<LastName>Lance</LastName>
<EmailAddress>smlance@albany.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>08/18/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>SUNY at Albany</Name>
<CityName>Albany</CityName>
<ZipCode>122220100</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5184374550</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1400 WASHINGTON AVE</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1524</Code>
<Text>ATMOSPHERIC CHEMISTRY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
