<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Communication Technologies, Social Tolerance, and Relationship Persistence</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>117999</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>04050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Social, Behav &amp; Economic Scie</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Divn Of Social and Economic Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Joseph Whitmeyer</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Contrary to much current opinion, new communication technologies may facilitate the persistence of social contact and the maintenance of social ties.  In so doing, they may increase exposure to a variety of opinions and backgrounds and thereby increase social cohesion and social tolerance.  Through the everyday use of new technologies, relationships may be less transitory than in the recent past and people may be increasingly aware of diversity within their personal network of relationships. These trends may aid in the diffusion of information and attitudes between individuals and groups that may otherwise be sparsely or infrequently connected.  This project focuses on inter-generational relationships in the context of children departing rural communities for post-secondary education&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goal of this research is to pre-test the design and measures for a longitudinal study into how the use of new communication technologies is related to the stability and durability of people?s relationships, and how awareness of acquaintances? activities might influence social tolerance. Rural communities and the life course transition of a child leaving the community for post-secondary education provides a unique context in which to study these effects.  Children who leave for post-secondary education gain experience and diversity, but often do not return to their rural communities. Individuals experience a loss of intergenerational contact, and the rural community does not benefit from the children?s experience. This research uses a mixed methods approach, a survey administered over the internet and by telephone of a sample of first-generation students from rural communities and at least one of their parents or guardians, and a series of interviews with rural households. The survey and interviews will collect information on a variety of processes related to persistence and awareness, including variation in technology use, relational maintenance, social support, and cross-generational contact.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/08/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/08/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1754863</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Keith</FirstName>
<LastName>Hampton</LastName>
<EmailAddress>khampton@msu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Michigan State University</Name>
<CityName>East Lansing</CityName>
<ZipCode>488242600</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5173555040</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>Office of Sponsored Programs</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Michigan</StateName>
<StateCode>MI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1331</Code>
<Text>SOCIOLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9179</Code>
<Text>GRADUATE INVOLVEMENT</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
