<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SG:  The roles of plant resource strategy, pathogens and mycorrhizal fungi in plant invasions- a belowground test of the Resource-Enemy Release Hypothesis</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>200000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08010208</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Environmental Biology</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Betsy Von Holle</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Some introduced plants are aggressive and fast-spreading, and can be harmful to both natural ecosystems and society by interfering with crops, wildlife, and native species of conservation concern. Despite their large economic impact, it remains unclear why some introduced plants become invasive and others do not. One possibility involves how plants interact with soil fungi. Most plants have beneficial fungi associated with their roots, which are vital for nutrient uptake. However, the roots of plants are also often attacked by harmful fungi. This project aims to uncover how the interactions between beneficial and harmful root-associated fungi influence the success of non-native plants relative to native plants. This project will provide research training for undergraduate students including both laboratory and greenhouse methods. Additionally, the researchers will engage in outreach to K-12 students, as well as the public, to inform them about invasive species and plant-fungal interactions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This project will examine the linkages between soil fungal communities and plant resource strategy within the context of the Resource Enemy Release Hypothesis, which predicts that nonnative species that have escaped their natural enemies in a new range will have relatively higher productivity as compared to native species, and that this advantage increases with resource availability. This research will test whether plant-fungal relationships differ systematically between fast and slow-growing species, using a well-studied Eastern North American invasive shrub system. Additionally, the research team will test whether differences in plant-fungal relations depend on a plant's co-evolutionary history with soil fungi, or alternatively, whether differences in plant-fungal relations apparent in invasive species are due to their overall bias toward fast growth. Multiple native and invasive plants, representing congeneric pairs with a range of plant growth characteristics, will be included in the study to control for phylogeny. In the greenhouse, plants will be subjected to two complementary inoculation experiments to test the relationship between each plant and its soil microbial community, and to test the mycorrhizal responsiveness of each species. DNA sequencing will then be used to characterize the response of root-associated fungal communities to differential conditioning by plant hosts, with emphasis on pathogen and mycorrhizal communities in greenhouse and natural field settings.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/03/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/03/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1754182</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Louis</FirstName>
<LastName>Lamit</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ljlamit@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/03/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jason</FirstName>
<LastName>Fridley</LastName>
<EmailAddress>fridley@syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/03/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Douglas</FirstName>
<LastName>Frank</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dafrank@mailbox.syr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/03/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Syracuse University</Name>
<CityName>SYRACUSE</CityName>
<ZipCode>132441200</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3154432807</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>OFFICE OF SPONSORED PROGRAMS</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>New York</StateName>
<StateCode>NY</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1182</Code>
<Text>POP &amp; COMMUNITY ECOL PROG</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
