<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>STEM at the Poles: Teachers and Researchers Exploring and Collaborating</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>377622</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office of Polar Programs (OPP)</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Elizabeth Rom</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The Arctic Research Consortium of the U.S. (ARCUS) will administer and implement, "Teachers and Researchers Exploring and Collaborating (PolarTREC)", a program that selects U.S. teachers and informal educators and prepares them to participate in cutting-edge field research with polar scientists in various, and often remote, locations in the Arctic and Antarctica. Through hands-on field experiences, participating teachers (pre-service and in-service) and informal educators will improve teaching strategies, develop resources for their careers, and change how they teach STEM in the classroom and to the public. The project's goal is to invigorate polar science education and understanding by bringing educators and polar researchers together in professional collaboration. By integrating research and education, PolarTREC will help sustain and grow the considerable scientific and public enthusiasm for polar research and education. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Twelve teachers or informal educators will be  recruited, selected, and matched with polar researchers. ARCUS will maintain a website for dissemination of information about the expeditions, provide orientation training for the teachers that includes field safety and communication training, provide travel support for the teachers to meet with scientists prior to deployments and for them to join the scientific expeditions in the field. Participants in the TRE will not only increase their knowledge of polar science and effective teaching practices, but also will develop long-term collaborative professional relationships with polar researchers and become part of an ever-growing educator network.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>04/13/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>04/13/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1754290</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Rich</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bob@arcus.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Janet</FirstName>
<LastName>Warburton</LastName>
<EmailAddress>warburton@arcus.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>04/13/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Arctic Research Consortium of the U.S.</Name>
<CityName>Fairbanks</CityName>
<ZipCode>997093710</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9074741600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3535 College Road, Suite 101</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Alaska</StateName>
<StateCode>AK</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>017Y</Code>
<Text>Polar Special Initiatives</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
