<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Mathematical Modeling in Environmental, Biological and Other Sciences</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>101360</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Matthias Gobbert</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Mathematical Modeling in Environmental, Biological and Other Sciences (MMEBS) Program is an eight-week research experience for undergraduate students hosted by Bethune-Cookman University (B-CU). The Program recruits heavily from underrepresented minorities (URMs), women, and those individuals with limited STEM and research opportunities in their home institutions. The Program faculty has extensive experiences in mentoring these types of students, in helping them develop research projects, and in guiding these research projects. The overall objectives of this REU Site are to promote early engagement of undergraduate students in research, to expose students to interdisciplinary modeling and data analytic resources, to foster active learning through hands-on experiences in a collaborative research environment, and to inspire students to pursue advanced STEM education and research careers. The Program also fosters long-term mentoring relationships between participating students and faculty through intensive collaboration and interaction. The Program looks for at least 80% of URM participants to increase diversity in future STEM workforce.&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;With mathematical modeling as the main precept, a multidisciplinary team of science, mathematics, and computer science faculty will provide to participating students research-learning experiences in the data analytic aspects of multiple scientific disciplines including mathematics, chemistry, computer science, biological and environmental sciences. Instructions include introduction to modeling; data analytic software training; LaTeX document preparation training; research paper writing and poster design; Excel modeling (spreadsheet modeling) tutorial; and working on cutting-edge research projects in different areas on mathematics, biology, chemistry, environmental science and computer science. Students will work in groups. Students and faculty will be encouraged to continue their work during the year and submit their research papers to professional journals. Students are also encouraged to present their work at conferences throughout the year. Participants and involved faculty will stay connected to form research and professional networks that will remain after the Program. The participants will be well prepared for graduate studies in STEM fields and various careers that will have positive impact on our society.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/14/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/14/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1755561</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Seenith</FirstName>
<LastName>Sivasundaram</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sivasundarams@cookman.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yungkul</FirstName>
<LastName>Kim</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kimy@cookman.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/14/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Bethune-Cookman University</Name>
<CityName>Daytona Beach</CityName>
<ZipCode>321143012</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3864812547</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>640 Mary McLeod Bethune Blvd.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1594</Code>
<Text>HIST BLACK COLLEGES AND UNIV</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7335</Code>
<Text>WORKFORCE IN THE MATHEMAT SCI</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
