<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Support for the Workshop on Meteorological Sensitivity Analysis and Data Assimilation; Aveiro, Portugal; July 2-6, 2018</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>12/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>10000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>06020100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Geosciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Atmospheric &amp; Geospace Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Nicholas F. Anderson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award is for travel support for 5-6 researchers from the U.S. to participate in an international workshop titled: "Meteorological Sensitivity Analysis and Data Assimilation," to be held in Aveiro, Portugal from July 2-6, 2018.  Presentations will include a mix of tutorials on fundamentals, overview talks on recent development paths, posters or short seminars on new findings, and some formal debates.  Students will have an opportunity to present their work.  The workshop will be held at a self-contained facility at which all participants will share meals and evening discussions, providing many opportunities for dialogue with and between experts to make maximum use of time.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Data assimilation lies at the heart of numerical weather prediction that, in turn, lies at the heart of weather forecasting.  Much of the improved accuracy of weather forecasts during the past decade is due to improvements in the accuracy of estimates of the current weather that data assimilation provides.  Implicit or explicit sensitivity analysis is a key component of both data assimilation and weather forecasting, since it links uncertainties of predictions with uncertainties of initial condition or observations.  Both data assimilation and sensitivity analysis are computationally intensive, complex, multidisciplinary subjects.  In order to expedite progress in these studies and their applications, it is necessary to establish proper foundations and to perform robust evaluations for all scientific claims.  These are the primary aims of the workshop, with its principal societal impact being the further improvement of weather analysis and forecasting.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/08/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/08/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1755331</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ronald</FirstName>
<LastName>Errico</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ronald.errico@morgan.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Nikki</FirstName>
<LastName>Prive</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nikki.prive@morgan.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/08/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Morgan State University</Name>
<CityName>Baltimore</CityName>
<ZipCode>212510002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>4438853200</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1700 East Cold Spring Lane</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1525</Code>
<Text>PHYSICAL &amp; DYNAMIC METEOROLOGY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
