<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Research In Neutrino Astrophysics at the University of Wisconsin-River Falls</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>44578</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen V. McCloud</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award supports the Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) site in neutrino astrophysics at the University of Wisconsin-River Falls (UWRF).  Six undergraduate students per year will participate in ten months of summer research on projects with the IceCube Neutrino Observatory or South Pole neutron monitors.  Students will be integrated into a research collaboration that opened the field of neutrino astronomy, and work in a department where learning and involving undergraduates in research are priorities. Students will acquire a broad range of research skills, will appreciate the value of fundamental science to society, and will be mentored on giving effective scientific presentations and in communicating science.  To broaden dissemination to enhance scientific and technological understanding they will also be expected to give a presentation on their summer work, and participate in outreach activates, including presentations at the UWRF Upward Bound program. Benefits to society will occur when REU students apply the skills they acquire in computer programming, data mining and simulations to their STEM area of interest in their respective careers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Students will choose from research topics including neutrino astrophysics, cosmic rays, particle physics, and neutron monitor physics. Students will make contributions to the IceCube experiment that will help advance understanding and knowledge in the field of neutrino astronomy.  IceCube is a unique telescope located at the South Pole which looks at the universe via neutrinos. Some students will work on projects involving the South Pole neutron monitors. These monitors observe low energy cosmic rays and monitor solar activity. With access to IceCube's data or data from the South Pole monitors, high performance computing resources, and personnel, students will make real contributions while acquiring research skills that are transferrable to many fields of science, technology, and engineering.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/09/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/09/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1757517</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>James</FirstName>
<LastName>Madsen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>james.madsen@uwrf.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/09/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Surujhdeo</FirstName>
<LastName>Seunarine</LastName>
<EmailAddress>surujhdeo.seunarine@uwrf.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/09/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Wisconsin-River Falls</Name>
<CityName>River Falls</CityName>
<ZipCode>540225013</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7154253195</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>410 South 3rd Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Wisconsin</StateName>
<StateCode>WI</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>9134</Code>
<Text>Integrative Activities in Phys</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>SMET</Code>
<Text>SCIENCE, MATH, ENG &amp; TECH EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
