<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: New approaches to engineering cells, tissues, and organs</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>354811</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07050000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Engineering Education and Centers</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Mary Poats</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The goal of this Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Site is to advance the training and to increase the diversity of the next generation of researchers and regulatory engineers and scientists. Ten participants annually will pursue independent research to advance fundamental science in cellular and tissue engineering while developing new technologies, including 3D printing and miniaturized biological organ systems.  Participants will also gain valuable training through workshops in the relevant technical skills, as well as lab notebook skills, technical writing and figure design, the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) approval process, and the responsible conduct of research. In addition, leveraging a partnership between the University of Maryland and the FDA undergraduate researchers will have the opportunity to contribute to the science of regulating the translatable outcomes of fundamental research in cell and tissue engineering. Thus, this REU site not only enriches future engineers and scientists, it also emphasizes the development of the next generation regulatory engineer and scientist.  &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;In this REU site, mentored undergraduate researchers will investigate innovative approaches to engineer cells, tissues, and organs.  Projects include organ-on-a-chip (including blood-brain-barrier, gut, kidney, lymph node), cancer cell microenvironment on a chip, biomanufacturing-on-a-chip, and 3D-printed tissue engineering constructs.  Investigations into each of these topics will add to the fundamental knowledge in cell and tissue engineering while advancing the engineering techniques of 3D printed biological systems and organ-on-a-chip systems.  Furthermore, by inspecting fundamental bioengineering questions through the lens of the FDA, the investigations will enhance the field of regulatory science. Advances in molecular-, cellular-, and tissue-based therapies present significant challenges for regulation and commercialization; a well-trained workforce with perspectives on technology advances, ethical issues, and health safety will be critical to the proper translation of these technologies.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>01/24/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>01/24/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1757745</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Ian</FirstName>
<LastName>White</LastName>
<EmailAddress>ianwhite@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/24/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kimberly</FirstName>
<LastName>Stroka</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kstroka@umd.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>01/24/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Maryland College Park</Name>
<CityName>COLLEGE PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>207425141</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3014056269</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3112 LEE BLDG 7809 Regents Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Maryland</StateName>
<StateCode>MD</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1360</Code>
<Text>HUMAN RESOURCES DEVELOPMENT</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>116E</Code>
<Text>RESEARCH EXP FOR UNDERGRADS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
