<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>REU Site: Physics at Miami University</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>09/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>355531</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Physics</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Kathleen V. McCloud</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award funds the Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) site in physics at the Miami University Oxford Campus.  Ten students will be supported for ten weeks of summer research each year in topics from biophysics, optics and quantum optics/quantum information, condensed matter physics, and physics education research.  The goals of the site are to provide (i) mentored research opportunities for a diverse group of students; (ii) professional development topics; (iii) interactions with other students and faculty on a professional and social level. The overarching goal is to promote physics as a professional choice and send more talented students to graduate school in STEM fields.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Student mentoring will take place on multiple levels. REU students work in groups with one or two undergraduate students and a Masters level graduate student. Working groups will meet regularly with the mentors and discuss progress, or solve problems encountered.  The site will enhance the research and professional skills of the participants and the students will meet on a regular basis to discuss professional development topics. Through these activities, the site is training the next generation of physicists.This site is supported by the Department of Defense in partnership with the NSF REU program.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/08/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/08/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1757575</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Herbert</FirstName>
<LastName>Jaeger</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jaegerh@MiamiOH.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Jennifer</FirstName>
<LastName>Blue</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bluejm@miamioh.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/08/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Miami University</Name>
<CityName>Oxford</CityName>
<ZipCode>450563653</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5135293600</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>500 E High Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Ohio</StateName>
<StateCode>OH</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>R141</Code>
<Text/>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7736</Code>
<Text>DOD ASSURE PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9250</Code>
<Text>RES EXPER FOR UNDERGRADS-SITE</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
