<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: In-cloud Destination-driven Distributed Denial of Service Filtering</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anita J. LaSalle</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to improve security by providing the strongest levels of network destination control with minimum deployment requirements. This project addresses the problem of Distributed Denial-of-Service (DDoS) attacks on the Internet, which have been used in recent years to silence a variety of organizations, including companies, governments, and non-profits. The proposed mechanism defends against such DDoS attacks, and can improve Internet availability for a variety of customers. Bringing a DDoS-prevention mechanism to market prevents attackers from silencing and denying service to their targets, enabling increased availability to deployments of such systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project explores the commercial potential for a cloud-based traffic filtering technology.  The technology combines two significant, but distinct, approaches to Distributed Denial-of-Service (DDoS) prevention - commercial approaches that perform in-cloud filtering to remove the most obvious DDoS traffic, and academic approaches that perform in-network filtering based on protocol-specific fairness criteria. The technology explored combines the in-cloud filtering of existing commercial approaches, together with a mechanism called "capabilities" in the academic approaches, to create an in-cloud, destination-driven enforcement of per-flow bandwidth allocations. This destination-driven approach can enforce a wide variety of destination-specified policies with a single mechanism, and each destination can choose the traffic that it wishes to prioritize. As a result, the same mechanism can to be used to defend against DDoS attacks and to provide priority to certain traffic.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/01/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/01/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1758179</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yih-Chun</FirstName>
<LastName>Hu</LastName>
<EmailAddress>yihchun@uiuc.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>11/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign</Name>
<CityName>CHAMPAIGN</CityName>
<ZipCode>618207473</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2173332187</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>SUITE A</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Illinois</StateName>
<StateCode>IL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
