<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Fast Formation Cycling Methods and In-Situ Diagnostics for Lithium-Ion Battery Manufacturing</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>726267</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project will be in promoting clean energy technologies. More than half of the United States? greenhouse gas emissions come from transportation and electricity production. Lithium-ion batteries are a promising technology to facilitate the adoption of electric vehicles and renewable power generation that drastically reduce greenhouse gas emission. However, the high cost of lithium-ion batteries threatens the commercial viability of clean technologies. This Phase II project will develop manufacturing process technologies that reduce the capital and operating costs of the most expensive step in lithium-ion battery manufacturing. Low-cost batteries will push electric vehicles towards widespread commercial adoption. Electrification of mass-transit buses will improve urban air quality, especially for the low-income population located near bus depots. Large-scale battery systems enabled by low-cost batteries will turn renewable power generation such as solar and wind from periodic energy sources into on-demand energy sources to alleviate our dependence on fossil-fuels. This Phase II project will help lithium-ion batteries become a key technology in the successful departure from oil dependence, combat of climate change, and the United States? energy security.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase 2 project addresses the need for deeper understanding of the fundamental science behind the solid electrolyte interphase (SEI) layer. SEI layer quality is a key determinant of long-term battery reliability, performance, and safety, but the underlying electrochemistry that governs SEI composition and evolution remains poorly understood. This Phase II project will develop novel, in-situ diagnostics to directly measure the evolution, performance, and characteristics of the SEI layer as it is formed during lithium-ion battery manufacturing. Deeper insight into the complex morphology of the SEI layer will advance much-needed industry knowledge of battery performance, quality, and longevity. Additionally, there is a sizeable body of work in modeling the degradation of batteries throughout their lifecycle. With improved cell-level traceability, the manufacturing insights enabled by this Phase II project will expand the current understanding of the ?ideal battery? at the beginning of life and complement ongoing work on how batteries degrade over time. This insight opens the door for quality control in battery manufacturing based on more direct quality metrics such as longevity and reliability rather than indirect metrics such as beginning of life capacity.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/06/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/06/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1758531</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Eric</FirstName>
<LastName>Din</LastName>
<EmailAddress>eric.l.din@gmail.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/06/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Hive Battery Inc</Name>
<CityName>SEATTLE</CityName>
<ZipCode>981192795</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7086209310</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>1631 15TH AVE W</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4080</Code>
<Text>ADVANCED COMP RESEARCH PROGRAM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
