<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Cultivating STEM Teaching Identity in Noyce Teacher Scholars</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>03/15/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>02/28/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>842267</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Karen Keene</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Cultivating STEM Teaching Identity in Noyce Teacher Scholars is a Noyce Track 1 project at California State University San Marcos (CSUSM). The project will encourage highly qualified mathematics and science students to pursue secondary teaching careers at high-need schools.  The project team includes the CSUSM School of Education and College of Science and Mathematics, Palomar and MiraCosta Community Colleges, and Vista Unified, Escondido Union High School, and San Marcos Unified school districts. The project aims to recruit 40 CSUSM mathematics and science undergraduates to the CSUSM teaching credential program, which includes acquisition of an Authorization to Teach English Learners. In addition to scholarships, the project will offer early STEM teaching experiences to Noyce Scholars, as well as provide them with early career mentoring.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Noyce Track project includes a focus on developing a teaching community using Wenger's Community of Practice Framework and will implement evidence-based approaches such as internships and induction activities and will leverage existing activities and partnerships.  The program will also build on model programs implemented at CSUSM by the PIs. The embedded training on teaching English Language Learners has important value, as area schools have a high enrollment of ELL students. Additionally, the project will include efforts to recruit scholars from partnering community colleges, with an emphasis on recruitment of underrepresented minorities. The models implemented for faculty teamwork, collaboration with community colleges, and partnerships with school districts have the potential to provide insights for teacher preparation efforts at other institutions.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/20/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/20/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1758492</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Paul</FirstName>
<LastName>Jasien</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jasien@csusm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/20/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Charles</FirstName>
<LastName>De Leone</LastName>
<EmailAddress>cdeleone@csusm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/20/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Rong-Ji</FirstName>
<LastName>Chen</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rchen@csusm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/20/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Linda</FirstName>
<LastName>Holt</LastName>
<EmailAddress>linda holt@csusm.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/20/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>University Auxiliary and Research Services Corporation</Name>
<CityName>San Marcos</CityName>
<ZipCode>920784362</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7607504700</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>435 East Carmel Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
