<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Collaboration to Improve STEM Teacher Recruitment and Preparation</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>05/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>04/30/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>718503</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>11040100</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Education and Human Resources</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Undergraduate Education</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Sandra Richardson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Collaboration to Improve STEM Teacher Recruitment and Preparation is a Robert Noyce Track I Scholarships and Stipends project at Southern University of New Orleans. The project aims to recruit, retain, and certify 22 highly qualified minority biology and mathematics secondary teachers. These undergraduate biology and mathematics majors and postbaccalaureate STEM professionals will complete the project prepared to teach in high-need schools in Louisiana's Jefferson Parish School District. STEM teacher training efforts in the project have the potential to enhance student learning and lead to better employment opportunities and job stability in Louisiana, translating to STEM education excellence in the state. Project results will impact over 17,000 students in the partnering school district.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The goals of this project are to 1) certify 22 secondary mathematics and biology teachers to serve in high-need schools and 2) provide early professional support for long-term success in the teaching field. Project activities will include: i) intensive recruitment of future STEM teachers from a pool of STEM undergraduate students and STEM professionals; ii) early field experiences for prospective teachers in high-need schools; iii) an on-campus seminar series on Characteristics of Highly Effective STEM Teachers; iv) Praxis I and II teacher certification exam preparations; v) development of a STEM teaching lab; vi) post-certification mentoring of scholars by the project's leadership team and secondary mentor teachers; and vii) research investigations on the effects of summer training and enrichment on the motivation of STEM majors. Customized content and pedagogy courses, unique field experiences, and internship opportunities at Brookhaven National Lab will serve as project resources in the project's development of well-rounded, well-prepared secondary mathematics and biology teachers.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/28/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/28/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1758321</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Cynthia</FirstName>
<LastName>Singleton</LastName>
<EmailAddress>csinglet@suno.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/28/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Murty</FirstName>
<LastName>Kambhampati</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mkambham@suno.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/28/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joe</FirstName>
<LastName>Omojola</LastName>
<EmailAddress>jomojola@suno.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/28/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Louise</FirstName>
<LastName>Kaltenbaugh</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lkaltenbaugh@suno.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/28/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Southern University New Orleans</Name>
<CityName>New Orleans</CityName>
<ZipCode>701260002</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5042865311</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>6400 Press Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Louisiana</StateName>
<StateCode>LA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1795</Code>
<Text>ROBERT NOYCE SCHOLARSHIP PGM</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9178</Code>
<Text>UNDERGRADUATE EDUCATION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
