<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Autonomous Seismic-Controlling System</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>01/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anita J. LaSalle</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is to advance the paradigm and constructability of building automation systems that improve earthquake-resilience of high-rise structures. The project can potentially improve citizen's safety by standardizing a smart seismic-controlling system for new high-rise developments to be placed in growing dense cities within highly-active seismic zones. By constructing buildings with modular seismic technology, the current expenses and risks of the real estate developer associated with the design and construction of these special structures in these locations can also be eliminated. Furthermore, expenses linked to catastrophic structural failures and on-going structural and non-structural repair can be prevented because of the autonomous and responsive nature of this project.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project frames a building automation system that control hazardous oscillations in high-rise buildings by mimicking the human FAP-behavior to manage its body postural balance after its quiet stance is disturbed. The proposed resilient performance of autonomous seismic control allows a minimization of structural and non-structural damage to the susceptible architecture by counteracting the loads in real-time. Our previous experiments with human participants subjected to lateral loads, and our past research on earthquake-resilient robotic structures for buildings has proven reliability of the technology to minimize the fundamental period of free vibration of a high-rise building threatened by major seismic motion. This I-Corps project can move the construction industry forward by challenging the motionless-based structural performance of current buildings.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/15/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/15/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1758196</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Wilfredo</FirstName>
<LastName>Mendez-Vazquez</LastName>
<EmailAddress>wilfredo_mendez@pucpr.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/15/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pontifical Catholic University of Puerto Rico</Name>
<CityName>Ponce</CityName>
<ZipCode>007179997</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>7878412000</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>2250 Blvd. Luis A. Ferre-Aguayo</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Puerto Rico</StateName>
<StateCode>PR</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>9150</Code>
<Text>EXP PROG TO STIM COMP RES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
