<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>SBIR Phase II:  Passive Radio for the Internet of Things</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>02/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>01/31/2020</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>749996</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Muralidharan S. Nair</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this project is to develop low-power, low-cost and small&lt;br/&gt;form factor wireless connectivity solutions, facilitating the deployment of inexpensive and long-lived&lt;br/&gt;wireless sensors and devices for a diverse set of applications. For instance, it is infeasible to place&lt;br/&gt;conventional sensors or wireless connectivity on low-cost or disposable items due to the high cost and&lt;br/&gt;short battery life of wireless communication devices. With the successful completion of this project,&lt;br/&gt;items ranging from consumer packaged goods to medical consumables and pill bottles could be&lt;br/&gt;connected to the Internet. Brands and manufacturers could gain previously inaccessible market and&lt;br/&gt;product insights based on the way products are used, while consumers could enjoy benefits ranging&lt;br/&gt;from new services and features (such as automated product reordering) to better-designed products&lt;br/&gt;which more closely fit their needs. By enabling new use cases for wireless connectivity, this technology&lt;br/&gt;can prompt innovation across many industries.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This Small Business Innovation Research (SBIR) Phase II project introduces a new long-range&lt;br/&gt;backscatter-based communication technology based on Chirp Spread Spectrum, a wireless protocol&lt;br/&gt;which can be detected at extremely low signal levels. The low-power wireless system prior to this&lt;br/&gt;project is comprised of three elements: A passive backscatter-based radio, a first gateway device which&lt;br/&gt;provides an illumination signal, and a second gateway device which receives the resulting&lt;br/&gt;backscattered data and forwards data to the Internet. In this project, the passive backscatter-based&lt;br/&gt;radio will be implemented in an integrated circuit form, realizing the low power and low cost possible&lt;br/&gt;with this technology. The two gateway devices will be combined into one full-duplex radio device, to&lt;br/&gt;address the needs of the majority of deployment scenarios. Techniques to localize the backscatter&lt;br/&gt;radios within the field of the gateway device will be explored. Finally, security challenges will be&lt;br/&gt;addressed and the system will undergo extensive evaluation and testing.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>02/06/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>02/06/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1758699</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Aaron</FirstName>
<LastName>Parks</LastName>
<EmailAddress>nsfsbir2@jeevawireless.com</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>02/06/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>JEEVA WIRELESS INC</Name>
<CityName>Seattle</CityName>
<ZipCode>981950001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>2062146177</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>4000 Mason Road Ste 300</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Washington</StateName>
<StateCode>WA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>4096</Code>
<Text>COMMUNICATIONS RESEARCH</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>5373</Code>
<Text>SMALL BUSINESS PHASE II</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8034</Code>
<Text>Hardware Components</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>8035</Code>
<Text>Hardware Devices</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>HPCC</Code>
<Text>HIGH PERFORMANCE COMPUTING &amp; COMM</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
