<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Collaborative Research: Enhance the Resilience of Water Infrastructure in Mid-sized Cities Adjacent to Energy Industry</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/15/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>59366</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07020000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Chem, Bioeng, Env, &amp; Transp Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bruce K. Hamilton</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>1759542 (Lou)/1760673 (Reible). At the heart of U.S. energy and chemical processing industry, Hurricane Harvey caused multiple chemical spills/explosions, flooding of superfund sites, and even the flooding of a primary pump station, which draws river water to a drinking water treatment plant (WTP). If the source water is contaminated by hazardous chemicals released from multiple sources, compounded by the failure of a WTP, public health, and also productivity of the local industry will be severely threatened. This study will address drinking water safety issues under threats of the release of hazardous chemicals during major natural disasters, and identify strategies to improve infrastructure resilience in mid-sized cities. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This research will obtain extremely valuable data relating to the drinking water quality and the release to transport of hazardous chemicals caused by Harvey. The investigation will provide answers to the following critical questions: 1) What kind of hazardous chemicals in an energy production region have the highest risk to be released and contaminate source water under major natural disasters? 2) What are their distribution, fate and transport patterns from the source point to WTP intake spots? 3) What strategies should be taken to enhance the resilience of the drinking water system in mid-sized coastal cities adjacent to energy industry? The research results will provide communities a better understanding of the risks and how to manage them. The contingency plan can be applied to small and mid-sized cities, which often have limited resources and few alternatives. The strategies identified will enhance the integrity of urban infrastructure, as well as the normal production of industrial activities.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/12/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/12/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1760673</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Danny</FirstName>
<LastName>Reible</LastName>
<EmailAddress>danny.reible@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kayleigh</FirstName>
<LastName>Millerick</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kayleigh.millerick@ttu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/12/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas Tech University</Name>
<CityName>Lubbock</CityName>
<ZipCode>794091035</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8067423884</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>349 Administration Bldg</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>071Y</Code>
<Text>Hurricane Harvey 2017</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>7643</Code>
<Text>ENVIRONMENTAL SUSTAINABILITY</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
