<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID: Powering through the hurricane: self-organizing power electronics intelligence at the network edge</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>10/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>09/30/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>60000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07010000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Electrical, Commun &amp; Cyber Sys</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anthony Kuh</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Summary&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;As Texas experiences the strongest hurricane in more than 50 years, communities are working tirelessly to rebuild homes and infrastructure. As the lifeblood of modern civil society, electricity has not been fully restored in many neighborhoods because of the long repair time for the bulk power infrastructure.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This RAPID project aims at collecting data of electricity needs in areas affected by Hurricane Harvey, and developing fast reconfigurable power electronics intelligence at the network edge (PINE). The objective is to enable end users to quickly restore prioritized electric loads during the recovery phase. The approach is to integrate distributed energy resources that are readily available, as well as to endow the distribution grid with edge-based power electronics control, so as to provide local communities with at least the critical portion of their electricity needs.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Intellectual Merit:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The intellectual merit of this project is three-fold. First, this project will quickly collect data about the shortage of power in communities affected by Hurricane Harvey. Second, based on the data, energy-constrained microgrid scheduling will be formulated and computed in a distributed manner. Third, the power-limiting control of power electronics interface at the end user level will be designed and tested.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Broader Impacts:&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;Approximately 45% of the Texas A&amp;M main campus and 100% of Texas A&amp;M Galveston campus students were affected by the Hurricane Harvey. This project provides direct benefits to the students and their families in this rebuilding phase. This project also provides relief to many remote areas which may have to wait for weeks or even months before the full restoration of the bulk power infrastructure. This team will actively participate in this state-wide Rebuild Texas Initiative. The research results will be disseminated through publication and lecture&lt;br/&gt;notes, which can benefit many other communities that are subject to the risk of natural disasters.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>09/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1760554</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Prasad</FirstName>
<LastName>Enjeti</LastName>
<EmailAddress>enjeti@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Le</FirstName>
<LastName>Xie</LastName>
<EmailAddress>le.xie@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Panganamala</FirstName>
<LastName>Kumar</LastName>
<EmailAddress>prk@tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>09/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798477635</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>TEES State Headquarters Bldg.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>071Y</Code>
<Text>Hurricane Harvey 2017</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
