<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>I-Corps: Low-complexity Asynchronous Re-sampler for Optical Coherence Tomography</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>08/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>50000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>07070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Directorate For Engineering</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Industrial Innovation &amp; Partnersh</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Anita J. LaSalle</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The broader impact/commercial potential of this I-Corps project is based on significant improvements in accuracy and cost reduction of eye-related disease diagnosis by providing a high-quality, high-speed tissue imaging solution. Specifically, the project will shorten clinical scan time, and as a result, increase image resolution while reducing the number of required patient clinic visits. These improvements directly lower associated medical costs. The project goal is to create a new-generation of Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT), a technique that is used in the clinical practice to provide cross-sectional images of the retina.  Currently, the biggest challenge faced by OCT clinical applications is their slow scan speed, which leads to low image resolutions and therefore unsatisfying clinical experience. A high-quality, high-speed signal processing tool is needed for reliable clinical decision-making and disease monitoring with OCT systems.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This I-Corps project will further develop a new-generation of Optical Coherence Tomography (OCT).  The I-Corps project will explore the commercial potential of the innovation, a system capable of decreasing the signal processing time of swept source OCT (SS-OCT) devices by up to ten times according to lab tests. This device is based on a family of novel signal processing algorithms that significantly improve the accuracy and speed required for the medical images to be acquired. The SS-OCT platform will be enhanced in terms of the image acquisition speed, accuracy, and cost. This, in turn, will decrease the number of visits a patient needs to make to an ophthalmology clinic while increasing the overall clinic capacity to attend visiting patients per day, generating more revenue for those centers.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>11/01/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>11/01/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1760126</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Sebastian</FirstName>
<LastName>Hoyos</LastName>
<EmailAddress>hoyos@ece.tamu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>11/01/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas A&amp;M Engineering Experiment Station</Name>
<CityName>College Station</CityName>
<ZipCode>778454645</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>9798477635</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>TEES State Headquarters Bldg.</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>8023</Code>
<Text>I-Corps</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
