<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Chemistry Early Career Investigator Workshop</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>70498</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Michelle Bushey</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>Newer faculty often find the process of writing their first grant proposals to be quite challenging. Professors Matthew Whited of Carlton College and Gordana Dukovic of the University of Colorado are organizing a workshop that seeks to provide new faculty with insight about proposal writing and reviewing processes.  The workshop also seeks to position newer faculty to write more competitive proposals to federal funding agencies. Participants have the opportunity to network with successful grant recipients and program officers. They engage in mock panels, speed coaching sessions, and other activities designed to provide them with a better understanding of how to put together a research plan that is ambitious, yet realistic. Broader impact criteria is also discussed in terms of educational activities, outreach, and applications to societal problems. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The workshop, supported by the Division of Chemistry, is entitled, "Chemistry Early Career Investigator Workshop," will be held on March 26-27, 2018 in Alexandria, Virginia. This workshop will bring together 100 junior faculty from a broad range of institutions and demographics to discuss steps in strategically crafting research ideas, planning educational and outreach activities, and assessing and evaluating project aims. Potential participants can access more information (as it becomes available) at: http://go.carleton.edu/nsf2018 In addition an email address is also available: CHE-2018career@carleton.edu.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/27/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/27/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1762479</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Gordana</FirstName>
<LastName>Dukovic</LastName>
<EmailAddress>gordana.dukovic@colorado.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Matthew</FirstName>
<LastName>Whited</LastName>
<EmailAddress>mwhited@carleton.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/27/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Carleton College</Name>
<CityName>Northfield</CityName>
<ZipCode>550574001</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5072224303</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>One North College Street</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Minnesota</StateName>
<StateCode>MN</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1978</Code>
<Text>PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1978</Code>
<Text>PROJECTS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
