<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>RAPID:  Rescuing a living stocks collection damaged by Hurricane Irma</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>11/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>10/31/2018</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>45139</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>08080000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Biological Sciences</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Div Of Biological Infrastructure</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Reed Beaman</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>A Rapid Response Research (RAPID) award is made to the Montgomery Botanical Center (MBC) to rescue 109 imperiled living stocks impacted by Hurricane Irma, which caused extensive damage to living plant collections.  Initial rapid triage identified 109 living stocks that can be saved if acted upon quickly. The condition of these 109 stocks has been stabilized, and this project will enable these trees to be re-set and cared for during initial recovery.  Numerous NSF-supported research projects make use of the MBC living stocks in various disciplines including systematics, physiology, ecology, paleontology.  These stocks are also used in structural biology, genomics, and pollination biology studies. The collections being rescued by this project include plants of high scientific value which have extensive provenance data, prior research use, or exceptional rarity.  Some of these living stocks represent the only examples held in collections, and in one case, an example of a species thought to be extinct in the wild.  Living collections at MBC form the basis of MBC's outreach and educational programming, reaching students at every level from pre-K through Graduate School levels. Montgomery's formal and informal links with three nearby colleges, Miami-Dade College, Florida International University, and University of Miami, allow these living stocks to reach some of the most diverse student communities in the US.  Internships at MBC incorporate collections management to help emphasize the importance of such collections for advancing science.  In addition, active research on collections management by MBC and its collaborators leads to improved practice for botanic gardens and other living collections.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The project involves the initial righting and staking 109 palms which were felled by Hurricane Irma, and are in danger of desiccation and loss. Initial work involves clearing debris to allow access to these specimens.  Righting the largest of these specimens will require a tree crane and backhoe working in tandem, along with a support crew to stake, backfill and water these while the crane is holding the trunk in place.  The remaining palms will be righted using smaller equipment in tandem with the backhoe and support staff.  After righting and staking, the stocks will require consistent management for pests and pathogens in during their re-establishment phase.  This includes regular screening for pathogens, health monitoring, and collections management record keeping.  Undergraduate research assistants in agroecology and horticulture will be recruited to assist with all of these skilled tasks, working directly with the curatorial staff of MBC.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>10/20/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>10/20/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1762781</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>M. Patrick</FirstName>
<LastName>Griffith</LastName>
<EmailAddress>patrick@montgomerybotanical.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Joanna</FirstName>
<LastName>Tucker Lima</LastName>
<EmailAddress>joannat@montgomerybotanical.org</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>10/20/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Montgomery Botanical Center</Name>
<CityName>Miami</CityName>
<ZipCode>331564242</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>3056673800</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>11901 Old Cutler Road</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Florida</StateName>
<StateCode>FL</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1197</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH COLLECTION</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>1197</Code>
<Text>BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH COLLECTION</Text>
</ProgramReference>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7914</Code>
<Text>RAPID</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
