<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Spin Functionality in Perovskite Stannates Through Complex Oxide Heteroepitaxy</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>07/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>06/30/2021</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>140000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Continuing grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03070000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Materials Research</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Lynnette D. Madsen</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>NON-TECHNICAL DESCRIPTION: Semiconductor materials have formed the foundation of microelectronic devices that drive a wide range of technologies, including information technology, energy applications and national security.  In an effort to improve energy efficiency and performance of existing microelectronics, semiconductors with strong magnetic responses, or ferromagnetic semiconductors, have been recognized as a possible alternative to current non-magnetic semiconductors. This project addresses the challenge of identifying and developing a new class of ferromagnetic semiconductors to enable improvements in energy efficiency and performance. One class of promising ferromagnetic semiconductors is based on a class of oxide thin films based on Sn, known as perovskite stannates. The research involves the design, synthesis, and characterization of stannate thin films with strong magnetic response. Additional research activities include the training of undergraduate and graduate researchers, including underrepresented minorities, who are likely to find future employment in the information technology sector. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;TECHNICAL DETAILS: This integrated research and education program is focused on the development of a new class of spin-polarized semiconductors in epitaxial stannate oxide thin films through incorporation of magnetic dopants. Research activities include unique approaches to magnetic doping, including incorporating concentrations of magnetic dopants beyond the solubility limits at thermal equilibrium and co-doping on both types of cation sites. This research is timely as it exploits the recent development of high mobility epitaxial stannate films and it may provide an avenue to a room temperature ferromagnetic semiconductor that could make spin-based semiconductor electronics a reality and may revolutionize the microelectronics industry. Education aspects of this project include the training of undergraduate and graduate students, and the development of an apprenticeship and modular materials physics curricular program for local high school students.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>03/22/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>03/22/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1762971</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Yuri</FirstName>
<LastName>Suzuki</LastName>
<EmailAddress>yurisuzuki@stanford.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>03/22/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Stanford University</Name>
<CityName>Palo Alto</CityName>
<ZipCode>943041212</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>6507232300</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>3160 Porter Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>California</StateName>
<StateCode>CA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1774</Code>
<Text>CERAMICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
</Award>
</rootTag>
