<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>NSF INCLUDES DDLP - ACCEYSS: Association of Collaborative Communities Equipping Youth for STEM Success</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>12/01/2017</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>11/30/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>299536</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>01060400</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Office Of The Director</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Office of Integrative Activities</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Bernice T. Anderson</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>The ACCEYSS (Association of Collaborative Communities Equipping Youth for STEM Success) Network and Model project, an NSF INCLUDES Design and Development Launch Pilot, at Texas State University is forming a university-community partnership between interdisciplinary researchers (ACCEYSS research team), faith leaders and other community partners to implement an innovative model that prepares underrepresented and underserved youth to pursue undergraduate science, technology, engineering, and mathematics (STEM) degrees. The inaugural ACCEYSS network will include Texas State University, San Marcos Consolidated Independent School District, San Marcos Youth Service Bureau, City of San Marcos-Office of the City Manager, Hays County Youth Initiative, the Calaboose African American History Museum, and several local faith-based organizations.  Many historic advancements have been made through the efforts and activities of faith and community leaders uniquely poised to motivate and galvanize community-based action. A collaboration among these academic institutions, social/cultural organizations, and faith partners to work with the families and youth of underrepresented/underserved populations will be an essential asset for generating new perspectives and ideas for improving STEM academic and career outcomes related to broadening participation in the scientific enterprise. &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;During this launch pilot, the ACCEYSS research team and network will collaborate to design and develop the ACCEYSS model as a culturally-relevant, blended-learning strategy that integrates online and in-person STEM enrichment activities (e.g., summer institute, afterschool clubs) that are aligned with the Science and Engineering Practices and Disciplinary Core Ideas Dimensions of the K-12 Next Generation Science Education Standards. The collective impact framework will be used to build diverse capacity, leverage asset-based community development, and sustain mutually reinforcing non-exclusive policies and practices for STEM diversity and inclusion. Additionally, in this launch pilot, a multifaceted design-based research approach will be utilized to support middle and high school students' interest in and pursuit of STEM studies.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>12/06/2017</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>12/06/2017</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1764404</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Kristy</FirstName>
<LastName>Daniel</LastName>
<EmailAddress>kristydaniel@txstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dana</FirstName>
<LastName>Garcia</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dg08@txstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Shetay</FirstName>
<LastName>Ashford</LastName>
<EmailAddress>sa1137@txstate.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>12/06/2017</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Texas State University - San Marcos</Name>
<CityName>San Marcos</CityName>
<ZipCode>786664616</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>5122452314</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>601 University Drive</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Texas</StateName>
<StateCode>TX</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>032Y</Code>
<Text>NSF INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>029Z</Code>
<Text>Launch Pilots INCLUDES</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
