<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle>Conference on Hyperbolic Problems</AwardTitle>
<AwardEffectiveDate>06/01/2018</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>05/31/2019</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardAmount>27000</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03040000</Code>
<Directorate>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<LongName>Division Of Mathematical Sciences</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Victor Roytburd</SignBlockName>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration>This award provides support for graduate students and junior researchers to attend the "XVII International Conference on Hyperbolic Problems: Theory, Numerics, and Applications" (HYP2018) held at the Pennsylvania State University, University Park on June 25-29, 2018. The conference highlights recent advances in the fundamental theory of hyperbolic partial differential equations, as well as related mathematical models that have experienced sustained activity and exciting recent progress. Hyperbolic problems are ubiquitous in modern science and engineering, ranging from the mathematical theory of fluids, to collective motion of animals (such as flocks of birds), to traffic and pedestrian flow. The meeting is expected to have considerable impact on future developments of applied mathematics in academia, industry, and national Labs in the United States. The conference website can be found at http://www.hyp2018.psu.edu/&lt;br/&gt; &lt;br/&gt;One of the conference's objectives is to bring together researchers, students, and practitioners with interest in the theoretical, computational, and applied aspects of differential equations of hyperbolic type. HYP2018 is the seventeenth meeting in a biennial series with varying venues, whose last United States meeting (the twelfth) was held in 2008. The conference series is unique in its emphasis on encouraging interdisciplinary collaborations that involve sophisticated mathematics applied to challenging problems of great contemporary interest. Among the topics highlighted at the conference are: the mathematical theory of fluids, with new engineering, medical, and biological applications; hyperbolic equations on networks, with a variety of applications, most notably to traffic flow on a network of roads; kinetic and fluid models for collective dynamics of many-body systems; transport equations, with particular focus on optimality and mixing; the equations of general relativity; and control problems for hyperbolic partial differential equations and differential games. The list of plenary and invited speakers includes leading world experts in these scientific areas. Special panel sessions will be devoted to framing open problems to attract the attention of junior scientists in the audience.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.</AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>05/21/2018</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>05/21/2018</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<AwardID>1764156</AwardID>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Anna</FirstName>
<LastName>Mazzucato</LastName>
<EmailAddress>alm24@psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/21/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Dehua</FirstName>
<LastName>Wang</LastName>
<EmailAddress>dwang@math.pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/21/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Marta</FirstName>
<LastName>Lewicka</LastName>
<EmailAddress>lewicka@pitt.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/21/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Robert</FirstName>
<LastName>Kunz</LastName>
<EmailAddress>rfk102@engr.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/21/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Co-Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Investigator>
<FirstName>Alberto</FirstName>
<LastName>Bressan</LastName>
<EmailAddress>bressan@math.psu.edu</EmailAddress>
<StartDate>05/21/2018</StartDate>
<EndDate/>
<RoleCode>Principal Investigator</RoleCode>
</Investigator>
<Institution>
<Name>Pennsylvania State Univ University Park</Name>
<CityName>UNIVERSITY PARK</CityName>
<ZipCode>168027000</ZipCode>
<PhoneNumber>8148651372</PhoneNumber>
<StreetAddress>110 Technology Center Building</StreetAddress>
<CountryName>United States</CountryName>
<StateName>Pennsylvania</StateName>
<StateCode>PA</StateCode>
</Institution>
<ProgramElement>
<Code>1266</Code>
<Text>APPLIED MATHEMATICS</Text>
</ProgramElement>
<ProgramReference>
<Code>7556</Code>
<Text>CONFERENCE AND WORKSHOPS</Text>
</ProgramReference>
</Award>
</rootTag>
